In the year of 1722,
the Kangxi Emperor of the Qing Dynasty passed away.
Nian Gengyao, Governor-General of Chuan-Shan,
and Longkodo, Commander of the Nine Gates,
both played a role in the struggle over imperial succession
and were key to helping the Fourth Prince, Yinzhen, ascend to the throne.
Accordingly, the new Emperor held them in high esteem
and granted them unequaled political power.
They soon became central figures in the new government.
THE YONGZHENG EMPEROR
All kneel!
Lotus blossoms spring up on every side. They bloom and wither, time after time,
just as the concubines of the palace.
"Each year and every year, the blossoms return anew.
Each year and every year, the bloom of youth does not."
After the Yongzheng Emperor ascended the throne,
he accomplished many great feats.
However, he did not have many sons.
Concerned that there would not be enough male heirs to secure the throne,
the Empress Dowager held auditions
to fill the Imperial Harem every three years.
Every girl wished to be selected,
so that her whole family could rise up through her success.
But I didn't hope for that.
My only wish was
"to capture the heart of my fated lover
and cling together till our hair turns gray."
However, much changes over time.
No one could expect what would happen at the audition.
As a pious girl, I am not allowed great achievements like men,
but neither am I willing to discard my own life.
If I must marry someone,
only the finest of men will be my choice.
I will marry him and remain by his side as long as I live.
May Buddha grant me this blessing,
let me be passed over for service in the Imperial Harem.
ZHEN HUAN
SHANGSHAN TEMPLE
My lady, all other girls want to be chosen.
Only you wish to be passed over.
LIUZHU – HUANBI
The Buddha will surely remember your prayers.
Don't say it aloud or it will not come true.
WEN SHICHU
Is today a festival day? Even Doctor Wen has come to the temple.
- Shichu. - Huan.
I just checked up on your family.
Your mother told me you'd come here to offer incense.
Simply for a stroll and to pass an idle hour.
Huan, don't try to hide it from me.
I know you've been worried about the audition for many days.
I may only do what I'm allowed. The rest I leave to fate.
Huan, when my father lived, he often said,
"A jade vessel is the symbol of a pure heart."
He wanted me to give this to my future–
It is my own wish as well.
If you accept this, you won't be called to the audition.
In the time of the Shunzhi Emperor, it was decreed
that girls qualified to join the harem may not marry before the audition.
Though you intend to help, you need not give me such a valuable item.
I'm profoundly flattered.
Huan, I'm merely an imperial doctor with the means of a humble official,
but I promise to cherish you for as long as I live,
to love you, protect you and place you above all else.
Although you may find my words imprudent,
I truly hope you are passed over at the audition.
My father was once implicated due to strife in the harem.
He was unable to preserve his good name.
If this can befall even an imperial doctor,
then a concubine will not be spared.
I understand your concern.
But if I don't take part now, my sister Yurao must do so eventually.
My parents have no sons.
I have no choice but to perform my filial duty.
- Mei. - Huan.
SHEN MEIZHUANG
I heard you were summoned but hadn't had a chance to greet you.
I had hoped for the opposite.
Now you have a residence here in the capital
and no longer live with your grandparents.
- Now we may visit one another often. - Absolutely.
I often remember with fondness the bond we shared growing up together.
You dressed quite plainly today.
Even so, the observant will notice your true beauty.
It cannot be hidden.
THE EMPRESS DOWAGER
Xia Ruhua, daughter of the Magistrate of Jiaxing County, is passed over.
Bestow the flower.
What family are you from?
How can you pour hot tea on me? You must be punished!
- I'm sorry. - Answer me! Who is your father?
AN LINGRONG
My name is An Lingrong. My father–
My father is An Bihuai, Deputy Magistrate of Songyang County.
I knew you were from a humble family of the provinces.
I, Lingrong, am at fault. Please forgive me.
XIA DONGCHUN
I may forgive you,
but you must first bow down and beg for my forgiveness.
Only then will I show clemency, this once.
On your knees.
It's only a dress.
I know you are kind and generous. You mustn't be angered by trifles.
Who are you?
My father is Zhen Yuandao, Deputy Chief of the Grand Court of Review.
Deputy Chief of the Grand Court is not a high-ranking office.
Rank is of no importance. Justice is all that matters.
They now audition the Han Army of the Eight Banners.
Your behavior may disturb His Majesty.
If His Majesty vents his wrath, there is no way for us to make amends.
It will also tarnish the reputation of the Han Banners.
Such behavior does more harm than good. I hope you think twice.
- Are you all right? - Thank you for intervening.
I will never forget your kindness as long as I live.
Think nothing of it.
How do you dare act so brashly even within the Imperial Palace?
- And you are– - This is Meizhuang.
Please accept my greetings, Meizhuang.
No need to be so courteous.
"The clothing completes the person."
It's true everywhere in the world without exception.
You dressed simply but elegantly. No wonder they looked down on you.
I give you these earrings as a gift to commemorate our first meeting.
No, no.
May your wishes come true and may you enjoy the fruits of success.
I thank you for your generosity,
but I was born into a humble family.
I may not be able to repay your kindness.
"Birth is much but breeding is more."
You're a beauty. Do not begrudge yourself that.
An Lingrong, daughter of An Bihuai, Deputy Magistrate of Songyang County.
Age, sixteen.
An Lingrong bows in respect before His Majesty and the Empress Dowager.
May blessings and peace be with you.
You are passed over. Bestow the flower.
I'm grateful to Your Majesty and the Empress Dowager.
May Your Majesty and Your Highness enjoy health and happiness forever.
Others showed displeasure when they were passed over,
but your response was filled with courtesy.
Being allowed to meet Your Majesty and Your Highness
is the highest honor indeed.
The begonia in your hair is quite elegant.
Queen Mother, no need to bestow a flower, since she already wears one in her hair.
An Lingrong is selected. Bestow the sachet.
That one.
Xia Dongchun, daughter of Xia Wei, Captain of the Imperial Guard.
Age, eighteen.
Her name is intriguing. She is selected.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Shen Meizhuang, daughter of Shen Zishan, Colonel of Jizhou Garrison.
Age, seventeen.
Shen Meizhuang bows in respect before His Majesty and the Empress Dowager.
May Your Majesty enjoy long life and blessings.
May Your Highness enjoy good health and peace.
Have you read any books?
I am slow and can barely read, only Rules for Women and Advice for Women.
Most girls have only mastered the arts of sewing and embroidery.
It is truly impressive that you are able to read.
I thank Your Majesty and Your Highness.
Write down her name.
Shen Meizhuang is selected. Bestow the sachet.
Zhen Huan, daughter of Zhen Yuandao, Deputy Chief of the Grand Court of Review.
Age, seventeen.
Zhen Huan bows in respect before His Majesty and the Empress Dowager.
May blessings and peace be with you.
Zhen Huan, with which character do you write the name "Huan"?
"Huan huan" once described the slim waist of the concubines of the Chu palace.
It's from a poem by Cai Shen.
Yes, sir.
You are versed in poetry and literature. Zhen Yuandao raised his daughter well.
I only wonder if you're a match for such an auspicious name.
Lift your head.
Come forward.
Fairly decent.
"Beauties of slim waist in the Chu palace are quite graceful and charming.
But their youth and beauty will fade away with the years."
The Forbidden City is a nourishing place.
Your youth and beauty will never fade.
Those who would stay must leave,
and those who would leave must stay forever.
Many girls dream of being selected for the harem. Do not be sad.
Besides, we've both been selected. We can take care of each other.
Mei, it was truly not my wish to be selected.
Yes, but it is heaven's wish.
You will not be granted an ordinary life when you can live an extraordinary one.
Congratulations, Your Majesty.
Several fine beauties will be added to the harem.
Among the ordinary ones, it's pleasing that one or two are acceptable.
More than acceptable.
I've heard Shen Zishan's daughter quite resembles the young Concubine Jing.
THE EMPRESS
And Zhen is practically identical to–
She's somewhat similar around the eyes.
Somewhat similar is already quite enough.
Please forgive my curiosity.
But which rank will you grant to Zhen?
Sixth rank, First Attendant. We will call her "Wan."
CONSORT HUA
First Attendant Wan?
Yes, my lady. Daughter of Zhen Yuandao, Deputy Chief of the Grand Court.
Among the newly selected concubines,
she was the only one given an honorific name, but her rank is not high.
The one who made a display of her eloquence at the audition?
Yes, my lady. Exactly.
Was it His Majesty's decision to allot Chengqian Palace to her?
His Majesty wasn't involved. It was decided by the Empress.
Chengqian Palace is a wondrous place.
Not only spacious and magnificent, but also near His Majesty's Yangxin Hall.
The Empress always knows how to please His Majesty.
She will do anything to curry favor with His Majesty.
ZHOU NINGHAI – SONGZHI
Is there another palace available?
Yes, there is. Suiyu Pavilion, where Lady Fang used to reside.
It is clean and exquisite,
but it's a bit remote, a bit distant, and a bit small.
Besides, it's considered unpropitious.
Unpropitious?
Just because Lady Fang was sent to the Cold Palace after miscarriage?
I see no reason for such taboos.
Your Highness,
Consort Hua has changed the residence of Attendant Wan to Suiyu Pavilion.
I pity her.
Consort Hua is domineering. She decided without even asking your view.
JIANQIU
It's not the first time you've met Consort Hua. She has always acted so.
But His Majesty loves her exactly as she is.
Another strand of gray hair.
I bow to Your Majesty. May good fortune be with you.
Where is Consort Hua? Why didn't she come to greet me?
Your Majesty, my lady was indisposed today.
She went to bed early.
In that case, I'll leave.
I must meet with Consort Qi and the Third Prince.
Leave now, and you'll never again pass through the gates of Yikun Palace.
Hypocrite. You grow even more capricious.
Your Majesty hasn't called on me for a while.
I assumed you had forgotten me.
You're the only one
who dares behave so recklessly in my presence.
So fragrant.
Your Majesty grants Huanyi Incense to me exclusively and I use it every day.
Yes, I truly love the fragrance.
The others don't have it.
FANGRUO
Bow to the young mistresses. May good fortune be with you.
- This is– - The side door to Shunzhen Gate.
Concubines must enter the palace by going through the side door.
Only the Empress is allowed to enter through the main gate.
Mei.
Young mistress, now is not the time to converse.
The eunuchs will lead you to your residences.
It's getting late.
The Imperial Household Department has delivered your belongings to your palaces.
Young mistresses, please enter the palace.
It seems so deserted.
It's not deserted. It's peaceful and quiet.
Good, our young mistress loves peace and quiet.
Kang Luhai, lead eunuch of Suiyu Pavilion, bows in respect before Attendant Wan.
KANG LUHAI
May you enjoy happiness and good fortune.
Cui Jinxi, lead maid of Suiyu Pavilion, bows in respect before Attendant Wan.
CUI JINXI
May good fortune be with you.
Please rise.
- Yes, mistress. - Thank you, First Attendant.
From now on, you are all my servants.
I expect each of you to do your part.
Loyalty should always come first.
Yes, mistress.
Will you remember that?
We promise to be loyal to you without a second thought.
Rewards.
We are at your service.
Young mistress, you must be tired. Please rest.
YANXI PALACE
I'm flattered. The Empress sent you to bring the gifts personally.
It's an honor.
Think nothing of it. Now I must excuse myself.
Farewell then.
I'll see myself out.
You come from a humble family. No wonder others treat you poorly.
Such meager gifts. You have my sympathies.
Gifts from Consort Hua can't compare to those from the Empress.
Make a dress from the fabric the Empress gave us right away.
I'll wear it to the first official audience
with the Empress to show my gratitude.
Yes, mistress.
BAOJUAN
She always acts like this. Who can bear it?
SUIYU PAVILION
I now live in Xianfu Palace.
The palace mistress is Concubine Jing. She is kind and accommodating.
And for you?
As for me,
Lady Fucha doesn't seem overbearing.
But First Attendant Xia–
I'll just ignore her.
I'll only talk with you two.
By the way, you didn't bring any private servants with you.
Have the imperial maids served you well?
Baojuan is smart, she's a reliable one.
The other two young maids are only fifteen.
I don't expect much from them.
But it's fine, I'm used to a simple life. It doesn't matter at all.
Jinxi.
Yes, mistress.
Go tell the Empress
that I'm sending Juqing to Yanxi Palace to serve Attendant An instead.
Yes, mistress.
Juqing may be young, but she is loyal and reliable.
You may take her with you when you return.
If you need anything else, just feel free to ask me or Mei.
Thank you.
I just received some satin today, and I think it'll suit you well.
I'll ask Caiyue to take it to Yanxi Palace.
You two treat me so kindly. It's more than I can return.
What you have done for me is greatly appreciated.
The three of us entered the palace together,
and we know each other very well.
Of course we should take care of each other.
JIANG FUHAI
All young mistresses must perform the formal salutation to the Empress.
Your Highness the Empress, may blessings and peace be with you.
You may rise.
Thank you, Your Highness.
Please also greet the other concubines.
All young mistresses must bow in respect before Consort Hua.
May blessings and peace be with you, my lady.
You may rise.
Thank you, my lady.
I hear that Attendant Xia is quite clever.
May blessings and peace be with you, my lady.
I'm a First Attendant from the Xia family.
Attendant Xia dresses very well.
Your dress is made from expensive material, isn't it?
It was a gift from Her Highness the Empress.
I specifically chose this dress for today's audience.
I see that you know how to show gratitude, you are kindhearted.
Rise.
Thank you, my lady.
Which ones are Lady Shen and Attendant Wan?
I am Lady Shen of Xianfu Palace. I bow in respect before Consort Hua.
I'm Zhen Huan of Suiyu Pavilion. I bow in respect before Consort Hua.
Lady Shen is quite elegant and graceful.
Attendant Wan has dressed a little plainly,
but her beauty cannot be concealed.
His Majesty has a keen eye for spotting a true beauty.
Each of these is outstanding.
All right, rise.
Thank you, Consort Hua.
My lady, you are the true beauty of the nation, drawing all attention.
Your radiance is superior to ours. We dare not compete with the Consort.
Your words are sweet indeed.
But the phrase "beauty of the nation,"
isn't that reserved for the Empress?
Her Highness the Empress glows as bright as the moon.
Consort Hua's beauty sparkles like a shining pearl.
We are not capable of being compared with you.
I see there are more and more clever tongues in the Imperial Harem.
You two really do have clever tongues.
After pleasing the Empress, you start flattering Consort Hua.
You put on a show before everyone to curry favor with both sides.
Truly admirable.
I bow in respect before Attendant Xia.
You've both asked your servants to carry so many gifts.
Do you have enough room to keep them?
We intend to share all the imperial favors we've received.
I planned to send some to your residences after returning to my palace.
But since we've met here,
please pick out whatever you like.
Attendant Xia, please choose first.
My family's residence is already filled with such decorations.
But surely Lady Shen will bestow some small charity on you.
It seems she's quite good at catering to others.
How was someone like her selected? There's not a bit of good in her.
The Xia family is not even on a par with the servants of the Nian family.
Look at her dress.
She thinks she can swagger around because of the Empress' support.
On the day of the audition, I accidentally offended you.
I haven't stopped thinking about my mistake, and I am sorry for it.
Since you're from a military family,
you are surely endowed with civil and martial virtues.
As I expected, you're truly resolute and brave.
You will surely bring honor to your family's name.
That's exactly how I was brought up.
Such stupidity actually exists in the world.
But she was granted the rank of First Attendant.
Yes, my lady.
You're a concubine, just like her. You cannot hit her.
Let go of me!
May blessings and peace be with you, Consort Hua.
Consort Hua.
Zhou Ninghai, let her go.
In early fall, the Imperial Garden is as beautiful as a picture,
but the magnificent prospect is tainted by someone.
What a disappointment.
Second Attendant An tried to insult me.
I just wanted to teach her a lesson.
That's all.
Are the Empress and I no longer present?
I didn't know that Attendant Xia had been put in charge of the harem,
taking on the duty of instructing the others.
I'm afraid you're not qualified to take up this responsibility.
The red hue of the maple isn't very striking this year.
They say the maple turns brilliant red if dyed with a little blood.
Is that true?
Then I will award Attendant Xia the Scarlet Red
so that we may add some red color to the maples with her blood.
The Scarlet Red?
Young mistress, the Scarlet Red is a kind of punishment in the harem.
A beating with a wooden board that is two cun thick and six chi long,
until bone and tendon are broken, and the flesh is badly lacerated.
From a distance, you will see a patch of vibrant red, a most beautiful color.
For that reason, it is called the Scarlet Red.
Young mistress, please come with me.
Consort Hua, spare me!
Spare me!
Now, take her to the Office of Punishment.
Consort Hua, spare me!
Consort Hua!
Xia disrespected her superiors and acted in a reckless manner.
You may very well be startled.
However, though you may not have violated any rules,
it was you three who stirred up this whole incident.
Shut yourselves away and reflect on your mistakes.
I was scared to death.
Xia was stupid and arrogant, but her punishment was excessive.
I knew that Consort Hua was formidable, but never imagined to this extent.
Consort Hua ordered us to reflect on our mistakes.
Just to reflect on our mistakes. No need to be afraid.
What's the matter?
What happened?
Young mistress, I was on my shift.
I went to check the water level in each well of the Imperial Garden.
As soon as I arrived, I saw that the well–
I will go see for myself.
Fuzi?
How did a maid fall into a well?
I don't know.
The place is quite remote, people seldom pass by.
Of course you wouldn't know.
It was I who appointed Fuzi to serve Consort Hua.
Rise.
I have one more item to report.
Speak.
Consort Hua has punished Attendant Xia with the Scarlet Red.
Xia was irritating. She deserved it.
I'm terribly sorry for Fuzi. She died for nothing.
She was a mere serving girl.
What connections does Fuzi have?
Am I not allowed to scold her?
She is just a humble servant. She doesn't have any connections.
I see.
The other day, she hurt me in clumsiness while combing my hair.
I scolded her for it.
She cried out and ran away. She hasn't come back ever since.
I thought that was how the Empress disciplined her servants.
My lady, Fuzi is dead.
Dead?
How did she die?
When did it happen?
Her body was just pulled from the well. It was badly swollen.
It was surely the day you scolded her. She cried and ran off afterwards.
She was careless and fell in the well. Right, Jiang Fuhai?
My lady, I dare not speak.
Why not?
Eunuch,
are you implying that someone pushed her from behind?
- I wouldn't dare. - No matter!
If you won't take my word, you may investigate all my servants.
My lady, you exaggerate.
Let's speak plainly.
I'm sure you came here today by order of the Empress.
You've asked your questions, I've answered, and I have witnesses, too.
You may take them with you if you wish.
Otherwise, if you come to me with this matter again,
I will absolutely crush you.
My lady, I'll excuse myself now.
Idiot! How careless!
All of you must remember.
Fuzi ran off by her own choice, slipped into the well and drowned.
Yes, sir.
Young mistress, you've had a severe shock.
I saw something I shouldn't have.
Then you must find a way to forget it.
That day we met outside the palace, you made me a promise. Is it still valid?
Of course. I'll always place you above all else.
I'm at your command.
I refuse to serve His Majesty in bed.
It is against my wishes as well.
But since you're already here, it is only a matter of time.
For the sake of your future, it should happen as soon as possible.
But I'm really scared. If I serve His Majesty at this time–
I know I am not destined to spend the rest of my life with you,
but keeping you from harm for the rest of your life
is another way to keep my promise.
Since you want good repose to make a full recovery,
I'll prepare a special prescription
which will restore you to health in some time.
Your Majesty, please select a concubine.
Where's the name board for Attendant Wan?
Your Majesty,
the Imperial Medical Bureau reported this afternoon
that Attendant Wan suffered a shock which has led her to fall ill.
She needs isolation and rest.
Suffered a shock?
Consort Hua's servant Fuzi fell into the well for unknown reasons.
Attendant Wan saw the dead body by accident.
Consort Hua.
LADY SHEN
Congratulations, Lady Shen.
His Majesty has chosen you to serve him in bed.
Among the newly selected concubines,
you're the first to win His Majesty's favor.
But I–
This is Madam Liu, who is in charge of the imperial bedchamber.
Young mistress, she will tell you all the rules.
Shortly after, the Imperial Favor Carriage will arrive to take you to Yangxin Hall.
SU PEISHENG
Your Majesty, Lady Shen has arrived.
Carry her in.
Your Majesty.
Attendant Wan is as pretty as a flower, but she's also as timid as a mouse.
As she lacks resolve, her beauty is vain and useless.
CONSORT QI
She saw that bloody scene when she was new here. Of course she's scared.
You should know very well how arrogant Consort Hua has become.
On the day she came to visit me,
even though you're the Third Prince's mother,
you greeted her before she greeted you.
Your Highness, the Third Prince is not His Majesty's favorite.
And His Majesty isn't fond of me.
I'm growing old.
But Consort Hua is young and pretty. She also has the Nian family behind her.
My own First Prince and the late Empress's Second Prince both died young.
Now the Third Prince is the eldest son.
You have higher status than Consort Hua. She has not given birth to a child.
What you say may be true,
but His Majesty doesn't like the Third Prince.
If His Majesty doesn't like him, then you should try to change his mind.
Even you show such weakness.
No wonder the Third Prince failed to make progress.
Do these flowers please you?
I passed by the greenhouse yesterday, and saw they had come into full bloom.
So I had them sent to you.
I like them very much. Thank you, Your Majesty.
I see. There are chrysanthemums embroidered on your dress.
Why are you so fond of them?
"They would rather die on the branch retaining their scent
than be scattered on the cold wind."
I love them because they have integrity.
They do have integrity.
I like them because they're the only flowers that bloom in fall.
They do not wish to compete with the others.
Only when you can endure loneliness, may you enjoy happiness forever.
I've learned from His Majesty.
Changxi Hall. The name sounds like the study hall of an old scholar.
Since you favor chrysanthemums, let's rename it Cunju Hall.
My lady, look at those chrysanthemums.
Never in my life have I seen green chrysanthemums.
They're quite special indeed.
Look, the greenhouse workers are in such a hurry.
I bet they're delivering them to our palace.
Since they're gifts for me, then tell them to stop.
- Let us have a look first. - Yes, my lady.
Come here.
I greet Consort Hua.
It's due to your efforts that we may see such rare flowers.
Just put them here.
Consort Hua, these chrysanthemums–
Speak.
They are to be taken to Cunju Hall.
Then carry out your orders.
Please forgive me, Consort Hua.
Please forgive me, my lady.
Slap yourself.
It's my fault. It's all my fault.
Master, Attendant Wan has been ill two months and isn't recovering.
XIAO YINZI
Two days ago, I heard Doctor Wen say she'll need more time to recover.
Her beauty may have been ravaged by the sickness.
She cannot serve His Majesty.
That's why we've become the lowest among all the servants.
We should not bury our future and die with her.
Master, please lead us.
We can't serve you any longer, young mistress.
What happened? Just tell me.
The Imperial Household Department just informed me
that Concubine Li of Qixiang Palace has requested for me to serve her.
I see.
Concubine Li is a kind mistress. You're fortunate to have this chance.
Huanbi.
- Summon everyone. - Yes, mistress.
I've been ill for nearly two months.
Commotion is not good for my recovery.
And I don't need so many servants to serve me.
So I ask you.
If anyone desires to go,
he may receive a final payment from Huanbi and simply leave.
Let us congratulate Eunuch Kang and Eunuch Yin.
They've been requested by Concubine Li.
They will leave as soon as they've packed.
I'm just a servant. I had no choice.
A fine excuse. I don't believe you're being forced to go.
Your words conceal your true intent.
Liuzhu.
Eunuch Kang has served with true loyalty. He will do the same for any mistress.
Huanbi, give him the payment.
Eunuch Kang, farewell.
Eunuch Yin, here you are.
If you are as loyal as your master, Kang, you'll have a bright future indeed.
Thank you, young mistress.
Anyone who wishes may go with them. Today we still have some money to pay out.
After today,
Attendant Wan will report to the Empress, and you'll end up in hard labor.
You must think it through.
I don't have the wits to be of service to you, young mistress.
Young mistress, I will follow you without a second thought.
So will I, young mistress.
You've done me a great favor. I'll never betray you.
Why do you say that?
My elder brother was ill with no one to care for him.
Even in your illness, you were concerned and had Doctor Wen check on him.
If not for you, my elder brother would not have made it.
You've favored us so greatly, I will serve you with absolute loyalty.
Not only in this life,
XIAO YUNZI
but also after I reincarnate as a cow. I'll carry you towards becoming a Buddha.
Liar.
I am most sincere.
You've served a young mistress who has suffered long-term illness and disgrace.
You have never enjoyed advantage, yet still you serve me with devotion.
I receive more than I can repay.
As long as I'm here,
I will never let you be mistreated.
Thank you, young mistress.
The Emperor and the Empress arrive!
Your Majesty, may peace be with you. Your Highness, may fortune be with you.
Today is a family feast. No need to be formal. You may be seated.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
You always ask us to relax.
But we must follow tradition, so formality is of the essence.
MARQUESS GUO (YUNLI)
Only my 17th Brother would say such a thing.
He doesn't like formality.
He hasn't run off and was not late today.
That's already enough of an accomplishment.
Tonight is the New Year's Eve gathering, how could I be late?
First, a toast.
May you enjoy long life, health and peace. May our country thrive in peace.
Well said.
Long live the Emperor!
Jinxi, let me see that.
Jinxi made this peacock showing its tail, it's so vivid.
Very nice.
But nothing like the image of the Gods of Harmony the young mistress made.
Look, it's so lifelike.
The Gods of Harmony don't really exist. It came entirely from my imagination.
I've heard that some can make paper cutouts
that look identical to an actual person.
Young mistress, there is a master of the art of paper cutouts among us.
I just saw Xiao Yunzi make a portrait of you and hide it in his sleeve.
- Really? - Don't talk nonsense.
Xiao Yunzi, be generous. Let me have a look.
Let's see.
So alike.
Xiao Yunzi, you're so skillful.
I'm clumsy, unable to make a cutout of your beautiful face.
I'll make a better one next time, young mistress.
Your Majesty, I propose a toast.
Where's Attendant Wan?
Attendant Wan hasn't recovered yet.
It's freezing cold, so I told her to rest at her residence.
I heard of a custom in the palace.
On New Year's Eve, if you place something dear to you on a branch,
the higher the better, then you can make a wish.
If you truly like this little portrait,
you may put it on the tree in the courtyard.
And then you may wish for good fortune next year.
It will also be a great honor to Xiao Yunzi.
Good idea.
I'll go see.
Young mistress, you shouldn't.
You haven't fully recovered. It's not good to go outside.
If the Empress learns of this, she will blame us.
He's right.
It's late at night.
Everyone is enjoying the feast.
I'll put on my cloak before going out. It will keep me warm and concealed.
I've been ill for so long. It's time I took a walk.
- Young mistress. - Don't follow me.
I wish to go alone.
Anyone who dares detain me further,
will have to kneel on the ground this whole snowy night.
Young mistress!
Have the red plums in the Imperial Garden blossomed yet?
They blossom, even with the snow.
I wish to see it.
It's freezing cold outside. You should care for your health.
They blossom in the snow. How could I miss such a sight?
Don't try to stop me.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Let no one follow me. I wish to walk alone.
I drank overmuch.
- But Your Majesty– - Your Majesty.
- Say no more. - Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, where are you going?
Brother Yunli.
His Majesty forbade us to follow him.
But it's dark outside and the path is slippery. Please accompany him.
Why was the red plum placed here?
Consort Hua knows nothing of the matter.
It was she who was responsible for decorating the Imperial Feast.
Don't worry, Your Highness. I'll follow him.
Since we came to the palace,
all have prayed to win His Majesty's favor.
I first wish that my parents and sister be granted good health and fortune.
I next wish that I may live peacefully in the palace for the rest of my life.
There is endless strife in the harem.
It is not easy to protect myself.
The plum blossoms this year are just as beautiful as in the past.
"Each year and every year, the blossoms return anew.
Each year and every year, the bloom of youth does not."
Surely Consort Hua didn't intend to decorate with so many plum blossoms.
It is my own problem.
It all took place before Consort Hua became my concubine. She knows nothing.
It has been many years. You still haven't let it go?
Let what go?
Now I expect it will grow warmer after early spring.
You may come visit me. We'll converse and play chess together.
Young mistress, please be patient.
His Majesty is still occupied with his daily affairs, he'll come later.
Shortly, we will carry you to the bedchamber.
Young mistress, you may lie on the bed and await His Majesty.
Young mistress, what's the matter?
Now I'm somehow frightened.
Don't be scared.
What is it?
I'm–
Did Madam Liu teach you the rules of serving in bed?
I don't like to force anyone. Some other day.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Take her away.
Bring Second Attendant Yu.
Yes, Your Majesty.
What a misfortune. I've never performed such a lousy errand.
A concubine who was carried into Yangxin Hall is carried out untouched.
Who are you, sire?
Guess.
You're one of the nobles?
Have you heard of Marquess Guo?
Are you really Marquess Guo?
Have you ever seen me before?
Since coming to the palace, I have met neither His Majesty nor His Lordship.
Then how do you know I'm not Marquess Guo?
Your age does not seem to match his.
A person's appearance doesn't always match his age.
It is as you say.
I'm a First Attendant from the Zhen family,
I bow in respect before His Lordship.
You're the First Attendant who has been ill?
How does my lord know about the trifles of the harem?
I heard it from my imperial sister-in-law.
At New Year's Eve, His Majesty mentioned it. And I was there.
I see.
Are you recovering well?
Why didn't you dress warmly before going out?
Thank you for your consideration. I'm feeling well.
Liuzhu, this is Marquess Guo.
I wish you all blessings, my lord.
You were just playing "Apricot Blossoms Against the Sky."
It matches the setting so well.
I play quite poorly. Please forgive my lack of skill.
Your performance was excellent.
But when you started to play the line,
"Green shoots spring from the shoal, and still I am far from home,"
the tone of your flute faltered a little,
as if you were stifling a sob.
Was it due to homesickness?
"The smallest mistake a musician made, Zhou Yu would notice."
You have a good ear for music, comparable to Zhou Yu's.
We haven't–
I haven't heard such beautiful flute playing or a very long time.
Ever since Empress Chunyuan died,
none has played so well as you.
Your Lordship is too kind. I'm deeply humbled.
I dare not compare myself to Empress Chunyuan.
I must return to my residence. Enjoy the garden, my lord.
Go ahead.
Young mistress, you're back.
Pei-er.
Find a way to determine if Marquess Guo entered the palace today.
Yes, mistress.
You don't believe the man who appreciated the music was Marquess Guo?
What do you think?
Extra caution is always wise.
May good fortune be with you, Your Majesty.
- Rise. - Thank you, Your Majesty.
Why have you come so early?
This morning, you sent word that you had an authentic work of Wu Daozi.
I couldn't wait to see it, so I came right away.
Why so hurried? A painting cannot run away.
A famous painting is just like a beautiful woman.
I'll waste no time enjoying it.
If you have such thirst for beauty, why haven't you married?
Halt.
All of you will return to Yangxin Hall. I want to walk alone.
- You want to go higher? - A little bit.
I knew you would be scared.
It'll be your turn later.
Great. I'm afraid of nothing.
Well, Liuzhu. You dare play tricks behind my back.
Young mistress.
I greet His Lordship.
Are you all right, young mistress?
Why so timid now?
You were as brave as a heroine before.
I was discourteous.
I didn't know that His Lordship enjoyed standing at others' backs in silence.
So you blame me for my rudeness.
As I was passing by this place,
I recalled the flute music you played the other day.
I hoped I would meet you and have a chance to hear it once more.
But I didn't bring the flute with me today.
Then I must wait for next time.
This spot is filled with apricot blossoms.
The song you played also refers to apricot blossoms.
Are you very fond of them?
The apricot blossom is beautiful, but the fruit is exceedingly sour.
Furthermore, the stone is bitter.
If life begins in happiness but ends in misery, what is the purpose?
I'd rather it resemble the pine and cedar.
They're evergreen, but lack flower and fruit.
I've never heard such a point of view. It's quite innovative and unique.
I just spoke nonsense. Please forgive my silliness.
I was overly intrusive and rude today.
I have two music scores.
Five days from now, at this hour,
I'll share them with you in this place.
I hope that you will be here.
It is better to accept deferentially than to decline courteously.
Your Majesty.
Halt.
The Empress Dowager requires you at Shoukang Palace.
He didn't come.
You mean Marquess Guo, young mistress?
How silly of me.
He is a marquess.
In such weather, of course he prefers to recite poetry at home.
Why should he come to meet me?
His invitation was just a whim, but I took it seriously.
Young mistress, let's return.
Don't get wet in the rain. Let's go.
"Over the high mountain, a distant moon rises.
Though the moon is small, it shines clear and bright.
The one on my mind is far away from me.
One day apart and already my heart is heavy."
The sound of music lays bare the heart of the musician.
Something is on your mind and haunts you.
SECOND ATTENDANT YU
It's her again.
Who's there on the swing?
Why didn't you come forward to bow in respect?
My young mistress is First Attendant Wan of Suiyu Pavilion.
Is there really an Attendant Wan? I've never heard of her.
Young mistress, it is true that a First Attendant lives there.
She has long been ill and seldom goes out.
I am Second Attendant Yu. I bow in respect before Attendant Wan.
Greetings.
I'd like to offer some advice, Attendant Wan.
If you are not well, then you should not be outdoors.
Otherwise, your ill fortune may bring harm to others and you will be to blame.
You are very kind.
I would like to offer counsel to you in return.
I await the wisdom of your words.
It is said that His Majesty prefers those who are always courteous.
But Attendant Yu, when you saw me here, you did not bow in respect.
So I must ask you to greet me again.
You're only a First Attendant who has never enjoyed the imperial favor.
How dare you ask me to bow in respect. You don't deserve it.
Young mistress, Attendant Wan is of higher rank.
You serve me. How dare you take her side!
You don't actually believe that your rank indicates your status, do you?
Besides, your rank is only slightly above mine.
Don't be overbearing.
What if it is our desire
that you bow in respect before Attendant Wan?
May good fortune be with you, Your Majesty.
Young mistress.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty. May blessings and peace be with you.
Your Majesty, may blessings and peace be with you.
The other day, I did not intentionally break my promise and arrive late.
Though I have been ill for several days,
you have never left my thoughts.
Did you come back to wait for me?
You may rise.
Help your young mistress up, she is still very weak.
Young mistress.
Your Majesty, I admit my fault.
I offended Attendant Wan out of blindness and ignorance.
I apologize to Attendant Wan and beg for her forgiveness.
Your Majesty, please spare me this once.
Your Majesty, "A fault confessed is half redressed."
I believe Attendant Yu is truly regretful for her error.
Your Majesty, please forgive her.
Since Attendant Wan tries to intercede for you,
it is not good for us to disappoint her.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Take note, Second Attendant Yu is hereby demoted.
She must leave Zhongcui Palace and live someplace beyond our sight.
Yes, sir.
Your Majesty.
You just said that Attendant Wan's rank was only slightly above yours.
I now promote Attendant Wan to Noble Lady.
Sire, promoting Attendant Wan before she serves you goes against custom.
You are now so punctilious in performing your duty
that you even interfere with my decrees?
I dare not. I shall execute your order immediately.
Are you so overjoyed that you forget to show your gratitude?
Firstly, I have made no contribution to the nation.
Secondly, I have begotten no heirs.
I don't deserve to receive such great imperial grace.
We declare that you deserve it, therefore, you absolutely deserve it.
Rise.
You drop to your knees so frequently, you completely neglect your own health.
Young mistress, please return to your residence.
I excuse myself.
What's the matter? You're frightened?
Your palm is sweaty. Are you nervous?
You're the Emperor.
You were not afraid of me before today. You were very bold.
I didn't know you were the Emperor.
But now I know.
You are filled with regal dignity.
I'm only an ordinary woman. I cannot help but fear you.
Fear will bring overcaution.
Overcaution will turn us into Emperor and his concubine.
That rainy day, I did not intend to break my promise.
I was only steps away from the Imperial Garden.
But at that moment, the Empress Dowager called me to Shoukang Palace.
When I returned to the Imperial Garden, you had already disappeared.
I then caught cold and was ill for several days.
Your Majesty, are you feeling better now?
I stand before you in health talking with you now.
Is it not so?
I'm so foolish.
Concern will cause confusion.
In fact, I did come to the garden that day.
Really?
Did you get wet in the rain? Were you ill after that?
Thank you for your concern, Your Majesty.
I also stand before you in health.
All is well then.
I have high esteem for you, simply because of your nature.
If you were the same as the other concubines,
I would not take my promise to you so seriously.
I'm so foolish. I didn't realize it at all.
I intentionally hid the truth from you. How would you know?
Why is your hand so cold?
Is it because of the wind?
I don't feel cold.
You've been out for a long time. Let me escort you back.
Walking is tiring, I'll carry you instead.
I dare not.
Why not?
Others will talk, Your Majesty.
I must care for the one who is dear to me.
If the others wish to talk, then let them talk as they will.
We greet Your Majesty.
My arms are sore.
You mean to say that I am heavy?
You are not heavy.
I was concerned I would hurt you if I held you too tightly.
But if I held you too loosely, you might fall.
I was torn in that dilemma. That's why my arms are sore.
You really know how to embarrass others.
When Lady Wan was First Attendant, only you remained to serve her?
Yes, sir.
Peace and quiet is good for my recovery.
And I really don't need so many servants.
That's unreasonable.
You've been promoted to Noble Lady. It's time you had more servants.
Tomorrow I'll ask the Imperial Household Department to send you decent staff.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
She has already risen to Noble Lady.
PEACE
- His Majesty is very fond of her? - It seems so.
But her promotion goes against custom.
Your Highness, you must speak to His Majesty.
Palace custom was established by our ancestors.
The ancestors are called sons of heaven. And Son of Heaven refers to the Emperor.
She's an extraordinary girl. It is just a matter of time.
Frightened?
Concubines are always frightened the first time they serve in bed.
I am not frightened.
Tonight is my wedding night.
I am terrified.
Madam Liu taught me how to serve the Emperor.
But she has never taught me how to serve my husband.
I've displeased you. Please forgive me, Your Majesty.
No one has ever spoken to me this way.
Since you regard me as your husband,
you need not be so cautious before your husband.
The night before last, she served.
LADY CAO – CONCUBINE LI
Last night, she served again.
This afternoon, she played chess with His Majesty.
She is at Yangxin Hall this very moment.
The minx. She always manages to entangle His Majesty.
Because His Majesty has allowed her to do so.
Others are unable to do the same.
SERVING RECORD
I bow in respect before Consort Hua. I bow in respect before Concubine Li.
- Rise. - Thank you, my lady.
It seems that Lady Shen has lost some weight.
Is it because His Majesty no longer calls on you these days?
It's not like that.
I've simply lost my appetite due to the sultry weather.
So that's it.
Now that Lady Wan enjoys His Majesty's favor,
I thought Lady Shen had grown uncomfortable.
I would not dare.
Lady Wan is intelligent and beautiful.
Being favored with imperial grace is only natural.
Were it any of the others, it would not matter.
But Lady Wan and Lady Shen are as close as sisters.
Why didn't you share this grace with your sister
when you enjoyed the favor exclusively?
Lady Wan has been busy serving His Majesty recently.
Lady Shen is unoccupied.
Do you have time to make a copy of the account book?
My lady, I will gladly comply with your command.
Did His Majesty choose her to serve him again tonight?
His Majesty has gone to Consort Qi's residence.
Why did he go to see her?
As long as it's not Lady Wan, it doesn't matter who it is.
What time is it now?
It's still early. The sky has just grown dark.
His Majesty has asked Lady Shen to learn how to read the account book.
Then I should teach her personally.
- Summon Lady Shen. - Yes, my lady.
The candles are flickering.
Blow out two of them.
Yes, my lady.
Young mistress, no need to wait up.
His Majesty has chosen Consort Qi and has gone to Changchun Palace.
It's fine.
By your voice, you sound relieved, and yet unhappy.
I'm confused as well.
I hoped that His Majesty would not come.
Yet when I find that he hasn't, I'm not happy at all.
For better or for worse, Lady Shen comes from a noble family.
Why is your handwriting so illegible?
The candlelight is too dim. I can't see clearly.
Please forgive me, my lady.
You've just copied the account book. You must know that expenses are heavy.
As the leader of all the concubines, I must set an example of frugality.
Besides, it is said that if your handwriting is truly good,
then you may write beautifully even in the dark.
Noble Lady, your excuse is not convincing at all.
Then I'll make another copy.
Go ahead. I'll take a nap.
Songzhi, the light is too bright, blow out two more candles.
Yes, my lady.
"Raindrops fall on Dongting Lake.
Fog shrouds the Imperial Mausoleum.
I await my husband, but he has not arrived.
The ripples in the lake are not–"
Young mistress, please stop.
The title is "Consort Xiang's Complaint." It's unpropitious.
Halt.
It's "Consort Xiang's Complaint."
I know nothing of that.
"It's clear that the song is full of worry and sorrow.
As if to complain that her lover has not yet returned."
I'm not by her side. That's why she laments.
I'm disquieted by the sound of your music.
May blessings and peace be with you, Your Majesty.
Rise.
Your Majesty, why are you here?
"I've grown careworn for thinking of my lover."
I've finally tasted that kind of feeling.
Your Majesty, I thought you were at Consort Qi's residence.
I've already seen her.
On the way back, I saw the beautiful moonlight.
I wanted to come see what you were doing.
Such wonderful music. I am fortunate not to have missed it.
Does eavesdropping befit the dignity of the Emperor?
You grow bolder and bolder.
As punishment, you must play another piece.
Which song would you like to hear, my dear?
What did you call me just now?
It was a slip of the tongue.
I love the way you just spoke to me.
Your birth name is Zhen Huan. What is your nickname?
I don't have a nickname.
Then I shall call you Huan Huan. Do you like it?
Huan Huan.
It's clear that Consort Hua made things difficult for you.
That account book was full of numbers and she dimmed the light intentionally.
One copy would be hard enough.
Young mistress, your eyes are red now.
I had no choice. Just because she is Consort Hua.
I'm so sorry for you.
I'm fine. I've already fought off the sleepiness.
Qianli Pond isn't far from here. Let's take a walk.
I've heard that His Majesty has added some lamps.
The red fish look much more beautiful at night.
We ran out of fish food.
Xiao Shi, get us some more.
Yes, mistress.
Young mistress, look.
Here you are, young mistress. I've been looking for you everywhere.
Why are you out so late at night?
Does Consort Hua have any instructions for me?
The Consort has received some fine ink sent from Huizhou as a tribute.
She wanted to share some with you, but you left so quickly.
Caiyue, go with Songzhi.
But you will be left alone–
Try to come back as soon as possible.
Yes, mistress.
Help–
Help me!
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
- Rise. - Thank you, Your Majesty.
How's Mei?
Lady Wan, Lady Shen is all right now.
But she took in a lot of water and had a terrible shock. She's unconscious.
CONCUBINE JING
JIANG CHENG
We have already made a prescription.
As long as Lady Shen follows our instructions,
she will recover very soon.
How did you serve your young mistress?
Please forgive us, Your Majesty.
How did Lady Shen end up in the water?
I don't know.
Nonsense!
You're Lady Shen's closest servants, how can you know nothing about it?
It's true. We really know nothing.
She was feeding fish at Qianli Pond, I went to get more food.
On the way, I heard shouts that she'd fallen in.
And Caiyue?
CAIYUE
Songzhi said that Consort Hua wanted to give her some fine ink,
she'd forgotten it earlier, and asked me to go fetch it.
So when Lady Shen fell in the water,
there was no one by her side?
Your Majesty, Consort Hua is here.
It's late at night. Why have you come?
I heard that Lady Shen nearly drowned, so I came in a hurry.
Is she recovering now?
Useless servants! How did you serve your young mistress?
It worries His Majesty.
Servants like them are only a burden to Lady Shen.
I suggest that they be sent to the Office of Punishment.
Please forgive them, my lady.
I know Consort Hua is expert at dispensing rewards and punishment.
But Caiyue and Xiao Shi have served Mei all along.
If they're sent to the Office of Punishment now,
Mei will be left without any reliable servants by her side.
They failed to keep Lady Shen safe. Why bother to keep them by her side?
Besides, Qianli Pond is less than a hundred paces from Yikun Palace.
It took place near my residence. How can I let them off easily?
That's precisely why I'm concerned.
Because the accident took place near Yikun Palace,
it could damage your prestige, others may think that's why you're upset.
That you don't truly care if Lady Shen nearly drowned.
These servants are insignificant, but your reputation is of great importance.
Consort Hua should think twice.
I agree with Lady Wan.
Let's make the decision after Lady Shen wakes up.
It will not be too late to send them to the Office of Punishment at that time.
I have another suggestion. I don't know if it's proper to state it.
Speak.
We still don't know what happened before Mei fell in the water.
But the guards didn't respond in time.
That's why she took in so much water and fell unconscious.
In my view,
it would be better to replace the guards at Yikun Palace.
It is Mei who suffers this time. But if there were another incident,
and Consort Hua became the next victim, what would we do?
Lady Wan just argued that we should let them make up for their mistakes.
Then why did you suggest replacing the guards at my palace?
It seems that your suggestion is partial.
It is for your own good, my lady.
His Majesty cherishes you greatly.
How could His Majesty let those careless servants protect your palace
and leave you endangered without misgivings?
Besides, being replaced is not a punishment for the guards.
Safety is the most important thing.
We can never let this happen again.
I'll ask Su Peisheng to replace them with
highly capable guards to protect Yikun Palace.
Only then will I rest easy.
How dare she interfere with my affairs!
Do not worry, my lady.
His Majesty favors her now. Many people hate her for that.
Who is serving Yu now?
She has lost the Emperor's favor, and become bad-tempered.
Even her own maid has left her after being beaten.
The wretch lives on her own now.
Your servant Kang Luhai is utterly useless.
Is his apprentice loyal to you?
You mean Xiao Yinzi, my lady?
He is not as cunning and devious as his master. Somewhat reliable.
Send him to serve Yu.
Mei.
Huan.
Someone tried to kill me.
Mei, did you see his face clearly?
The only one who could do something like this–
But Qianli Pond is so close to Yikun Palace.
If she wanted to play a dirty trick on me, she wouldn't do it on her own territory.
She should know how to avoid arousing suspicion.
It's worth the risk.
Others would not suspect that
she'd play such a dirty trick in her own territory.
You have the Emperor's favor.
She was afraid our strength would grow to the point that it's hard to control us.
So she had to get rid of one of us first.
Then we would be too weak to fight against her.
This ink was received from the Governor of Shandong as a tribute.
This ink stick may be of good quality,
but it can never compare with those in Yikun Palace.
Do you really plan to do nothing about Lady Shen's accident?
You saw Consort Hua hold her head high when she just paid a visit to me.
That means His Majesty has already made up his mind.
Even if I wanted to do something, I'm unable to do anything about it.
In any case, we all know who must be responsible for this.
Sometimes we have to settle a matter by leaving it unresolved.
"All good things must come to an end."
Such as the good days when the late Emperor and I had just met.
I thought my devout prayers had been heard by the heavens.
God had granted me the finest man in the world,
and I could remain by his side as long as I lived.
Perhaps the late Emperor and I were not made for each other.
It was my destiny to be selected at audition
and meet the late Emperor in the garden.
It was also my destiny to meet Consort Hua and Empress Wenyu in my life.
But what is the true destiny of a person?
No one may know until the end of one's life.
Then how should we live our life?
At this age, I finally understand.
One must believe in destiny, but never resign oneself to it.