I am moved by Xiao Yunzi.
He has served me since I entered the palace, his loyalty absolute.
It is rare to find a true friend,
let alone a servant of such loyalty.
Such are Jinxi, Huanbi and Liuzhu. They have been entirely devoted.
Yet those in the palace are fickle. They curry favor with the powerful.
Not a single one refuses to follow along blindly.
I have always been obstinate, refusing to subject myself to another.
In my moment of distress when I fell into disgrace,
were it not for these loyal servants, devoted in heart and soul,
I likely would have met the same fate as Consort Hua.
My lady, congratulations. Please make a wish by flying a kite.
Your Majesty, look.
I can't believe there are so many lotus blossoms in April.
Now listen.
"Two phoenixes on the wing."
It sounds so graceful on the flute.
A pair of phoenixes on the wing glide in perfect harmony,
paired in a happy marriage filled with peace and joy.
Every woman in the world dreams of such a match.
Has your dream come true?
In honor of Concubine Wan's birthday
I present a pond filled with lotus blossoms.
My lord, you have outdone yourself. I am honored.
I told you to devise a novel idea.
I never imagined it would be so extraordinary.
You asked me to plan a celebration for Concubine Wan.
I, your brother, would surely do my utmost.
I'm curious how you managed to make the lotuses bloom in this season.
The lotus roots were planted some time ago.
I made them bloom by diverting water from
a hot spring outside the palace into the pond.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Huan, you've returned.
You come at a good time. I was just thinking of you.
I've used almost all of the healing balm. I wanted to ask you for more.
What a coincidence. I thought the very same thing.
- You see, I've brought some with me. - I keep troubling you.
I've already used three or four containers.
But I still need you to make some more.
Huan, you're expecting a child. Please sit down.
I am simply idle.
It is wonderful to be able to use my skills for your sake.
Don't tire yourself.
His Majesty the Emperor!
Huan Huan.
Your Majesty, may blessings and peace be with you.
- Rise. - Thank you, Your Majesty.
I've told you not to move needlessly. Why do you bother to kneel?
You stood up so quickly. What if you slipped and fell?
I am not so fragile.
Huan, since His Majesty now accompanies you,
I will excuse myself.
The Empress and I will go to
the Temple of Heaven for a prayer ceremony.
In the meantime, Consort Hua will be in charge of the harem.
I know you are often at odds with her.
You must yield to her if she makes things difficult.
If you are aggrieved, tell me upon my return.
I understand.
You carry a child now. Don't go to Yikun Palace unless needed.
I will take extra care. Please rest easy, Your Majesty.
It is out of deep concern that I must keep enjoining you.
His Imperial Majesty and Her Highness the Empress depart!
Your Majesty and Your Highness, we see you off in respect.
No matter how long I sleep, I remain weary.
I feel sore around the waist.
Young mistress, is anything wrong?
It is nothing.
I have often been to Consort Hua's palace
to receive instruction these past few days.
I don't know what kind of incense is burned there.
I find the smell pungent.
Consort Hua is fond of the incense, especially in great quantities.
It is fragrant only from a distance.
I think I will ask Xiao Yunzi to send for Doctor Zhang.
- Return as soon as possible. - Yes, Mistress.
- I bow in respect before Concubine Wan. - You may rise.
By order of Consort Hua,
Concubine Wan must report to Yikun Palace to listen to her words.
I would not fail to attend,
but I am not well today.
Could you convey my apologies to Consort Hua?
By His Majesty's decree, Consort Hua is in charge of the harem.
My lady, you should not disregard His Majesty's orders.
- Is the Empress Dowager recovering? - She remains the same.
She keeps coughing after nightfall and cannot sleep through the night.
I bow in respect before Consort Hua.
I was unwell this morning. I arrive late. My lady, please forgive me.
You may rise.
There have been a number of quarrels among the maids and eunuchs recently.
If not for the favor their mistresses enjoy,
they would never dare behave this way.
They have surely been influenced by the improper behavior of their mistresses.
Concubine Wan.
Do you acknowledge your error?
Today all the concubines have gathered here to receive instruction.
Concubine Wan arrives late needlessly and displays contempt for her superiors.
Kneel at once!
I acknowledge my error.
Concubine Wan of the Zhen family
has offended her superiors and affronted me.
As punishment, she must kneel outdoors and read the Admonitions for Women aloud.
My lady, the sun shines fiercely at this hour
and the granite is extremely hard.
Concubine Wan carries a child. You cannot order her to kneel.
My lady, please forgive her.
For the sake of her unborn child, please forgive her, my lady.
It is your right to punish Concubine Wan, but if His Majesty's child is harmed,
you will surely be castigated when His Majesty and the Empress return.
Do you think you can threaten me with His Majesty and the Empress?
Of course I must be punished for my error.
But I carry His Majesty's child. I truly cannot kneel for long durations.
My lady, please reconsider.
Do you take me for a fool?
You have been quite well during pregnancy and you are already past three months.
Your condition should be stable by now.
I have already consulted the imperial doctors.
Kneeling for two hours should cause no harm to a pregnant woman.
- How dare you! - Kneel.
Don't.
Young mistress.
I will accept your punishment
only because you were left in charge of the harem by imperial decree.
True justice exists in the heart of man. It cannot be imposed through punishment.
Very well. Now we will see
whether true justice is imposed by my command
or exists in what you call the heart of man.
Read it aloud, word-for-word, until I am satisfied.
Concubine Wan is pregnant. It is improper for her to kneel.
Should pregnant concubines be allowed to defy the palace rules?
Since you are so eager to intercede,
why don't you kneel and join her?
Lady Hui is not trying to intercede.
My lady, please do not vent your anger on her.
If I insist on doing so, what say do you have in the matter?
Kneel beside her and hold the book in your hands.
Let her read it aloud. She may even learn something.
I am here.
It's terribly hot.
Bring chairs for all of the concubines.
Let them observe what happens to those who defy me.
Even from beautiful women, the smell of sweat is just as pungent.
Songzhi, bring out the incense burner.
Remove these odors by burning more Huanyi Incense.
Yes, my lady.
"I was beloved by my late husband, due to instruction from my mother and teacher.
I married at age 14 and became a member of the Cao family.
Forty years have passed since then. Trembling with fear--"
You are not allowed to enter.
So much time has passed. Why does she still kneel?
It is too soon for Consort Hua to relent.
Halt!
I am from Suiyu Pavilion. I urgently ask to see the Empress Dowager.
Her Highness is ill. She sleeps after her medicine.
How dare you disturb her!
It is a matter of life or death. Please let me enter.
If you disturb the Empress Dowager, it will cost you your life.
- Your Highness! - Be gone!
If not for Suiyu Pavilion, you'd have been beaten already.
Be gone!
- Huanbi, what is it? - A Jin, where is the Marquess?
"Humility and delicacy are foremost.
In ancient times, female infants were placed
under the bed when three days old.
Spindles and bricks were laid next to them to announce their birth to the ancestors."
- Servants. - Yes, my lady.
Beat them.
One of them is with child and may not be beaten, so beat the other one.
Yes, my lady.
- Don't beat her. - Young mistress, careful.
- Young mistress, watch out! - Don't beat her!
Young mistress.
My lady.
If you grow listless again, your good friend
will take another beating for you.
My lady, I am truly not well.
Just look at her, everyone. How foolish she is.
She feigns illness just as Lady Fucha did
not realizing that the same excuse becomes worn out from overuse.
Why don't you try something new?
My lady, Huan is very weak.
If she collapses from heatstroke, you won't be able to bear the blame.
I intend to find out whether she will collapse.
Zhou Ninghai, burn some mint and mugwort.
Yes, my lady.
If she collapses from heatstroke even after burning these herbs,
I will consider it an act of intentional deception.
Even though I cannot punish you,
I will never spare Lady Hui or Attendant An
who are party to your devious ways.
My lady, it has been an hour already.
No hurry. She must continue to kneel for another quarter hour.
My lady, Concubine Wan already looks pale.
Is she making this disingenuous display for my benefit?
I wager that she is in perfectly good health.
- Huan. - Young mistress.
Huan.
- Young mistress. - Huan, are you all right?
Out of the way!
- Huan. - Young mistress.
- Marquess Guo? - Young mistress, what is it?
He dares intrude into Yikun Palace.
Stop! Where are you taking Concubine Wan?
You must know that intruding into the harem is a capital crime.
That will be for His Majesty to determine.
I cannot stand by while the imperial heir is harmed.
If I am punished someday, as you say,
I will have a clear conscience and no regrets.
Stop!
My lady, there appears to be blood on the ground.
Send for the doctor.
- What happened? - Careful.
The blanket.
Young mistress.
It was caused by her foolishness.
She didn't say anything.
No matter which imperial doctor said she could kneel for an hour,
you should not have held her there so long.
Caution is the prudent choice. Some actions cannot be undone.
Why didn't you stop me? Your hindsight is useless now.
My lady, please quiet your anger.
My lady, don't vex yourself. You must care for your health.
The imperial carriage of the Emperor has just reached Xuanwu Gate.
So soon?
Any news from Suiyu Pavilion?
Did she keep her child?
The imperial doctors are still gathered at Suiyu Pavilion.
There is no further news.
Lady Cao, kind mistress.
My lady did not mean to embarrass you. Please devise a way to help her.
My lady, regardless of whether Concubine Wan loses the child,
if you wish to regain His Majesty's favor in the future,
then you must submit for the present.
Huan Huan.
Are you awake?
It's a blessing from Heaven you're finally awake.
You have slept for several hours.
Your Majesty.
You have returned.
Huan Huan.
I am deeply sorry.
Your Majesty.
My child--
Is my child all right?
We will have another child someday.
Young mistress.
Your Majesty, my child.
Your Majesty!
My child!
Do not cry.
If you are grieved, His Majesty will feel even deeper grief.
The imperial carriages returned in haste upon hearing the news.
Your Majesty, this is no time for mourning.
Concubine Wan has lost her child through man-made, not natural causes.
Where is that shrew?
I greet Your Majesty.
I am guilty.
Concubine Wan offended me today.
I intended to teach her a lesson with a modest punishment.
I did not mean to harm her unborn child.
I don't even understand how such a thing could happen.
I hope that Your Majesty will forgive my ignorance.
Your ignorance?
You knew that Concubine Wan was pregnant and yet you insisted on punishing her!
And you didn't regret it afterward!
Vile wench!
It was caused by my ignorance.
I do not believe that you are ignorant.
Yet you are indeed quite vicious.
Even if Concubine Wan did commit an error,
why not punish her in the morning?
Why must you wait till midday when the sun shines most fiercely?
In my eyes, you are as vicious as a viper.
How can I keep such a woman as my companion?
Your Majesty.
I was truly aggrieved by Concubine Wan's arrogance.
But I never thought of harming her unborn child.
I experienced the same loss myself.
Your Majesty, how could I possibly be so cruel?
"Do not impose on others what you do not wish for yourself."
The Empress will instruct the harem concerning my decree.
For Consort Hua of the Nian family, the honorific name "Hua" is revoked.
Her power to assist in the affairs of the harem is annulled.
She is forbidden to approach me without being summoned.
I will execute your decree. Your Majesty, please rest assured.
Your Majesty.
It was an unwitting blunder.
Your Majesty, how can you be so merciless?
How innocent Concubine Wan was.
How innocent all the concubines were!
They all had to endure the scorching sun with Concubine Wan!
From now on,
every midday,
you must kneel at the gate of your palace for four hours.
Be gone!
You may all leave. I will remain with Concubine Wan.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Concubine Wan, your health is most important.
You have many years ahead of you. Be measured in your grief.
This time...
if Marquess Guo had not rescued you from Yikun Palace
and sent a messenger to report to me,
I cannot imagine how much worse it might have turned out.
Your Majesty, I venture to ask.
Did my child just die for nothing?
Why not kill that wench to vent our hatred?
We are hard pressed for allies in the field.
I must take that into consideration.
Yet she has killed your own child, Your Majesty.
Huan Huan.
For my sake, please endure this a while longer.
Do not make it difficult for me.
Nian Gengyao has sent his regards with this memorandum. Take a look.
General Nian is as engaged with family affairs as he is with affairs of state.
He has inquired about Consort Nian in every memorandum.
Obviously, he does so intentionally.
If he lacks all propriety before you, he offends and disrespects the Emperor.
If he lacks propriety before the people, he offends everyone in the country
and ignores the imperial favors granted to him.
If you were Emperor, what would you do?
"When you do not hold an office, you need not consider policy."
I am softhearted and incapable of handling serious matters.
The tears of a beauty cause me to lose my head.
To involve me in important affairs is to invite disaster.
I feel you have shirked your duties at the court.
I shall no longer allow you to remain aloof from these affairs.
There is a matter with which I truly need your help.
Simply say the word and I will comply.
Your Majesty, I am at your command.
Your Majesty said you did not wish to hold an audition for the harem.
I've selected several beauties of grace from among the imperial maids.
Your Majesty, please have a look and see if one catches your fancy.
I drank overmuch. Maybe another day.
This female singer has been training for a long time.
I simply hope her performance may please you.
Let her begin.
Lotus blossoms abound to be picked to the south of the Yangtze
Her voice is soft, gentle and gracious.
It is somehow quite moving.
Her dress is truly befitting.
I see that she has taken great pains.
No matter how beautiful her attire, her voice is even more striking.
Why does she cover her face?
Is she so unsightly that she must hide it?
Her singing skills are exceptional.
Even better than Attendant Yu and Attendant An.
Does her voice remind you of another's?
It is somehow similar to Lingrong's,
yet more pure and delicate.
Where is Lingrong? Why is she not in attendance?
She is suffering from a cough.
It's natural she should avoid meeting others.
"Such a beauty as she should be held in my arms at first sight."
Your Majesty, do you not recognize her?
I, An Lingrong, bow in respect before Your Majesty.
Were you not ill?
Her Highness the Empress sent one to care for me. I've already recovered.
Not only have you recovered, but your voice has improved greatly.
The Empress has outdone herself.
It is a great good fortune to have you by my side.
I saw that Your Majesty was dispirited, so I was compelled to take such measures.
I only hoped to restore good cheer and good health to Your Majesty.
Watch your step.
At this time last year, Lingrong was promoted to First Attendant.
Today she is promoted to Noble Lady.
Your Majesty is truly generous.
Your face is still quite pale.
Have you eaten the edible bird's nests brought by Su Peisheng?
Yes, I have.
Yet it takes time to make a full recovery. It will not take effect so quickly.
I see that the scar on your neck has disappeared.
It's fortunate that your face was not marred.
If a scar were left on your face,
it would be as a slight flaw in pure white jade.
Your Majesty, it seems you treasure my appearance.
Huan Huan's beauty merits praise.
Only now I learn that you care for my appearance to this degree.
Concubine Wan, you are overly assertive.
In consideration for your recent loss,
I shall overlook your disrespect this time.
You must try to calm your emotions.
Your Highness, are you not fond of Concubine Wan?
Why is it that you do not encourage His Majesty,
but rather dissuade him from visiting her?
I know my own son very well.
The Emperor is overly attached to Concubine Wan.
That's why he was troubled to see Concubine Wan grieving.
The Emperor may show favor to any concubine,
but not exclusively.
Consort Nian has fallen from his favor.
If Concubine Wan becomes dominant, the harem will be unbalanced.
Besides, there is not much submissiveness in Concubine Wan's temperament.
She needs to temper herself.
The Household Department is busy making dresses with Sichuan brocade for Lady An.
Lingrong is fortunate. She now enjoys His Majesty's favor exclusively.
Mei is here.
Why are you making winter clothing yourselves?
The Imperial Household Department is too busy to make them.
- I want to take you somewhere. - Let me put away this silk thread.
Come.
- Where are we going? - Let's go.
- Mei, that is the Cold Palace. - Come quickly.
When will His Majesty come?
- I won. - You cheated.
Someday His Majesty will be fond of me.
How could His Majesty still remember you?
Look at you. You smell.
I won't give it to you.
Are you all right?
The reason you brought me here
was not to see Concubine Li, was it?
Did you notice the lady next to Concubine Li?
She was a Noble Lady who served His Majesty before.
Who is she?
It doesn't matter who she is.
It only matters that she was once with child,
then had a miscarriage due to a fall.
She lost His Majesty's favor due to her excessive grief.
Afterwards, she slandered Consort Nian, claiming she had killed her unborn child.
And for that, she was sent to the Cold Palace.
If you continue to succumb to despair,
you will eventually meet the same fate as those we have just seen.
Come quickly.
Concubine Wan.
Consort Qi, please forgive me.
Let it be. Go as far away as you can.
My lady, you forget yourself.
Consort Nian has fallen out of favor.
Consort Jing is incompetent. Consort Duan is gravely ill.
You are the most powerful Consort in the palace at this moment.
If you don't assert your authority by showing haughty superiority now,
who will even remember Consort Qi in the future?
My lady, think it over.
If not for this minx, how could His Majesty neglect us?
It was her pregnancy that claimed the life of my child!
I remember!
It's all your fault.
Lady Fucha says that my pregnancy claimed the life of her child.
Then what of my child? Who should be responsible for my loss?
You discovered your child at the very moment I lost mine.
When I suffered the most, you enjoyed your proudest moment.
If not you, then who was responsible?
Everything happens for a reason.
Good. Very good.
You even dare to offend me now.
Cuiguo, slap her until she bleeds at the mouth.
Begin.
Only when she feels pain,
will she realize how much of it she caused for Consort Qi and myself.
Young mistress, let's roll a boiled egg on your cheek.
It will reduce the swelling.
Why did you yield to Consort Qi?
It matters not. You may offend her openly.
Offend her openly?
Who am I now? How can I afford to do so?
Lady Fucha was right.
As I started feeling physical pain,
I began to realize how much pain remains in my heart.
Liuzhu.
Ask Xiao Yunzi to capture some butterflies.
Young mistress, it is hard to find butterflies at this season.
They are out of season now.
But I must obtain some.
They must be the most beautiful kind.
Yes, young mistress.
I greet Your Majesty and Your Highness.
I have arrived late for good reason. Your Majesty, please forgive me.
No matter. You may rise.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Why are you late? Did something happen?
I was passing by Yimei Garden and saw new plum blossoms.
I couldn't help but stop to view them, so I arrived late.
Have the plum blossoms in Yimei Garden all bloomed?
They have come into glorious full bloom.
Lady Hui, how could I miss such a wonderful sight?
Why don't you walk with me so we may enjoy it together?
With pleasure, Your Majesty.
Plum blossoms in the snows of winter. Don't keep this wonder to yourself.
Please bring us along as well.
I am a pious girl from the Zhen family without talent or virtue.
I was unable to carry an imperial heir to term.
Overwhelmed by guilt, I cannot look the Emperor in the face.
I sincerely pray that the Emperor will be blessed by Heaven,
have peace and joy
and enjoy long life and blessings.
If my wish should come to pass, I will renounce eating meat
and go without His Majesty's favor.
Huan Huan.
Is that you?
I am unable to look Your Majesty in the face.
Why are you unable? Do you no longer wish to see me?
Please come no closer.
Your hands are freezing cold. Have you no fear of falling ill again?
I only thought of my prayers for Your Majesty.
If I have caused Your Majesty concern, it is certainly my fault.
I must excuse myself now.
Such a sweet fragrance.
It is no surprise that butterflies are drawn to you even in wintertime.
In the same way, I am captivated by you.
I have prayed for Your Majesty day and night.
Bathing and burning incense, I dare not neglect the slightest detail.
This is wonderful.
Concubine Wan has not set foot outside her residence since the miscarriage.
I have been concerned for several months.
I have prayed for both of you day and night.
I wished for you both to be reconciled, without a breach between you any longer.
When was there ever a breach between Huan Huan and myself?
Never.
It is merely that I have not been well and could not serve Your Majesty.
I am incompetent. I am unable to win His Majesty's favor.
It is no fault of yours. Concubine Wan is overly competent.
You enjoyed His Majesty's favor exclusively
when she was absent.
But with her present, you are unable to share in it.
Huan has not served him for some time. He naturally feels a sense of novelty.
Then what of the future?
You have served His Majesty for quite some time.
Do you still want to catch his eye in the future?
Your Highness, please guide me.
In fact, we concubines should gather frequently for conversation.
If we are close, misunderstanding and dissent will disappear naturally.
We are all companions to His Majesty. There should be no dissent between us.
In such weather, I'm reminded of a story that took place in the wintertime.
I do not remember it very well,
but during the reign of the Han Emperor,
Consort Qi was in favor and offended Empress Lu.
Later, Empress Lu became Empress Dowager.
She chopped off Consort Qi's hands and legs,
gouged out her eyes, cut off her ears and made her mute.
She had her locked in the latrine and called her a "human swine."
Consort Qi had once been a great beauty.
It is a pity that she ended up that way.
Though Empress Lu was ruthless,
it was Consort Qi who dared humiliate her, having long been doted upon.
She brought great trouble upon herself indeed.
It is thus clear that Empress Lu was a very vindictive woman indeed.
Lady Fucha, don't you agree?
Jinxi, help Lady Fucha sit up properly.
We're just telling stories. Lady Fucha, what's the matter?
I have heard of another story that is even more horrifying.
During the Tang Dynasty, two concubines were made into "human swine."
Then they were immersed in wine jars.
They were called...
Bone Liquor.
These acts were utterly merciless,
but everything happens for a reason.
It was to be expected.
Young mistress, what's the matter?
Young mistress, wake up!
She first struck me as quite bold.
But she is merely a coward who made a display of her toughness.
Jinxi, Lady Fucha is not well. Carry her back to her residence.
Yes, mistress.
You would beat an defenseless dog to scare away a lion.
Now the dog has been beaten.
Having seen it, I eagerly await what you have to tell me.
It's a pleasure to speak with someone as clever as yourself. It's much easier.
You have been stained by the disgrace of Consort Nian.
Princess Wenyi has fallen into neglect as well.
It seems His Majesty has not visited you in about half a year.
It's my own fault for being so shortsighted.
I should have chosen a better master. To my chagrin, I chose wrongly.
I dare blame no other for that.
Yet you are still seen as closely tied to Consort Nian.
What will you do?
In truth, I am greatly concerned for my future.
I simply hope that Consort Nian will not cause me trouble.
In fact, you are equally as clever as Consort Nian.
You followed her in the past merely to secure your own standing.
Lady Fucha.
- They will make me into a human swine. - Who would do that?
- My lady, help! - It's impossible. No one would dare.
- Don't let them! - It's impossible.
You.
- What has happened to your mistress? - Nothing, my lady.
But a few days ago, she had a talk with Concubine Wan and Lady Cao.
She fainted then and has remained in this state since she was revived.
- Did Concubine Wan intimidate her? - It made no sense.
Lady Cao was there as well. But she didn't have such a shock.
Young mistress, Consort Qi is outside. She asks to see you urgently.
I don't have time.
Go tell her that Lady Fucha's state will not bring trouble upon her.
Tell her to behave.
Yes, my lady.
Consort Nian is said to be ruthless and brash. Everyone fears her iron fist.
But these tactics may prove quite effective
in dealing with those who oppose you.
I must learn the essence of Consort Nian's style and use it in the future.
In the past, I was subjected to cruel oppression.
It is time to change that situation.
How does it feel to wait for someone who never comes?
Now I finally understand.
I wonder if I keep watch like this,
will His Majesty finally arrive?
My lady, rest easy.
General Nian has sent word that he knows you are neglected.
He has made a compact with Duke Dun
to sound out His Majesty's true intentions.
No matter what may have happened, why did he realign himself with Duke Dun?
Though Duke Dun, the 10th prince, has helped him in the past,
it is improper to be closely associated with him.
You have returned.
Your Majesty, I rode hard on a swift horse and intercepted this.
From a carrier pigeon at Duke Dun's residence.
As I expected, Duke Dun has won Nian Gengyao's support
to usurp the throne
and recognize Yunzi as Emperor,
as well as Consort Dowager Yi, mother of Yuntang, as Empress Dowager.
The 10th prince's plan will surely fail this time.
If he succeeds, the Qing Dynasty will come to an end.
Xia Yi.
Your Majesty.
Tell your men, the Guillotines,
to watch over Duke Dun's residence for me.
Tonight we will send the Cavalry Brigade to
surround his residence and capture them all.
Yes, Your Majesty.
I am deeply indebted to you.
I merely contributed my modest abilities.
Only you could go near Duke Dun's residence
without arousing suspicion.
This solid evidence gives you sufficient reason to send in your army.
Tonight I need you to watch over Duke Dun's residence for me.
- If anything happens, come immediately. - Yes, Your Majesty.
I greet Your Majesty.
- What progress? - All is well.
The Cavalry Brigade has captured Duke Dun.
I am indebted to you for your assistance in this matter.
I did not wish for you to witness such terrible strife between brothers.
I know it was difficult.
Time has passed and circumstances have changed.
When I look at Consort Nian, I shudder.
Fortunately, we granted Huanyi Incense to Consort Nian exclusively.
One of the ingredients is musk, which has already harmed her fertility.
If Consort Nian were ever to conceive a son,
Nian Gengyao would surely support the child as heir to the throne.
Once they forced you to abdicate,
then you and I
would lose everything and no longer live in peace.
In the past, when Consort Nian was with child,
I had no choice but to kill my own child.
How could it not bring pain?
At the time, we had Consort Duan carry it out.
Since she has taken all of the blame,
you should let it go now.
So far I've lost a great many children.
Who knows if that is not a punishment from heaven?
I personally measured out the drug and had it sent to Consort Nian.
If someone is to be punished, it should not be you to bear the worst.
Consort Nian is pitiful, but her brother Nian Gengyao is to blame.
He is accustomed to acting with arrogance.
If he had admitted his errors sooner,
he would not have reached the point of impeachment by all of the officials.
Your Highness, please forgive me. I am guilty.
I don't understand. What is it?
I was fully aware of something but have hidden it from all others until now.
I dare not hide it anymore.
What is it? Tell me.
Consort Nian took bribes from officials outside the palace.
Then she introduced them to General Nian for promotion.
Consort Nian threatened me
that if I dared tell anyone, she would kill the princess and myself.
Your Highness, how could Consort Nian be so brazen?
- How much did she receive? - I have no idea.
But the total could be in the hundreds of thousands.
His Majesty cannot abide corruption.
I never thought it could happen in the harem!
- Bitch! - Consort Nian, what is this?
How dare you betray me!
Have you forgotten how you came this far?
You were ready to do anything to curry favor with me.
You faithless wretch!
You have all heard Consort Nian.
She has close ties with Lady Cao.
For that reason, what Lady Cao just said is credible.
Jianqiu, report to His Majesty.
Ask the Office of Punishment to interrogate
the servants at Yikun Palace, every one.
Especially Zhou Ninghai.
The crimes committed by Consort Nian are too numerous to be listed.
Your Majesty, how do you intend to dispose of Consort Nian?
Consort Nian has shown insufficient virtue for a high-ranking concubine.
She is hereby demoted to Second Attendant.
His Majesty is benevolent and treats the concubines with leniency.
I have faith that Attendant Nian will repent and reform.
I thank Your Majesty on behalf of Attendant Nian.
Which eligible girls from deserving families
will now be selected for the harem?
We must give encouragement to those meritorious officials.
Quite a few officials contributed to the suppression of Duke Dun.
In accordance with Your Majesty's intent,
I selected Guwalgiya Wenyuan,
daughter of Censor-in-chief, Guwalgiya E'min,
and Li Ying, sister to the Vice Commander of the Cavalry Brigade, Li Bin.
You may decide, Your Majesty.
The Li family belongs to the Han Banners.
Exactly.
The Guwalgiya family belongs to the Bordered Yellow Banner of the Manchu.
There are not many concubines from the Manchu Banners.
- It is well to add one more. - Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, which rank you will grant her?
Grant her an honorific name as Noble Lady Qi.
She will enter the palace on the first of November.
Your Majesty, are you still concerned about Nian Gengyao?
Nian Gengyao has been discharged of all his posts.
He is assigned to guard the gate.
If he can act dutifully, then I will show him mercy.
Yet Nian Gengyao performed guard duty
in the Imperial Yellow Jacket I awarded him.
He swaggered through the streets and rumors were aroused.
He would have the people think that I am an unrighteous emperor.
Perhaps Nian Gengyao wishes to remind you of his former merits by the Yellow Jacket.
However, he thinks only of himself, ignoring Your Majesty's prestige.
How can I be mindful of his former merits?
Your Majesty.
Attendant Nian is outside. She asks to see Your Majesty.
I refuse.
Your Majesty.
It doesn't matter how you punish me.
I only hope you spare my brother's life.
You may keep him as a dog or a horse to serve at your side.
Your Majesty.
I beg you, Your Majesty.
Considering his service in calming Qinghai Province,
we cannot bear to use capital punishment.
Nian Gengyao will take his own life, Nian Fu will be beheaded.
All sons above the age of fifteen will be exiled to the borderlands.
I greet Your Highness the Empress and all the concubines of the palace.
You may rise.
Thank you, Your Highness.
As expected, you are a true beauty.
Come forward and let me have a closer look.
Yes, Your Highness.
From the gifts given by the Empress,
choose some fine things for Concubine Wan,
as a token of my gratitude for sharing the same palace.
Who is this that refuses to bow before Lady Qi?
I wondered who it might be. It turns out to be Consort Hua.
It appears you are quite forgetful, my lady.
You still behave as in the old glorious times of your family.
But you forget that even rats will abandon a sinking ship.
Even rats will abandon a sinking ship.
Well said indeed.
You were admitted to the harem to reward your family's loyalty.
What is the difference between yourself and the old me?
You believed you were living out a dream.
But in the end, your fate will be the same as mine.
A mere low-ranking Second Attendant. How dare you offend me!
Wait until I inform the Empress and Concubine Wan.
And what of the Empress? And what of Concubine Wan?
Didn't I defeat them before?
Besides, you are merely a pawn who relies on their power and standing.
Even though they may rest easy for the present,
are you certain they will not fall from their high position someday?
We shall wait and watch.
I am told Lady Qi was quite upset last night.
It's natural for a girl to be in low spirits at times.
She is not one to be troubled over trifles.
There must be a reason for her sulking.
The only reason is Attendant Nian.
What is wrong with her? Even after all that has happened, she is restless.
She offends her superiors repeatedly.
His Majesty is lenient time and again.
Yet she chafes at it and refuses to repent.
She shows little thanks for His Majesty's clemency.
Tell me, what should be done?
Nian Gengyao has passed away.
Your Majesty has shown great mercy by allowing Attendant Nian to live.
Now that she refuses to repent,
must she not be severely punished?
Kill her to calm the anger of all the other concubines.
Come.
You are quite astute.
And remorseless as well.
I've just heated the tranquilizer prescribed by the imperial doctor.
Mistress, take it before you sleep.
My lady, Lady Cao has died.
Go first to make arrangements. I will arrive later.
Go.
Several days ago, I saw that Cao Qinmo was not well.
But how could she die so suddenly?
Doctor Wen told me secretly
that His Majesty and the Empress Dowager were unable to tolerate her.
They instructed the maid to drug her.
It was she who betrayed Attendant Nian Shilan.
Everyone will assume
that Cao Qinmo died tormented by her guilt.
Cao Qinmo was an adept in intrigue.
But no matter how calculating she was,
she could never match His Majesty and the Empress Dowager.
Cao Qinmo betrayed Consort Hua for her own advantage.
She was likely to betray another someday.
Mistress, do it quickly. Burning offerings to the dead is against palace custom.
If we are discovered, we will be punished severely.
Only you and I remain at Yikun Palace.
I am not allowed outside the Forbidden City.
I have no choice but to honor my brother right here.
Where else?
I remain alive, but I am no different from a dead person.
Mistress, don't be sad. You have many years ahead of you.
His Majesty is utterly ruthless.
It is all on account of that wretched Zhen Huan.
Even after my dying breath,
I will not forgive her.
Where is Suxi?
He has already left to fulfill your orders, mistress.
- A report, my lady. - What is it?
I have noticed something in the past few days.
It seems one has been observing us from outside.
Did you see him clearly?
Yes. He pretended to be sweeping the road.
In fact, he was hiding at the foot of the wall to spy.
Did you see his face? Which palace is he from?
He is a eunuch who serves Attendant Nian, named Suxi.
Since Zhou Ninghai was terminated, Suxi has been serving Attendant Nian.
I also observed that he was carrying flint.
His intent is malicious.
He has not yet had a chance only because we are heavily guarded.
Do not stop him.
But keep watch on him secretly.
- No rash actions to alert the enemy. - Understood.
- Where is Lady Qi? Has she returned? - My lady, you've forgotten.
After the opera, Lady Qi went to dine at Consort Jing's palace.
The snow outside has just melted.
She may not find her way home in the night.
Light more lanterns at the door of her residence.
Suxi is here. He snuck into the side chamber where Lady Qi resides.
He's waited so many days. He finally has a chance to carry it out.
That depends on whether you allow him to do so.
If I don't help him, then how can he report back to his mistress?
What kind of riddles are the two of you playing?
First go outside and wait there. Then catch him once the blaze gets strong.
Yes, mistress.
Mei.
Do you want to see Nian Shilan dig her own grave?
Lady Qi's side chamber and warm room is connected to my quarters here.
If the flames grow and come through, I won't stand a chance.
The Osmanthus oil is for brushing hair. Why are you pouring it out?
Don't say a word.
You must tell me what you're planning.
Nian Shilan sent her servant to burn me to death.
I have harmed no others, but I will not let others harm me.
You are going to assist her.
We will use her ploy to our advantage.
Very well, if we are to put on a show, then we must give it our all.
I don't want to leave her any chance to live.
Fire! There's a fire!
Fire! Hurry!
Fire!
- Who is it? Who was lurking there? - This is the one who started the fire.
His Majesty the Emperor!
- It's all right now. Don't be frightened. - Mei was--
Lady Hui, how is your wound?
She must be in shock.
It was all my fault. Why did I ask her to join me for chess?
Concubine Wan, please rest easy.
Lady Hui's mental state is not at issue. Yet she was badly burned.
How could a fire start so suddenly?
Where is the lead eunuch here?
Your Majesty, please forgive me. I was overly careless.
But I have caught the man who started the fire. He awaits your judgment.
- Did someone set the blaze? - Yes, Your Majesty.
- Bring him here. - Yes, sir.
Bring him!
When the fire broke out, this eunuch was lurking outside Suiyu Pavilion.
I found flint and oil on his person. He was caught with solid evidence.
What palace are you from?
Your Majesty, he serves Attendant Nian at Yikun Palace. He is named Suxi.
What have I done to displease him
that he should try to burn the palace and end my life?
Fortunately, the servants noticed.
Otherwise, I would have lost my life and could never see Your Majesty again.
Your Majesty, I was told Attendant Nian never got along with Concubine Wan.
Now she's fallen into disgrace. Of course she must hate us both.
He is merely a low eunuch.
He would not dare burn down Suiyu Pavilion.
Someone must be behind this.
At first, I intended to show her mercy.
I wanted to give her an opportunity to make a new beginning.
Who could foresee that she would grow even more vicious?
Let it be.
Tell the Empress and Consort Jing
to interrogate Suxi overnight.
If his crime is proven,
send Nian to the Cold Palace at once to take her own life.
- No need to report to me. - Yes, Your Majesty.
My residence is smaller than Suiyu Pavilion.
Please tolerate this and stay here for now.
I am very happy indeed that I can stay here.
The new year is coming.
Nian Shilan's interrogation must come to an end before New Year's.
It would be unpropitious otherwise.
Today is the 25th.
The 29th should be the latest.
She will surely die.
Otherwise, I burned myself in vain.
As soon as your wound heals, I will let you use the healing balm.
It is the most effective way to erase the scars.
Jinxi.
Did Eunuch Su say at what time he would send Nian to death?
At the Cold Palace, sentences are always carried out in the evening.
I need to see off Consort Hua.
Why was the Emperor fond of you? Do you know?
Is it because of your beauty?
The palace has never lacked for beautiful women.
You say that His Majesty doted on me
simply because I am sister to Nian Gengyao?
You knew it full well in your heart.
- Why deceive yourself and the others? - Nonsense!
Why has His Majesty never truly loved me?
Even if he did,
you and Nian Gengyao have been overbearing for so many years.
And that true love
may long have been erased completely.
How would you know, wench?
When I first entered his household, he was still a Duke.
I became Secondary Princess Consort.
I was his favorite at the time.
He said I was the only woman he loved.
However, there were many women around him.
More than enough to arouse my jealousy.
He stayed with one concubine one night.
Then he stayed with another the next.
Have you ever stayed up waiting for someone until dawn?
I knew from the beginning that he was the Emperor.
I will never be the only woman to pass the night with him.
Of course.
My affection for His Majesty has been far greater than yours.
Later I conceived a child. He was very happy.
But gradually, the happy moments grew fewer and fewer.
I could feel it.
The third prince was the only child growing up at his residence.
I knew that he was worried.
So I told him
there was no need to worry.
I would give birth to a prince for him.
Yet not long after that,
I took the medicinal tonic served to me by Consort Duan and I lost my child!
The imperial doctor told me
that the child had already grown into a baby boy.
You lost your child,
so you wanted my child to be buried alongside yours?
He was only four months in my belly.
And you planned to put him to death.
I never planned to kill your child!
It was your lack of strength
that made you miscarry after kneeling for only an hour.
All women who dare vie with me for His Majesty's favor must die.
Before, I instructed Yu to kill you with drugs.
But I never thought of killing your child.
Though it was not your intent,
were it not for the Huanyi Incense in your palace,
I would not have become so weak
and miscarried after kneeling for only an hour.
The Huanyi Incense?
Do you know why you never conceived another child after your miscarriage?
Did you know that Huanyi Incense contains a large amount of musk?
You have been using it for a great many years.
Of course you would never conceive again.
Utter nonsense!
That incense was granted to me by His Majesty!
His Majesty.
Impossible.
It's impossible.
If it were not by His Majesty's decre--
It can't be.
Why didn't any imperial doctor tell you about the musk?
Not only did he make you barren,
but he also caused your miscarriage.
It was by His Majesty's decree as well.
The medicinal tonic given by Consort Duan
only served as a dissimulation to cover His Majesty's role.
No matter how much safflower you have forced Consort Duan to take,
it will not bring back your child.
Why?
Because you are from the Nian family.
His Majesty has long been vigilant against Nian Gengyao.
He'd never let you give birth to a child bearing the blood of the Nian family.
Your Majesty.
Your Majesty!
You have caused me so much pain!
Has Nian Shilan's funeral ended?
She died in such a tragic way.
It seems you feel ambivalence towards her today.
I thought I hated her very existence.
But now that she has died, I only feel melancholy.
In the beginning, she married a Duke and was favored.
Who could foresee, after holding such power and prestige for years,
that the man who shared her bed would scheme against her
and bring her to such an end?
Isn't it only natural in the palace?
Intrigues for His Majesty's favor.
Intrigues for status.
We intrigue for our desires. Why not the Emperor as well?
Can we not survive without intrigue?
This balm was made by Lingrong. It can remove scars.
You try it first.
If it proves effective, I will ask her to prepare more of it.
It smells sweet indeed. The scent tells me it is a good thing.
Young mistress, what is that?
This is a healing balm for removing scars.
Could you let me take a look?
Is something wrong?
I have already used several boxes, yet never felt any ill effects.
I cannot tell right now.
Would you let me take a sample and examine it?
Yes, Doctor Wen, please examine it carefully.
By the way, Your Majesty,
there are many vacant positions in the Imperial Harem.
Do you intend to select concubines to fill those openings?
Tell me your thoughts.
According to protocol, you may have one
Imperial Noble Consort, two Noble Consorts,
four Consorts, six Imperial Concubines,
and the remaining positions are not limited.
At present, you have three Consorts, Consort Duan, Consort Jing and Consort Qi,
with one Imperial Concubine, Concubine Wan.
Several positions remain to be filled.
There is no hurry to fill the positions of Noble Consort and Imperial Noble Consort.
Yet we may add one more Consort.
Let's promote Concubine Wan to Consort.
I am not qualified yet.
It is not a matter of qualifications.
Concubine Wan has outstanding virtues.
Naturally she should be promoted to Consort.
Yet it has not been long since she joined the harem and she has no child.
Someday when she gives birth to a prince,
we will promote her to Consort. It would be a great honor to her.
No matter.
We shall promote her to Consort Wan.
Your Majesty and Your Highness, thank you for your kindness.
- Rise. - Huan, congratulations. It's a great joy.
You are eager to congratulate Huan. Did you think you would be excluded?
Lady An will be promoted to Concubine An as well.
Choose an auspicious day for their conferring.
Let these two close friends be conferred on the same day.
Besides, First Attendant Xin has been serving me for quite some time.
Attendant Xin will be promoted to Noble Lady.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Thank you, Your Highness.
Congratulations, An.
My Lady, we congratulate you on your promotion to Consort.
- You may rise. - Thank you, my lady.
Huanbi, see the Conferring Officer off. Don't forget to bring some gifts.
My lady, after the conferring ceremony, you receive instruction from the Empress.
You must show gratitude to His Majesty and Her Highness.
The Conferring Officer reminded me just now.
Liuzhu, fetch my gown and help me put it on.
Yes, mistress.
- Hurry, unfold it and see. - It's exquisite.
Oh, this is-- What will we do now?
The conferring ceremony gown is granted by His Majesty.
How can it be damaged?
If discovered later, it will be regarded as a deception of the Emperor.
Liuzhu, where is Director Jiang of the Household Department?
He just accepted our gifts. He is still in the courtyard.
- Bring him here. - Yes, mistress.
Hurry, as quickly as possible.
It's all my fault.
My headache began so suddenly.
Yet we should not miss this auspicious moment.
No matter. You may stay inside until you are well.
Empress Wan Wan?
Your Majesty, may blessings and peace be with you.
Wan Wan, why didn't you call me "my dear"?
My dear.
Wan Wan.
Wan Wan, you've finally returned.
I, Zhen Huan, bow in respect before Your Majesty.
What are you doing here?
I greet Your Majesty.
Where did you get this gown?
Impudence!
Your Majesty.
How could this happen? Huichun, how could this happen?
The other day, as Her Highness tidied Empress Chunyuan's things,
she found that two southern pearls were missing from this gown
and that silk threads were loose as well.
So I took it to the Imperial Household Department for repair.
I meant to retrieve it when I had time.
But I have been occupied these two days and forgot to retrieve it.
I don't know how this gown came to be worn by Consort Wan.
- Please forgive me, Your Highness. - Fool! How many times have I told you?
You must take extra care with Empress Chunyuan's belongings.
How dare you disregard my words!
Any other dress would be suitable.
Why did it have to be this one?
She was wearing this when we first met.
Remove it.
I have been careless.
I put on Empress Chunyuan's clothing by mistake.
Consort Wan has been meticulous in all matters.
It surely wasn't intentional.
Explain what happened.
Before leaving for the Empress's palace, I found that my gown was torn.
So I borrowed a replacement from the Imperial Household Department.
I did not know the origin of this dress.
I did not mean to offend Empress Chunyuan.
- Your Majesty, please forgive me. - Consort Wan is--
Consort Wan?
Even though the conferring ceremony has been performed,
she has not yet received instruction, and the ceremony is incomplete.
Suiyu Pavilion has been restored.
Return there to reflect on your errors.
By order of His Majesty,
Suiyu Pavilion will be closed off. No one is allowed access.
Who are you?
Director Jiang has been sentenced to death by imperial decree.
I am the new director of the Imperial Household Department.
Men, close the door.
Yes, sir.
What is this?
He who fails to fulfill his duties, will pay for it with his head.
Yes, Director Gou.
What is this?
Don't disturb the young mistress.
Young mistress, I should be held responsible for this matter as well.
I thought the gown looked familiar to me.
But I did not recall that it was Empress Chunyuan's dress.
And Director Jiang never served Empress Chunyuan.
It appears we have fallen into another trap.
Oh, Empress.
You have truly outdone yourself with this scheme.
Mistress, why do you suspect her?
If not at the Empress's command,
who would dare touch the belongings of Empress Chunyuan?
How could it be a coincidence?
"When the shepherds quarrel, the wolf has a winning hand."
I am merely a pawn in the Empress's hands.
You have never been disloyal to her.
Yet you have been elevated continuously and doted on by His Majesty.
This has likely inspired envy and dread in the Empress.
I have fallen from His Majesty's favor,
and the Empress rejects me.
Moreover, this matter concerns Empress Chunyuan.
It is the deepest grief that lies upon His Majesty's heart.
I'm afraid that what happened today
cannot take a favorable turn in a short time.
We can only wait for an opportunity.
An opportunity?
At this moment,
what difference is there between this place and the Cold Palace?
Let it be.
Wan Wan?
In His Majesty's heart,
I am merely a substitute for Empress Chunyuan.
My dear elder sister, you are good to me indeed.
Though you have been dead so many years,
even now you still support me and protect me.
If His Majesty shows mercy to her again,
I am afraid your efforts will be in vain, Your Highness.
This time, even if His Majesty shows mercy to her again,
I'm afraid Concubine Wan will no longer be the same.
Concubine Wan is a very proud woman.
Though she has been doted on for years, she now knows she is merely a substitute.
How can she bear it?
It turns out your true purpose was to plunge her to the depths of despair.
Truly admirable.
Guards, please open the door!
Concubine Wan is ill.
I, Xiao Yunzi, beg you on my knees.
Guard, Concubine Wan is gravely ill.
Please, His Majesty ordered her confinement.
He did not forbid her to see a doctor.
Why not have a drink with your comrades? Guard, I beg you.
By His Majesty's decree, no one is allowed to leave the palace.
Nothing else matters. Close the door.
Don't close the door!
Guard, I beg you.
Open the door, please.
Young mistress.
I am truly useless, unable to send for a doctor.
Let it be. Do not trouble the guards.
I can endure it.
Liuzhu, help me get up to take a walk.
Young mistress, what do you wish?
Taking a stroll may refresh me somewhat.
Young mistress, what is it?
- What are you doing? - Don't stop me!
- What are you doing? - Let me out!
- Step aside. - Back!
- Back, impudent one! - My lady has collapsed.
Let go of me. Let me out.
Who dares come forward?
Out of the way!
Liuzhu!
Liuzhu.
Your Majesty, I have an urgent matter to report.
Speak.
Servants at Suiyu Pavilion tried to break out.
The guards were diligent in their duties.
- A maid was injured in the conflict. - Do you know the reason?
Your Majesty, they said that Concubine Wan had collapsed.
The servants wanted to leave and send for a doctor.
The guards were faithful to your orders and would not let them leave--
Impudence!
I ordered her to be confined.
How dare you prevent her from seeing a doctor!
If Concubine Wan should have a mishap, will you take the blame?
I am guilty and deserve death.
Send the captain of the guard to the Office of Punishment.
Yes, Your Majesty.
- Su Peisheng. - Your Majesty.
Send the imperial doctor to Concubine Wan.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Report her latest condition to me at once.
- It must be Doctor Wen! - Yes, Your Majesty.
She is awake.
Do not move.
Chilblain ointment was just applied to your hands. You need to recuperate.
You must be hungry.
Come. Bring it here.
Doctor Wen prescribed a stew of
edible bird's nest with donkey-hide gelatin.
Please take it while it's warm.
Doctor Wen.
My lady, I congratulate you.
Congratulations, my lady.
My lady, Doctor Wen says that you are with child, one month.
Jinxi.
You and Doctor Wen remain here.
The rest of you may leave.
Doctor, what do you think of my condition?
This is your only chance to reestablish yourself.
His Majesty has already heard about this. He ordered me to care for you, my lady.
The Empress ordered that extra care be taken with your diet and daily activities.
My lady, you may rest easy now.
Really?
Doctor, do you think it is possible to reestablish myself?
If this is so,
you have said quite a few things,
why did you not mention the lifting of my confinement?
And His Majesty sends me no words of comfort.
Besides, your caretaking
is meant for my child only.
Not for me.
My lady.
Do not worry.
No matter how difficult,
I will not give up on myself or make this child suffer.
That is well.
Lady Hui and I feared you would be tormented.
On your word, my lady,
I shall spare no effort in caring for you.
Young mistress, you now carry a child.
What you eat nourishes the both of you. You'd better take as much as you can.
Where is Liuzhu?
She hasn't had enough rest lately.
She caught cold and is sleeping.
- I should look in on her. - Young mistress.
Liuzhu has just fallen asleep.
And you have just woken up.
Why not visit her later?
Don't try to stop me. I must look in on her.
Young mistress.
Young mistress, it's not needed.
Liuzhu is--
She is no longer here.
What did you say?
Young mistress, how do you think Doctor Wen was admitted?
The guards outside the palace did not listen to our pleas.
It was Liuzhu who threw herself onto the blade.
Fearing they had caused a death, the guards sent for Doctor Wen.
But Liuzhu--
She is no longer here.
Huanbi, you--
I should have concealed it, lest it endanger your child.
My lady, I know you are upset.
But no matter how upset you are now, you must understand
that your own health is the most important thing now.
Liuzhu died for you, my lady.
Do not let it be in vain.
Only when you have preserved yourself, will you be able to avenge Liuzhu.
From childhood, Liuzhu and I grew up together.
She was a true sister to me.
Young mistress, don't!
My lady, your hands have just been bandaged.
If you hurt yourself,
when you want to avenge Liuzhu in the future,
you will be strong in will but weak in power.
Yes, indeed.
Only if I live well,
will Liuzhu's death not be in vain.
Queen Mother, may blessings and peace be with you.
- You may rise. - Yes, Your Highness.
Whether I enjoy peace matters not.
Whether the child of the Emperor is safe is my true concern.
Do you refer to Concubine Wan's pregnancy?
I was told by His Majesty,
that Concubine Wan was hoping you would take charge of her health.
I am incompetent and lack virtue.
I can't even preserve my own eldest prince.
You are capable of this. I trust you on this point.
Since you entrust me with such a task, I dare not refuse.
You may preserve yourself only when you try to protect others.
Yes, Your Highness.
Consort Hua was arrogant and domineering in her day.
But once she fell into disgrace, everyone persecuted her mercilessly.
I also realized at that time
that Consort Hua was merely a pawn of His Majesty and the Empress Dowager
used to restrain her brother Nian Gengyao who held unparalleled power at the time.
Before her death, I went to see her
so she would realize the truth in the end.
I never imagined it was Empress Wenyu
who would gain from our conflict after all.
I brought Consort Hua to the depths of despair,
and Empress Wenyu brought me to the depths of despair.
Empress Dowager.
Empress Dowager, what's the matter?
I am growing old now. My sight already fails me.
It cannot be.
Your Highness, you are unchanged from your youth.
Your sedan chair is ready now.
We have already walked much today.
Why not return and rest?
Very well, let's return.
Yes, Your Highness.