Lingrong used to sing so well,
her voice sonorous and resounding.
Ever since her voice grew hoarse,
she struggled to devise a way, planning to use ice dancing
to win His Majesty's favor.
Lingrong appeared meek and mild,
but deep down, she was cold and cruel.
She sent me the healing balm knowing full well that it was poisonous.
She resented me, and all the others,
believing that she had been exploited.
Human nature is unfathomable.
We were once like sisters to one another, but ended up as enemies.
These congratulatory gifts are almost identical.
Set aside the ordinary gifts to bestow upon others.
Most are forgettable, except for this coral bracelet from Marquess Guo.
It is of exquisite craftsmanship.
"The coral in my palm I may not keep,
for it has become the flower of the royal palace."
Mei is unwell. We shall visit her.
I wish you good fortune, Noble Consort Xi.
Halt.
You must be in high spirits to take a stroll, Lady Ning.
I am merely wandering about.
I shall soon return and rest with Tuanrong.
Your cat, Tuanrong, is very lovely.
Has she grown bigger?
If you are curious, my lady, please come to Chunxi Hall now.
Yet you are always followed by so many servants.
Tuanrong may be too frightened to call out.
My lady, you do know Tuanrong's call is truly alluring.
On such a beautiful night,
we shall take a stroll together while the mood inspires us.
I accept your invitation
and shall visit your residence.
Do not follow us.
What are you doing?
My lady, do not disdain this dagger.
I was once hurt by a foolish leopard.
I later stole into the leopard garden and slit its throat.
Huanbi, if you cry out,
I might slit her throat by accident.
You don't need to frighten Huanbi. You've resented me for long, haven't you?
Otherwise, you would not have had Tuanrong call out for all of those cats,
hoping to kill me along with my unborn child.
You knew it all along,
yet you have long tolerated me calmly.
I do not wish to assail you for your mad love.
You are now His Majesty's favorite.
It is not worth killing me
over Marquess Guo.
You knew.
You cherish silk tree flowers above your own health.
Besides, I was told
that Marquess Guo sent for an imperial doctor
to rescue you from death.
But what would he think if he learned that he had saved a wicked soul?
His Lordship was kind to save you, but you are vicious and cruel.
You don't deserve to harbor feelings for him.
You remained silent when you heard I had harmed your mistress,
yet the mere mention of His Lordship arouses your anger.
You–
You fiend.
If I am a fiend, then Noble Consort Xi is foremost among all fiends.
You found love in Ganlu Temple,
but you showed insatiable desire and seduced His Majesty once again.
The Marquess Guo that I know
is the bravest and the most gallant man in the world.
I have never seen him so frustrated and weary.
When you returned to the palace, my suspicions were aroused,
but they were confirmed at the mid-autumn family feast.
- It was you eavesdropping. - What is it to you?
You think I don't deserve to have feelings for His Lordship.
But you are even less worthy.
You have no idea.
It is so much harder to betray the one you love.
Where did you get this? This coral bracelet
is His Lordship's favorite treasure
which he obtained in the Nan Hai Sea some years ago.
He has never shown it to anyone. What are you doing with it?
You should ask its owner.
His Lordship owes you nothing.
Why can't he forget you?
So be it.
His Lordship loves you, heart and soul.
If you have any feeling left at all, it shall weigh on your conscience forever.
The bit of kindness His Lordship has shown me
may well mean nothing to you.
But for me, it is a warmth found but once in a lifetime.
- What a lunatic! - Let her be.
Lady Ning is of a passionate nature.
Look, my lady!
- Sister Huan! - Yurao!
- Miss Yurao. - Greetings, my lady.
Yurao, let me see your face.
YURAO
It's a joy to reunite after years apart. Why the tears, Sister Huan?
His Majesty is delighted with the twins, so your family has been invited to visit.
His Majesty also said
that Miss Yurao can settle in the palace to keep you company.
I don't see my parents. Are they here, too?
Justice Zhen is still recovering from his illness.
His Majesty has summoned your mother to the palace.
To ease your mind, my lady, Miss Yurao rushed here to visit you.
You shall meet your parents in the palace shortly, my lady.
The Imperial Medical Bureau has made
this slimming balm for you, young mistress.
Despite reducing your weight, your body should remain firm.
Apply more on my waist.
Young mistress, it is done.
Baoque, help me–
Young mistress, are you all right?
Young mistress! Young mistress!
Concubine An collapsed at Yanxi Palace.
Has the imperial doctor attended to her?
Yes, my lady.
But Concubine An refused to have the imperial doctor examine her.
The maid who sent for the doctor
said Concubine An collapsed from being on a strict regimen.
Her diet, for what?
Since she fell out of favor,
it is said she secretly practices for the ice festival every day.
All the Emperors of our dynasty have had high regard for the ice games,
so an ice festival is held every year.
An Lingrong is quite clever to strive for His Majesty's favor in this way.
The ice games must be practiced from childhood.
As for the ice dance,
dancers are required to be lithe and flexible,
not skills to be acquired in a short span of time.
But I know of a way to obtain immediate results.
In the Han Dynasty, Zhao Feiyan found favor with Emperor Cheng.
She was a slender and agile dancer, for she used a weight reducing treatment.
Pressed into the navel, a substance is absorbed into the flesh
that whitens the skin and wards off weight.
The complexion is brightened.
However, it contains musk.
I have heard that a bath of azalea flower infusion
can serve as an antidote to the musk toxins.
If that were true,
the Zhao sisters, Feiyan and Hede, having such great power,
would have conceived children after using up all the azalea flowers.
If Concubine An is told of this,
she will treat it as an invaluable treasure.
The treatment is truly effective. You have lost much weight, my lady.
But its effect is far too potent. I am worried–
It is of no concern.
Tomorrow is New Year's Eve.
I know the amount of musk contained in it.
Please bathe in the azalea flower infusion, my lady.
In any case, I have consumed many different medicines all these years.
Whether I take such a bath or not makes little difference.
The ice festival of last year was spectacular.
I greatly admired the performance of "Nezha and the Dragon King."
The Taizu Emperor was adept at skating.
When he led his skating team, they were even faster than horses.
I was told that when Your Majesty was the Fourth Prince,
you always triumphed in the competition of mounted archery on ice.
Concubine An.
May blessings be with you, Your Majesty.
It's freezing. Take care lest you fall ill.
Concubine An may aptly be given the name "Flying Swallow of the Ice."
It recalls the "Flying Wild Goose" danced by Noble Consort Xi.
They are both as graceful as sprites.
I dare not compare myself to Noble Consort Xi,
for I merely follow her example.
Very well then. We shall spend the New Year together.
As you wish, Your Majesty.
Lotus blossoms abound to be picked to the south of the Yangtze
Fields of lotus leaves...
Baoque.
- Empty this censer. - Yes, my lady.
How is Mei progressing?
In less than a fortnight, Concubine Hui will be in labor.
She has been well nourished and her condition is stable.
Every time, you say the same words.
But the more I hear them, the more it puts me at ease.
Sister Huan.
Miss Yurao, you run fast. Please mind your step.
Jinxi will take care of me here. You may leave now.
Yes, Miss Yurao.
Xiao Yunzi is flying a kite with Hongyan. Would you like to see? It must be fun.
No, you may go on your own.
I bow before Noble Consort Xi.
You may rise.
The Empress requests your presence in Jingren Palace at once.
What is it?
JINGREN PALACE
Lady Qi, you insist on making an accusation against Noble Consort Xi
and request the presence of all concubines of the Imperial Harem.
State your accusation.
I accuse Noble Consort Xi of infidelity,
a stain upon the Imperial Palace not even death can atone for.
Palace custom is strict! Lady Qi, do not spout nonsense!
I swear by my Guwalgiya clan.
If any part of what I say is false, may my clan perish, leaving no progeny.
Since you accuse her of infidelity, tell me who the adulterer is.
Doctor Wen Shichu.
Wen Shichu is a trusted personal doctor. He takes her pulse daily.
It is no surprise if proximity breeds fondness.
What both of you have said is pure conjecture.
It is reasonable for Doctor Wen
to treat Noble Consort Xi when she falls ill.
Moreover, Doctor Wen has long been close to her maternal family.
It is fitting that they look after one another in the palace.
How could this be considered infidelity?
In other words, they were childhood playmates.
You are spouting nonsense. Do you have any proof?
Yes, of course.
Before Noble Consort Xi was selected for service, Doctor Wen proposed to her.
- I bow before Your Highness. - Raise your head and speak.
Bin-er?
It's you.
You do recognize her, Noble Consort Xi.
She married Chen Si, a servant of my family.
She previously served the Zhen family.
I ask only one question. When you served the Zhen family,
did Wen Shichu ask for the hand of Zhen Huan,
who you see before you now as Noble Consort Xi?
Speak aloud before the Empress! Has Chen Si taught you no manners?
A fortnight before the auditions, Doctor Wen did propose marriage.
However,
he did not propose formally...
but in private with Noble Consort Xi.
- Did Noble Consort Xi accept? - No, no, she–
If Noble Consort Xi and Doctor Wen were truly in love,
they would not be here at present.
Their presence means that Noble Consort Xi has nothing to hide
regarding her friendship with Doctor Wen.
Lady Qi, if it were true
that Noble Consort Xi and Doctor Wen had a love affair,
they would take great pains to conceal it.
The best way to conceal a misdeed is not to commit one in the first place.
But if you do commit one, someday it will reveal itself.
Feiwen of Yongshou Palace has witnessed this several times.
Feiwen, when was this? What did you observe?
Tell me everything exactly as it happened.
One day, Noble Consort Xi was talking with Doctor Wen.
Few servants were there.
I went in with Miss Yurao,
and then I saw
Doctor Wen was touching her hand.
They were sitting still, their gaze fixed upon each other.
Doctor Wen drew back his hand as soon as he saw us.
The cuff of his robe was exposed, which goes against decency.
It was embroidered with five bamboo leaves.
Thinking it over afterwards,
I feared Noble Consort Xi would kill me if she knew what I had seen.
Therefore, I begged Lady Qi to save me.
An insignificant maid has already seen quite a lot.
But when none is watching, there must be further misdeeds.
This could have serious consequences.
Bring Doctor Wen here for questioning.
I bow before Your Highness and all the young mistresses.
You may rise.
Doctor Wen, excuse me.
This embroidery is unique. Do you always wear it on your cuff?
Your Highness, my mother is fond of bamboo,
so she embroiders bamboo leaves on my cuff to remind me of my family.
Your Highness,
the embroidery on his cuff is nothing new.
If one pays attention, it will be noticed.
It means nothing.
How strange for an imperial doctor to speak face-to-face with a Noble Consort,
his cuffs rolled up as if he were at home.
In the future, imperial doctors may enter a Noble Consort's palace,
rolling up their cuffs or taking off their clothes,
in fact, doing anything they wish.
Noble Consort Xi summoned me to inquire after the health of Concubine Hui.
Pleased to learn that Concubine Hui was well, she offered me some tea.
I rolled up my sleeves while drinking tea.
I was at fault for my lack of manners.
If Noble Consort Xi had any respect for the other imperial doctors,
she would not have entrusted you with attending to her best friend.
The relationship between you two is nothing ordinary indeed.
Young mistress, you–
Feiwen, you have served me for some time,
but I did not know you had such a mind.
I shall be loyal to His Majesty only.
If you are offended, please forgive me, my lady.
Were I to be offended by your loyalty to His Majesty,
would I not be considered unfaithful and unrighteous?
Allow me to ask her a few questions, Your Highness.
Feiwen, as my maid,
you've come here to disclose my private affairs.
You do know this marks the end of your service, don't you?
I hope you have performed your duties.
Tell me.
Before coming here,
did you wipe the colored glass vase on the padauk table in the main hall?
Yes, I wiped it clean.
Nonsense!
On the padauk table, there is no colored glass vase,
but a green jade one.
I was mistaken. It is a green jade vase indeed.
No colored glass vase has ever been on the padauk table in the main hall.
You have never invested the least effort into serving me.
Rather, you note details like an imperial doctor touching my hand,
or the embroidery on his cuff.
Others would not dare observe such things.
Why do you focus on such details?
Your motives are quite suspicious.
I have been too preoccupied with this matter to pay attention to trivialities.
Were Doctor Wen and Noble Consort Xi to have a love affair,
they would remain vigilant.
If that were the case, how could Feiwen witness such details?
Is it not possible that Feiwen snatches up every word and deed of her mistress?
His Majesty the Emperor!
May blessings and peace be with you, Your Majesty.
How can I have peace when there is none in the Imperial Harem?
Please forgive us for disturbing you, Your Majesty.
Tell me what the commotion is about.
I accuse Noble Consort Xi of infidelity, staining the Imperial Harem.
Nonsense, you wretch!
I swear on my life that I have told the truth.
Lady Qi swore a solemn oath before us all. She may have some secrets to reveal.
If it is merely a misunderstanding, it is better to investigate at once.
If rumors spread, the reputation of Noble Consort Xi will be ruined.
Very well. You may speak.
If any of it should prove false, you will not be spared.
Your Majesty, I can prove the love affair between Noble Consort Xi and Doctor Wen.
After Noble Consort Xi left the palace, Doctor Wen often visited her,
sharing the same room in Ganlu Temple.
If you do not believe me, you can question one of the nuns.
She is here in the palace at present.
I am Jingbai of Ganlu Temple.
I bow before Your Majesty and Your Highness.
Please say what you must. We do not wish to disturb your devotions.
Yes, my lady.
Noble Consort Xi ignored us while at Ganlu Temple.
We had no choice but to keep a respectful distance from her.
At that time, Doctor Wen often visited her.
Sometimes when I passed by her residence,
the door was closed even in the daytime
with both maids keeping watch at the door.
I found it inappropriate and wished to alert her,
but was scolded.
Therefore, I spoke of it no more.
After that, she feigned illness and moved away from Ganlu Temple
as rumors had become widespread.
She moved to Mount Lingyun with her two maids.
It is unknown
whether she and Wen maintained further contact or not.
Is the Doctor Wen you mention here in the hall now?
Buddha be trusted, it is he.
Your Majesty, I have a headache. I would like to return and rest.
Your Majesty, Noble Consort Xi has given birth to your offspring
and manages affairs of the Imperial Harem.
She may not claim credit, but she has rendered great service.
A thorough investigation is needed, Your Majesty,
so that Noble Consort Xi may be spared from rumors.
Noble Consort Xi returned to the palace with a child conceived while away.
His Majesty did not visit her often.
If Jingbai is telling the truth, Doctor Wen was her most frequent visitor.
Therefore, the children of Noble Consort Xi–
Lady Qi, you are suggesting they are not His Majesty's offspring.
For the sake of the empire, you must not make dangerous conjectures.
Your Majesty, please pay no heed to her!
Noble Consort Xi returned with her suspicious pregnancy.
Only Jinxi and Huanbi were serving her at that moment.
I daresay the truth will emerge through excruciating torture.
How dare you!
Only injustice will be obtained through torture.
Torture should not be misused to force a confession.
Your Majesty and Your Highness,
torturing Jinxi and Huanbi is the sole way to uncover the truth.
Otherwise, Noble Consort Xi and Doctor Wen might be wronged.
These lowly maids will never confess without the use of torture.
If they can endure all 72 techniques of the Office of Punishment
without changing their story, it might be credible.
Even if they survive the torture, they will be maimed.
What use is it to prove their innocence in this way?
Your Majesty, to prove my mistress's innocence,
I am prepared to endure any trials.
Noble Consort Xi, I know you care for Huanbi and Jinxi.
But if they are not submitted to torture, you put yourself in a dilemma.
You must bear the heartache.
Imperial Brother, I heard everything.
Forgive me, Your Majesty. I came to greet the Empress Dowager,
but found the Imperial Harem in absolute silence,
excepting the palace of the Empress.
So I decided to come here only to hear those words at the door.
As a clan relative, I wish to affirm
my faith in Noble Consort Xi and her children.
Ever since she came to the palace,
she has diligently managed affairs herself.
I believe in Noble Consort Xi.
Count Shen has a proud heart and never associates with concubines,
but strangely he has such fine words for Noble Consort Xi.
You say she has managed affairs herself as if you had seen it with your own eyes.
I need not.
I can tell by her slender frame that she has spared no effort.
While your plump body, Lady Qi, is the sign of a comfortable life.
- You– - You shut up!
Having Count Shen's pledge of faith is a good thing,
but His Majesty has high hopes for the Sixth Prince.
For the sake of the generations to come, we must be thorough.
In that case,
what do you suggest?
The only manner to prove his kinship is through a blood test.
I learned of it from the imperial doctors.
A drop of blood from each individual
is dripped into the same container to see if the blood intermingles.
If it does, they are kin.
Otherwise, they are not.
This is fairly easy,
but I dare not harm Your Majesty
to obtain a drop of blood.
Your Majesty,
even if Hongyan is proved to be your son by the blood test,
it will harm your paternal bond with him if he learns of it when grown up.
Despite your great expectations for Hongyan,
others will speak ill of him due to this test.
This is exactly why the test must be performed.
On this matter, there is no room for error,
or Your Majesty could hand the entire empire to an outsider.
I thought we were deeply in love, Your Majesty,
but things take a sudden turn and fall apart.
If I had known you would come to suspect me,
I would rather have lived out my days all alone at Mount Lingyun.
Huan Huan,
as soon as the test is done,
you and your children may be proved innocent.
Your Majesty actually desires to do it,
for you do suspect me.
Since you suspect that Doctor Wen and I have had an affair,
then it is enough
for Hongyan and Doctor Wen to do the blood test.
Your Majesty will not be harmed
and our innocence may be proved.
- Su Peisheng, bring the Sixth Prince. - Yes, Your Majesty.
You shall prepare the materials for the blood test.
Yes, Your Majesty.
- Your Majesty, the Sixth Prince– - Get a drop of his blood.
Wen Shichu.
- It is impossible, Your Majesty! - Zhen Huan, on your knees!
I have done nothing wrong. Why should I kneel?
If the blood intermingles, they are kin.
There is nothing left to say.
Now, strip off the emblems of her rank and send her to the Cold Palace,
together with that little bastard!
Wen Shichu shall be flogged to death at once!
Who dares!
I have treated you well.
Why have you done this to me?
Your Majesty!
See it with your own eyes!
Something must be wrong with the water.
Your Majesty, something is wrong with the water.
Your Majesty!
Something is truly wrong with the water. Any person's blood intermingles in it.
Your Majesty, please look closely.
Something is wrong with the water.
Your Majesty, someone has played a dirty trick with the water.
Your Majesty, my lady is innocent.
Your Majesty, it is impossible!
I am infertile.
Doctor Wen and Jinxi could never be my children!
I know.
Your Majesty, this water tastes sour, for white alum has been added to it.
Your Majesty, as stated in the ancient medical books,
if white alum is added to water,
even the blood of strangers will intermingle.
If oil is added, even the blood of true kin will not, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, whoever is behind this has a wicked heart.
To keep the test just and fair,
the Empress herself prepared the water.
You are quite knowledgeable about medicine, aren't you?
If I played such a trick,
I would be easily caught.
Would it not be too risky?
Your Majesty, as the proverb says,
"A tiger cub cannot be caught without entering the tiger's lair."
It is worth the risk.
If it worked as intended, the Sixth Prince would be branded as Doctor Wen's son.
Who would perform the test again?
Your Majesty, I did not do it. Please see the truth.
As the Empress, why should I resort to a malicious plan to frame Noble Consort Xi?
Precisely. As the Empress, what more could you desire?
Please see the truth, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, if I had not seen through the trick in time,
Hongyan would have been killed in spite of being your son.
Your Highness, I have respected you and I have shown you deference.
I do not know how you have been so sorely offended
as to inflict this calamity on me.
Your Majesty, I have brought some clean water.
I am certain that nothing has been added to it.
- Test it again. - Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty,
please look.
Your Majesty, this test shall resolve your suspicion.
Huan Huan, I–
I have done you wrong. I shall indulge suspicion no more.
At last,
I have been proven innocent.
Sit.
Lady Qi, it has come to an end. What more do you have to say?
Your Majesty, the Sixth Prince may indeed be your son,
but it has been proven that she had a love affair with Doctor Wen.
You must not turn a blind eye to it!
I dare not deceive you, Your Majesty!
You might not believe me,
but Jingbai can be trusted.
Buddha be trusted, a nun may never lie.
Jingbai, you have brought shame upon your entire order.
Sister Huan, I was very worried at your long absence.
- Are you all right? - Yes.
Your Majesty, on my way back,
I encountered Miss Yurao with the maids and eunuchs, looking for Noble Consort Xi.
With her was eunuch Xiao Yunzi.
He stated that he knew someone from Ganlu Temple.
I felt the one-sided account of Jingbai might not be reliable. More is needed.
So I gave Xiao Yunzi my entry pass and sent him for his acquaintance.
Miss Yurao and Xiao Yunzi were unexpectedly swift.
Jingbai is not the only nun at Ganlu Temple.
Your Majesty, you shall hear another witness.
It has been years, my lady.
Do the chilblains on your hands still torment you in the winter?
Not so much,
but they still cause pain and they itch in the winter.
Now then.
How do you know about the chilblains on her hands?
She used to chop wood, wash clothing and do all the heavy work at Ganlu Temple.
Her hands were soaked in the river in severe winters.
It was impossible not to develop chilblains.
If she did not perform these tasks, Jingbai would scold and beat her.
Noble Consort Xi often fell ill
and was driven away to Mount Lingyun by Jingbai in a heavy blizzard,
which nearly cost her life.
Mount Lingyun is a remote and inaccessible place,
where feral cats attack.
If Noble Consort Xi did have an affair with Doctor Wen,
she could have left behind that desolate place
and spared herself from such suffering.
Huan Huan, you have truly been wronged.
Noble Consort Xi has suffered deep humiliation.
Your Majesty, this nun must be severely punished.
What do you suggest?
This nun has an evil mind
paired with a wicked tongue.
Her tongue must be pulled out in revenge for what she has done.
I always thought you gentle and kind, Concubine An.
I am surprised you can be so merciless.
Save me, Lady Qi!
Please save me!
Have mercy, Your Majesty! I beg you, Your Highness!
Young mistress, forgive me.
I had no choice but to come here,
or Lady Qi–
Lady Qi would have Chen Si beat me to death.
Your Majesty,
the young mistress has known Doctor Wen for a long time,
and it has always been purely friendship, no more.
Please see the truth, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, that Lady Qi induced Bin-er, Feiwen and Jingbai to slander me
is now self-evident.
But someone might be behind Lady Qi,
or she would not dare be so bold
nor plan so thoroughly.
Noble Consort Xi is right.
If this person is left in the palace to stir up trouble,
we shall have no peace in the future.
No one incited me. It was my own idea!
How pleasant to have your own sister in the palace.
When I see Noble Consort Xi with her sister,
it brings back memories, Your Majesty,
of serving alongside my elder sister in the Duke's residence.
Your Majesty,
were my sister alive today,
she would believe my innocence.
Would that she never had a sister such as you.
You may rise.
Lady Qi of the Guwalgiya clan,
for stirring up trouble in the Harem with inflammatory rumors,
shall be sent to the Cold Palace.
First Attendant Kang and Concubine Zheng,
acted upon hearsay and rumors and shall forfeit six-months' stipend.
The fate of the others shall be decided by Noble Consort Xi.
- Jinxi. - Yes, my lady.
- Accompany Bin-er and Moyan out. - Yes, my lady.
Feiwen and Jingbai
shall be flogged to death.
Have mercy, Noble Consort Xi! Your Majesty, I beg you!
Have mercy, Noble Consort Xi!
My lady, here is the tongue of Jingbai.
- Present it to Madam Guwalgiya. - Yes, my lady.
With this extra tongue, she shall learn to watch her own.
You are vicious to the core.
I thank Concubine An for her suggestion.
Wen Shichu!
Though you have had no affair with her, can you swear on your family
that you have no improper feelings towards any of the concubines?
Young mistress, you are quite out of your mind.
Your Majesty!
I have served you for years.
Why do you only have eyes for that offending wretch?
- Remove her. - Your Majesty!
Your Majesty!
Wen Shichu, as long as you are with her, you will do her harm one day!
I will wait for that day to come! Your Majesty!
Doctor Wen, you are well aware
that by your affection alone
you will bring harm upon others.
Your Majesty, my lady.
I shall prove my loyalty.
My lady, Jingren Palace is in chaos. Noble Consort Xi was wronged.
- Concubine An sent me to report to you. - What happened?
Lady Qi claimed that the Sixth Prince was Doctor Wen's son.
Young mistress!
We leave for Jingren Palace at once!
Tormented for the whole day,
I am weary.
You must be weary as well, Empress.
You have been in ill health.
The affairs of the Imperial Harem shall be left in the hands of Noble Consort Xi.
Your Majesty!
Consort Duan and Consort Jing shall help her.
You shall dedicate yourself entirely to your health.
You must not overexert yourself.
Your Majesty,
Doctor Wen has castrated himself and is on the verge of death!
Young mistress!
Send for an imperial doctor!
Quickly! Hold on!
Take this medicine. Quickly!
Push, young mistress!
Almost there! Almost there!
Young mistress, push harder!
Push harder! Young mistress!
How is he? Hold on!
Fetch some coagulating agent! It may save his life!
Young mistress, push!
Hold on, young mistress!
Fetch more hot water!
Quickly!
Why does she bleed so profusely?
You were aware that Mei was to be spared any shocks during pregnancy.
Yet your maid still sent word to Suiyu Pavilion.
Lingrong.
What fell intentions do you harbor in your mind?
I had no knowledge of it. I'm sure Baoque didn't do it on purpose.
If I knew it would come to this, I would rather suffer in Mei's stead.
We were selected together. I–
Whether intentional or not is now of no import.
It can be forgotten if Mei and her child are saved.
Otherwise,
you will answer for it.
You are right to hit me. It was my fault for not disciplining my servants,
causing such a calamity.
Baoque, come in!
I bow before you, my lady.
- You are shameless! - My lady, please forgive me.
How dare you endanger Concubine Hui's safety!
You were trying to embarrass me, weren't you?
My lady, have mercy!
I have been close friends with Mei for years.
Yet, wretch that you are, you startled Mei and provoked her labor.
You talked too much, vile scum!
The maid has no sense. Don't break the rules, Concubine An.
May blessings and peace be with you, Your Majesty.
If servants break the rules,
just drag them to a quiet place and flog them to death.
- Su Peisheng. - Yes, Your Majesty.
- Guards! - Your Majesty, have mercy!
I am at fault. I will never do it again!
- Spare me, Your Majesty! - Remove her.
I will never do it again! Have mercy, Your Majesty!
Never again!
Your Majesty.
Doctor Wen has stopped bleeding. He will live.
However–
Say it.
Just as all eunuchs,
he will never father children.
I know.
Why hasn't Concubine Hui finished?
Do not worry, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty.
Concubine Hui was shocked enough to affect her pregnancy. She's in danger.
I have meager knowledge.
Besides, Doctor Wen is the one who has been looking after her.
I am ill-informed of her situation.
If Doctor Wen is present,
though he cannot deliver the baby,
with his detailed knowledge of her state of health,
he can discuss the treatment strategy with me.
Hasten to bring Wen Shichu here.
Master!
Wei Lin!
Wei Lin, Concubine Hui's body is of warm constitution.
She's having a difficult labor due to an imbalance of the chi and the blood.
Hasten to give her wild ginseng to raise her energy,
followed by the medicinal tonic for bleeding after childbirth, hurry!
Yes, master. Hurry to prepare them!
Your Majesty, the medicine has been administered as Doctor Wen instructed.
She is bleeding less and can push now.
Send my decree to Concubine Hui.
She is now promoted to Consort Hui and may give birth at ease.
- Yes, Your Majesty. - I am greatly indebted to Mei.
After she has given birth to the imperial child safely,
I must make recompense.
Congratulations, Your Majesty! It is a princess!
Wonderful!
How is Consort Hui?
The young mistress is worn out. She cannot even speak.
- I shall visit her. - She is exhausted from childbirth.
It's better she rested, Your Majesty.
You must be tired, Your Majesty. Please return and rest.
When Mei recovers strength, you may visit her.
I will stay here with Mei. No need to worry, Your Majesty.
Very well.
But you must rest as well. Don't wear yourself out.
I shall return with you, Your Majesty.
I bid farewell to Your Majesty.
How joyous!
You need not worry anymore, my lady.
Have some tea.
Things have turned bad!
The young mistress is bleeding profusely again!
How is she? Hurry to fetch some coagulating agent!
It's no use.
Who said that?
Fetch the best medicine!
If she is not saved, I will bury you all with her!
Yes, my lady.
Huan.
- Mei. - Don't cry.
I need to speak with you.
Please send everyone out.
- Leave us. - Wen Shichu, you stay.
Shichu,
have you held her yet?
Hold her.
I–
I dare not.
I know.
I know you have always resented me.
That night,
I tricked you into drinking the wine sent by the Empress Dowager for His Majesty.
For you, it will be a lifelong regret.
Mei, you have been very imprudent.
I am glad to have been imprudent for once.
I have no regrets.
Shichu.
I wish to ask you a question.
In all these years,
have you ever
truly loved me a little?
Even for a moment?
The wine alone was not enough for me to be enamored.
Therefore...
it is not merely for the sake of Huan
that I have treated you with special care.
Truly?
I do not regret meeting you in this life.
Shichu,
hold her.
- Hold our child. - Yes.
Shichu,
you must watch her grow up
and protect her from all harm.
Huan,
please assist Shichu with our child.
How wonderful.
I have never once
lain down
like this
in your arms–
Light and shade
upon her bed-screen's peaks
Her hair drifts cloud-like
across rosy cheeks
Idly she rises to paint her brows
SUIYU PAVILION
Dallying with her makeup and hair
Admiring herself front and back in the mirror
Her face rivals blossoms in beauty
IN MEMORY OF SHEN MEIZHUANG
Embroidered on the silken vest she wears
Golden partridges fly in pairs
Have you arranged for Baoque's funeral?
Yes, my lady.
But, young mistress, you continue to think of Baoque in times such as this.
Then what should I be thinking of?
Young mistress, His Majesty hasn't visited for quite some time,
and you are not seeking a solution.
He is grieving the loss of Consort Hui.
In truth, even if Consort Hui had lived, she would not stand in our way.
But she was dear to Zhen Huan.
She had to die
so that Zhen Huan would be devastated.
And when I see Zhen Huan heartbroken,
my rage is satiated.
Consort Hui,
your death could be considered unjust.
This is for you.
Hold her.
She is gaining weight.
The day Mei was placed in the coffin,
I placed the jade vessel I inherited beside her.
Perhaps I should have given it to her earlier.
I was a fool to have made her live with regret all these years.
All my life,
I have failed her.
You must plan for your child.
Will you lose yourself in drink forever?
Huan, His Majesty has granted me permission
to guard her grave for three years to atone for my grave error.
I understand, Shichu. But the deceased never return.
You must live well so that Mei can be at peace in the underworld.
Noble Consort Xi, I gather you are not yet aware
that Concubine An's father has been accused
of ransacking several mansions and stealing 800,000 taels of silver.
His Majesty is enraged.
I wouldn't have known if you hadn't told me.
He is now the laughingstock of the palace.
You are clever to have your father spy on An Bihuai
so that his crime will be known.
Otherwise, Concubine An will grow overproud.
Were it not for your plan, my lady,
the evidence I found of An Bihuai's crime would be of little use.
His Majesty is still angry with the Guwalgiya clan.
It is An Bihuai who has brought about his own downfall.
I beg you to rescue my father, Your Highness.
Your Highness!
I would help you if I could,
but I am afraid you are on your own.
Please show me the right path, Your Highness.
His Majesty is kindhearted and greatly values his offspring.
You have never conceived in all of these years.
I have a secret prescription which is miraculously effective,
but quite fierce in nature.
If you bear offspring for His Majesty, you shall regain his favor.
He will then take care of your family.
But I used a weight-reducing treatment.
Even if I conceive a child for His Majesty,
I cannot carry it to full term, Your Highness.
If conception itself is enough to meet your pressing need,
why do you need to give birth?
Excellent!
Yunxi has improved much, excelling at horse-riding and archery.
These skills were also taught to Yunli by our Imperial Father.
Now he has forgotten them all.
Your Majesty, I have indulged in drink.
I am not in proper form.
Brother Yunli has not yet married.
When he does, his strength will be drained.
Had I known this was planned, I would not have drunk as much.
I've gotten drunk before firing a single arrow.
Fill his cup.
- Forgive me, my lord! - Merely a piece of clothing.
I will change in the side hall.
What is that?
Give it to me.
Yunli must be in love,
or he would not have such a feminine article on his person.
That paper cutout
resembles Noble Consort Xi.
Indeed it does.
It does look like Noble Consort Xi,
but does it not also resemble Huanbi, Your Majesty?
Next month is the Qixi Festival,
the perfect occasion to bring their romance to a happy conclusion.
The color is faded around the edges.
Yunli must have held it in his hands countless times.
Please forgive me, Your Majesty.
It is my portrait.
Truly?
Seven years ago,
I myself put the portrait in this sachet.
At the time, Consort Hua had forced my lady to kneel before Yikun Palace.
I encountered His Lordship and begged him to help.
After it was over, I expressed my gratitude in Ninghui Hall,
where I saw some colored paper on the table.
His Lordship asked if I knew how to cut portraits,
so I cut out a portrait of myself and put it in the sachet.
Once, His Lordship and I met and he asked to know my favorite flower.
I answered that it was the rabbit-ear iris.
Your Majesty, you will find petals of rabbit-ear iris in the sachet.
Indeed.
If it were not your portrait, how could you know what was in the sachet?
Huan Huan, have you ever noticed her feelings?
I have been fooled.
She has hidden her thoughts from me.
No wonder Yunli does not have even a secondary spouse.
Very well, it is decided.
- I shall betroth Huanbi to you. - Your Majesty!
As a lowly maid, Your Majesty, I do not deserve this honor.
When I left the palace to become a nun,
Jinxi and Huanbi were the only ones to share my weal and woe.
Huanbi and I grew up together as if we were sisters.
His Lordship has been in love with Huanbi for seven years.
I suppose that he does not intend to treat her badly.
What do you suggest then?
I shall accept Huanbi as my stepsister and place her name in my lineage.
She may then be married to Marquess Guo respectably
as second daughter of the Niohuru clan.
As you wish.
Huanbi shall be the secondary spouse of Marquess Guo
as second daughter of the Niohuru clan.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Congratulations, Marquess Guo!
-Rise. -Congratulations, Huanbi!
The Empress Dowager is gravely ill. Your wedding may ward off some bad luck.
Although the families of this marriage are not well-matched,
your love is true.
I shall obey you, Your Majesty.
Speaking of family status,
one matter came to my mind.
Several years ago, the Empress Dowager once proposed a marriage for you.
She was very fond of Meng Jingxian, daughter of Viscount Pei.
Now the news of your marriage has spread.
Viscount Pei cares so much for his daughter
that he sent me three memoranda consecutively,
saying that his daughter could become a concubine
to serve Marquess Guo.
I have no desire for additional spouses.
Moreover, Miss Meng has no interest in me. I shall not keep her for nothing.
Viscount Pei is an elder statesman who has served two emperors.
He will be pacified by your marriage to his daughter.
If he becomes resentful over this matter,
it will do little good for imperial politics.
Then I shall treat her well.
I bid you farewell, Noble Consort Xi.
Take good care.
The auspicious moment is at hand. All is prepared.
The daughter of Viscount Pei is on her way.
Miss Huanbi, you may set off now.
Go.
Would that it were you.
At least he would be truly delighted.
Huanbi is more fortunate than I.
He marries two women at once
but he loves neither.
Depart!
Congratulations, Your Majesty.
Concubine An of Yanxi Palace is three months pregnant.
Is that true?
The imperial doctor has felt her pulse. It is entirely true, Your Majesty.
The Empress kept it a secret
until the pregnancy of Concubine An became stable.
You were very thoughtful.
Concubine An is quite weak.
She used to have irregular menstruation.
She did not know until three months had passed.
Her father is still in prison, so she dares not make it public.
And I do take precautions against false reports of pregnancy.
I have been ordered to manage affairs of the Harem.
I shall help you to keep the unborn child of Concubine An from all harm.
It is a fine thing that Noble Consort Xi understands the importance of this.
Your Majesty, Concubine An is weak.
To assure a stable pregnancy and to soothe Concubine An,
I request that Concubine An be promoted to the rank of Consort.
There ought to be four Consorts, but–
It is for the benefit of the imperial line.
If she is not ranked as Consort, a discussion will be raised,
saying she was implicated by her father.
This would greatly perturb her. How could she attend to her pregnancy?
News of the grand conferment of all concubines has spread widely.
Once the Empress proposed conferring Concubine An as Consort Li,
you immediately suggested the grand conferment of all concubines.
They will all be grateful to you, my lady.
I do not wish to let the Empress do all the good deeds.
She wished to elevate An Lingrong. Why should I not take advantage of it?
We shall share the benefits.
Zhen Huan gains the advantage from the conferment of all concubines,
- but it will not last long. - You are wise, Your Highness.
Is the medicine for pregnancy sent on schedule?
The best medicine, as you ordered, Your Highness.
Last night, the doctor reported
that smoked mugwort leaves were used to steady Consort Li's pregnancy.
Mugwort leaves are already needed in the fourth month?
Consort Li is having a difficult time.
She is fortunate enough to carry an imperial baby even for a few months.
Tell the imperial doctor
that her pregnancy must appear normal, cost what it may.
Yes, Your Highness.
This fan with white jade handle is very effective.
With it in your hand, you won't even notice the heat.
This red gemstone is uncut
and can be embedded in your coronet by a craftsman.
I cannot receive such treasures from you, my lady.
You are His Majesty's most precious treasure.
Only the finest of treasures will suit you.
Is the imperial doctor who attends to Consort Li's pregnancy present?
Yes, Noble Consort Xi. It is Doctor Xu.
I bow before Noble Consort Xi.
Consort Li is now with child. You must be extremely cautious.
As the Empress said,
see to it that she does not lose her child as I once did.
Not only are my gifts to be examined, but all the other gifts as well.
You speak of yourself as an outsider.
If I ever had reason to suspect you, I would–
Nonsense! Say no more of the taboo.
I do it for our friendship.
If someone wishes to play a trick, it will be impossible to seize the chance.
- In fact– - This is Doctor Wei.
It is more secure if two imperial doctors examine the gifts together.
My lady, nothing harmful to pregnancy has been placed among these gifts.
Correct.
Then we can be relieved.
You don't conceive easily, so you must take extra care.
Doctor Xu, how fares Consort Li?
Her pregnancy is stable, my lady.
It may be noted from her good complexion.
Her fondness for fragrances is not a problem, is it?
Not at all.
You are an expert on fragrances.
What is the fragrance you use today?
It is Ninglu Incense.
If you like it, I shall give some to you.
Baojuan, fetch some Ninglu Incense for Noble Consort Xi.
Yes, my lady.
How could I trouble your servants?
Xiao Yunzi, follow Baojuan to fetch the fragrance.
Yes, my lady.
While fetching the Ninglu Incense,
I saw several fragrance boxes at the top of a shelf.
I was told Consort Li liked them no more and kept them there.
But as the boxes looked refined, they did not seem to be abandoned.
I caught Baojuan off-guard and opened a box to obtain some.
It looks like fragrant beeswax.
The scent is odd. What is it?
Noble Consort Xi claims to be ill and refuses to see me.
For the moment, I can't impute the loss of my child to her.
You must be patient.
The imperial doctor told me you mustn't keep the child any longer than six months.
You must abort the child or you will die.
You still have over a month to consider.
I know, Your Highness.
You are wise, my lady.
Consort Li used fragrance to conceal the smell of mugwort leaves,
but I detected it.
Consort Li is using mugwort leaves in the fourth month,
which is a sign of bleeding.
Consort Li has poor chi and blood circulation,
symptoms of night sweats and miscarriage.
She will not carry the child to full term.
You and I both know it.
I will not be held responsible.
Tell me what this is.
Jinxi!
Forgive me, my lady. I was too incautious,
for I overlooked the effect of this fragrance.
What is it?
Couples use it for passionate desires.
It can achieve such a strong effect just by slightly dissolving in water.
You may not be aware,
but it contains a large amount of ilang-ilang and Cnidium fruit.
It becomes even stronger when burned.
When masked by other fragrances,
a small amount can produce an effect without being detected.
The young mistress likes peach blossoms. Why are these lilies sent instead?
The gardeners in the greenhouse say that lilies can ease the mind,
so we were commanded to pick them and bring them to your palace.
My lady, lilies do ease the mind.
You're troubled by insomnia and fitful sleep.
Lilies will do you good indeed.
- Then put them over there. - Yes, my lady.
- Have the lilies been sent? - Yes, my lady.
The greenhouse sends them every day.
The doctor says the buds cause no harm. Consort Li also likes them.
It will be her birthday in a few days.
His Majesty will keep her company. No need for us to worry.
Do not worry, my lady. You shall feign illness and do nothing.
I must avoid her,
for the burden will be too much if she blames me for the loss of her baby.
Oh, my! Music has been playing all day long.
Yanxi Palace is filled with joy.
Surely it is, for she celebrates her birthday while carrying a child.
I arranged these flowers myself. Aren't they beautiful?
Truly, my lady.
The greenhouse shall send them to Yanxi Palace.
Once delivered, be sure to water the buds often
to keep them fresh.
After rushing about for the entire day,
at last I have a moment of peace to talk and drink with you.
I thought you liked scenes of excitement.
I do.
But I prefer spending time with you.
You smell wonderful.
Your Majesty, the imperial doctor said that intimacy is not advisable.
It's the fifth month. I assume it's safe.
- But the imperial doctor said– - You do not wish me to stay with you?
My ladies, I bear bad news. Consort Li has lost the baby.
It matters not. Why are you so nervous?
Consort Jing, Consort Li miscarried because she and His Majesty were–
- Young mistress! - Why is she bleeding profusely?
Hold on, young mistress.
My baby!
How is Consort Li?
With so much bleeding, the baby is lost for sure.
Vigorous sexual intercourse should not be undertaken during pregnancy.
They should have refrained from it.
Besides, she–
How is she?
She is bleeding profusely.
The imperial doctor says she will lose the baby.
I am at fault.
It is all my fault.
The baby is lost.
Huan Huan,
I have lost another child.
It was merely an accident, Your Majesty.
It was not.
Perhaps it was the wine.
Consort Li has been defeated.
It is suspicious how she lost the baby.
The imperial doctor warned her against intimacy with His Majesty.
- Why did she do so knowingly? - It was His Majesty who did so knowingly.
Yet why couldn't he control himself?
This Ninglu Incense of Consort Li is a treasure indeed.
Fresh and clean as if flowers were blossoming. It is truly precious.
Anyone with even a little of it can win His Majesty's heart.
What on earth is this?
Your Highness,
love is not necessary in intimate relations
if aphrodisiac fragrance is utilized.
Was it truly obtained from Consort Li?
Your Highness, I have no reason to malign her.
The day Consort Li miscarried, I found it quite suspicious.
The Emperor can handle his drink.
It is quite impossible for him to lose control after having so little.
His Majesty knew that she was pregnant.
Even if he did desire intercourse,
he would never be so reckless.
How could he not know the importance?
Consort Li also knew it.
Why did she not restrain him?
Therefore, I sent someone to investigate.
This was found among the incense ashes that Baojuan disposed of.
Consort Li has been sufficiently punished with the loss of her child.
It is quite enough.
But she dared beguile His Majesty with this ruse and tarnished the Harem.
She shall not be spared.
Consort Li is indeed guilty of mixing aphrodisiac fragrances,
but she has already lost her child and can no longer conceive.
She has been punished enough.
Your Majesty, please forgive her this time.
Moreover, her fragrances are of great benefit.
Some time ago, my face was scratched by a cat.
Consort Li gave me this healing balm.
It was very effective and no scarring remained.
Your Majesty, please consider her merits and forgive her this time.
You were scratched by the cat during your first pregnancy, weren't you?
Yes, my lady.
Why do you ask, my lady?
Your Majesty,
I do not have the good fortune to conceive because of my debility.
What Noble Consort Xi has said recalls something to my mind.
Noble Consort Xi was healthy back then.
Even though Nian Shilan spited her,
it was unthinkable that she should lose the baby after kneeling only half an hour.
In hindsight, was it not suspicious?
A healthy person is no match for a wicked plot.
Where is Wei Lin?
He is waiting outside to take your pulse, Your Majesty.
Send him in.
Musk was added to it, Your Majesty.
If applied to the face daily,
miscarriage will occur within three months.
It cannot be!
- Lingrong killed my child! - There is no mistaking it.
The balm in this container is now dry.
I gather it has not been used for some time.
It would take at least two containers to remove the scars.
With such a dosage, miscarriage is certain.
Your Majesty!
Lingrong is heartless.
It was An Lingrong's maid who adversely affected Mei's pregnancy.
Now we all know that she has evil intentions.
The maid must have been sent by An Lingrong.
It is a great pity for Princess Jinghe to be left motherless.
I wonder how An Lingrong feels
whenever she faces Princess Jinghe.
Wonderful.
Truly wonderful.
The woman I have loved for years turns out to be a devil.
Your Majesty.
We found these objects at the palace of Consort Li.
This musk is rich in fragrance.
This kind is extremely rare and produces an intense effect.
Who knows how many people have lost their lives because of it?
Dispose of it all quickly.
Were Noble Consort Xi's child and Shen Meizhuang both lost
because of what you did?
When I first plotted against them, I knew it would come to this.
Consort Li,
you have been by my side for years
and have never disobeyed me once.
How could you be so vicious behind my back?
Have you ever liked me, Your Majesty?
You have treated me
as if I were a docile pet.
I am vicious, you say.
But in the Imperial Harem,
who among us has never been vicious?
When the moment comes, everyone is vicious.
In this palace,
no one acts of her own accord.
But you are much more vicious than the others.
I will not order your death.
I will even preserve your title as Consort Li.
Yanxi Palace shall be your Cold Palace.
After you have recovered,
your face will be slapped every day,
and you shall kneel before the Buddha to atone for your sins.
You shall be a warning to others so no one will commit such evil deeds again.
This incense
is dedicated to my first unborn child.
He can now be at peace in heaven.
The color of the blossoms
is exactly the same as that of the aphrodisiac fragrance.
Yes, my lady.
The fragrance that Xiao Yunzi found by accident
turned out to be key to the downfall of An Lingrong.
The servants from the greenhouse delivered foxtail lilies every day,
but no one knew that the buds for that very night
were watered with aphrodisiac fragrances.
An Lingrong is an expert in fragrances,
yet those same fragrances have dug a grave for her.
Su Peisheng says
he will take good care of her at Yanxi Palace.
Sister, let's see who can fly a kite higher.
Hearing the word "sister,"
I thought it was Lingrong calling out to me,
or myself calling out to Mei.
Yet we can never turn back the clock.
This fathomless palace
has destroyed our friendships and family ties.
Every last one of us becomes a vicious monster,
determined to kill the others.
My friends and enemies have left me, one by one.
At the end of all these struggles,
at last I realize that my true enemy has always been the demon within me.