It was here that Mei was pushed and fell into the water.
I believed that by remaining in His Majesty’s favor
and having true friends by my side,
I could live out an imperial life as Lady Wan free from worries.
I was wrong and overly naive.
I hardly realized that the state and the harem
were driven by the same forces.
It is a ruthless world filled with bloody contests.
The concubines of the harem vied for His Majesty’s favor by every means.
Mei was entrapped by the others and nearly died.
It was a walk across thin ice. Many times I barely escaped the clutches of peril.
It was impossible for me to stay above the fray.
Before I realized it, I’d already been drawn into the strife.
Now the Imperial Household Department always gives us the finest goods.
They also allow Doctor Wen to send his medicinal tonic every day.
Do you think it is good? The medicine tasted very bitter.
There’s something else, Yu has really gone too far.
It is said she curses you constantly since moving out of Zhongcui Palace.
Let her.
My conscience is clear.
We’ll forgive her when it’s right.
She has lost much. Her anger is natural.
With time, she will calm.
Young mistress, you are very kind.
Young mistress, your tonic is ready.
Recently, the tonic tastes quite sour.
Perhaps it’s a new prescription from Doctor Wen.
I’ve only been up a short while, yet now I grow weary again.
Lately you’re always getting drowsy soon after rising.
Help me inside for some sleep.
Huanbi.
When did I become so lethargic?
For three or five days, you’ve been continually tired.
Of the day’s 24 hours, you’ve spent 10 to 12 asleep.
Two days ago, it was late morning when His Majesty visited.
And you were still asleep in bed.
Do you also sense that something is amiss?
Young mistress, please stay awake. I’ll ask Doctor Wen to come.
This acupuncture point is called the Hegu point.
If your somnolence is an ordinary symptom,
then acupuncture at this point will help.
If it was caused by a drug, the color of the needle may change.
As I expected, someone has tampered with my medicine.
Please look, young mistress. The needle tip has turned light green.
What is it? Poison?
No, it isn’t.
Someone has changed the dosage of my prescription.
It was done carefully, by adding a very small amount.
Even though I check on you daily, it is hard to detect.
But if you take this medicine over a long period of time,
you will experience fatigue and lethargy at first.
Within six months, you will grow deranged, finally ending in complete delirium.
The perpetrator must hold me in high regard
to attempt to remove me in such an ingenious fashion.
It’s fortunate we discovered it.
Young mistress, you will recover with treatment.
All medicine is dispensed by your prescription
and prepared in my palace.
It seems the new maids and eunuchs are highly suspect. We must take caution.
Young mistress, what is your plan?
I’ve made inquiries.
Huasui was formerly Attendant Yu’s servant.
After her demotion, several of her maids were sent away.
Huasui was among them. She was then reassigned as your servant.
I’m sure the wench planned to take revenge for Yu.
What loyalty.
Please spare me!
Tell the truth.
If you dare lie or conceal the truth,
you’ll be dragged away and beaten to death.
After becoming your servant,
Yu summoned me to her residence one day.
She gave me a great sum as reward.
Miss Yu said I wouldn’t have to worry about anything.
My only mission was to put something in your tonic and your meals.
I dug a hole at the corner of the wall upon her instruction.
When Miss Yu needs to pass along a message or a drug,
someone places a note in that hole, and I go there to retrieve it.
When is the note placed there?
Miss Yu has someone place the drug in that hole every other day.
Then I must go and retrieve it.
Every other day.
Then it’s tonight.
When do you retrieve the drug? Is there a password?
Between the seventh and the ninth hour, birdcall signals are heard from outside.
Then I must make the same signals in response.
Xiao Yunzi.
Tie her up in the warehouse. Don’t let her take her own life.
Yes, mistress.
Let’s go.
I must tell Mei about what has happened.
Yes, we must let Lady Shen know
so you may formulate a response together.
- And Second Attendant An? - Lingrong is timid.
We will not tell her. She would become frightened.
Catch him.
Xiao Yunzi, we have him. Hurry, go outside now!
Come on. Let’s catch him.
- Let me go. - Don’t resist!
- Please let me go. - Kneel!
Young mistress, please.
Lift his head. I’m afraid he is not a stranger.
Xiao Yinzi?
Eunuch Yin, are you well?
Lady Wan, I greet you.
Though we have not met for some time, we once were master and servant.
Just answer my questions.
Why were you sneaking around the palace after dark?
I–
- Xiao Yunzi. - Yes, mistress.
Strike this ungrateful traitor for me.
- Beat him until he speaks. - Yes, mistress.
Lady, please spare me!
Spare me!
- My lady. - Why have you come in such haste?
Xiao Yinzi did not return to Yu’s residence.
This morning, I was told he entered but did not leave Suiyu Pavilion.
The wretch.
My lady, eunuchs are weak. I’m certain he will confess under torture.
Yu is surely done for. My lady, will she betray you?
- What do you advise? - You must eliminate that possibility.
No.
My lady, if you take action now, you’ll draw attention to yourself.
Why not let Yu take the blame?
She planned to kill Zhen Huan to avenge her own loss.
If given a chance to live, how could she not betray us?
Of course she wants to live. But she won’t want her family harmed.
Huan, really.
What an awful thing. Why did you hide it from me?
It was the Empress who told me just now that Yu was plotting to kill you.
I didn’t mean to hide it from you.
These matters are unsettling and frightful.
It’s better to know nothing of it.
I’ve always regarded you as my own sister.
How could something befall my sister without me knowing about it?
Fortunately, it’s over now.
She is to take her own life by His Majesty’s decree.
But I am not at all content.
Nor am I.
No one takes heart at the death of another.
Besides, we have only stopped one plot. There’s no telling how many are to come.
Let’s deal with them one by one.
As long as we remain united, no one may trap us by guile.
Lingrong is ever mild and gentle, but she is also quite sure of herself.
Young mistress.
Yu refuses to die and has gone into a rage at the Cold Palace.
She demands to meet His Majesty one last time before she dies.
Did you report to the Empress?
She is suffering from severe headaches and cannot even leave her bed.
She is unable to address this.
Then only Consort Hua is qualified to do so.
Consort Hua has taken no action whatsoever.
They say she is indisposed.
She has always been close to Yu.
But now, she will take great pains to distance herself.
Yu claims she was framed.
Like a madwoman, she shattered the vessel of poison wine.
She also cursed the young mistress in a venomous tone. It’s an outrage.
Leave her be. It is merely her last-ditch struggle.
Mei and Huan, the hour is late.
I must return.
- Please take care. - Lingrong, farewell.
Let go of me! Keep your hands off!
Second Attendant An, why have you come here?
Zhen has heard that Yu is cursing her. She asked me to look into it.
Yu is decreed to take her own life.
But the madwoman ruined the poison wine and tore up the silk noose.
I am truly at a loss.
You’ve served His Majesty with distinction and have long experience in the palace.
You certainly should be able to discern His Majesty’s intentions.
- Young mistress, do you mean– - She is decreed to take her own life.
So long as she lives no more, your duty has been fulfilled.
Who will care if it was accomplished one way or another?
I understand.
Your servant will see you out.
Your Majesty, please help me!
Your Majesty!
Zhen Huan, fate will bring you to a miserable end!
I must let Zhen know
that I did it for her own good.
Lady Wan and Lady Shen, may good fortune be with you.
I’m here to inform you that Yu has passed away.
Then it’s settled.
All it requires is a length of bowstring and it’s neatly done.
You may rest easy now.
- Rest easy? - Yes, young mistress.
Weren’t you the one who sent Attendant An?
Yu was in a furor.
It was Attendant An’s idea to have me strangle her and get the job done.
- She was strangled? - Yes, young mistress.
It was Attendant An’s idea?
Yes, mistress. Even my master hadn’t thought of that.
So many dislike Yu that no one will say a word.
- Well done. You may leave. - Yes, mistress.
- Young mistress. - Are you all right?
Young mistress, are you well?
She has already died. Why tell us such an awful thing?
Young mistress, the scent of this incense will make you feel better.
- I bow before Attendant An. - Where’s Huan?
She’s having tea with Lady Shen. I’ll inform her you’ve arrived.
That’s not necessary.
It just so happens that I’d like some tea myself.
I’ll see myself in.
I never imagined that Lingrong could be so ruthless.
She did it for our own good.
But it all began with you. Lingrong was never involved.
Even so, she went to the Cold Palace and had Yu strangled.
It’s completely unlike the delicate and gentle manner she’s always had.
A baited cat grows as fierce as a lion.
Not even Su Peisheng knew how to handle the situation,
but Lingrong was able to settle it tidily.
It’s truly surprising.
It’s very different from the Lingrong I spend so much time with.
Young mistress, why don’t you sleep?
I’m a bit frightened.
Yu has passed away,
but it hasn’t brought this matter to an end.
Young mistress, you suspect that Yu was guided by someone else?
You should have kept her alive to interrogate her fully.
She hated me to the core. She would never reveal her master.
She might even accuse us of framing another in return.
But instead she has died.
The true culprit may be overly relieved, allowing us to trace the truth.
Then we should make use of Yu’s death.
A ghost!
You’ve all let your imaginations run wild talking of this ghost nonsense.
I don’t believe in such things.
Those who were hated by Yu in life would be haunted by her after death.
LADY XIN
- This does not concern us. - My lady, your words ring true.
There was no other behind Yu’s crime.
Of course she must reap what she has sown.
If she had been guided by another,
she certainly would haunt the one responsible for her death
asking why she’d been used as a mere instrument of another’s will.
- What’s that? - What is it?
- That sounds like Concubine Li. - It does.
- Jinxi, inform the Empress quickly. - Yes, mistress.
Let’s go take a look.
A ghost!
It’s late at night. Why are you screaming?
- Be quiet now! - A ghost! A ghost!
It’s her. Is she coming for us? Is she here now?
The next one to speak such nonsense goes directly to the Cold Palace!
Don’t just stand there. Help her up.
It wasn’t me!
I only prepared the medicine!
But I didn’t tell her to harm Lady Wan! It wasn’t me!
She’s lost her mind. Cover her mouth and take her to Yikun Palace.
One moment.
My lady, please reconsider.
This happened so suddenly. We should report to the Empress first.
Do as you see fit.
Concubine Li is in a bad state. I fear her words will offend the Empress.
There will be time to inform her later.
I assist the Empress in managing the harem.
Do you think I’m unable to resolve such trifles?
What Concubine Li said concerns the poisoning.
I was directly affected. I have no choice but to intervene.
You two hindered me like that. Are you opposing me intentionally?
Take her away.
Her Highness the Empress!
Your Highness, may blessings and peace be with you.
Your Highness, may good fortune be with you.
You may rise.
Thank you, Your Highness.
You’ve made such a commotion here.
When will I have peace?
What happened to Concubine Li?
Zhou Ninghai, you’re a mere servant. How dare you cover Concubine Li’s mouth!
This is an outrage!
Your Highness, Concubine Li lost her mind and was spouting nonsense.
I asked him to cover her mouth, lest her foul words disturb the others.
You must let her go.
Or did you intend to take her all the way to Qixiang Palace with her mouth covered?
My lady, save me! Yu is here!
I didn’t order her to do it! It wasn’t me!
Let go!
You’re right. No others were involved. She herself faced the consequences.
Fear not. Yu is not here. Return to the palace with me.
Yu is coming! She’s here! She’s coming for revenge!
What is this?
Your Highness, please help me! It’s a ghost!
Lunacy! Have you lost your senses? I can’t allow you to go around like this.
Jiang Fuhai. Take Concubine Li to Jingren Palace.
Your Highness.
Concubine Li has surely lost her mind.
Will she not disturb you at peaceful Jingren Palace?
I should take her and care for her.
Jingren Palace is quite spacious. We can certainly find room for her.
Though Concubine Li is delirious,
her words concern Yu’s poisoning.
It is of great importance. I must look into this.
Is it inappropriate to let Concubine Li stay with me?
Your Highness, we bid you good night.
We bid you good night, Your Highness.
- Jiang Fuhai, bring Concubine Li along. - Yes, Your Highness.
Your Highness, may blessings and peace be with you.
You may rise. Please take your seats.
Thank you, Your Highness.
I’ve summoned you so early because I want to know about last night.
Her Highness the Empress Dowager!
We greet the Empress Dowager. May blessings and peace be with you.
- You may rise. - Thank you, Your Highness.
Consort Hua visited me earlier and said that Concubine Li was not well.
So I’ve come to look into it.
Concubine Li is useless. She couldn’t even take a fright.
The saying is indeed true, “A guilty conscience needs no accuser.”
But Concubine Li said that Consort Hua guided her.
What of it? Concubine Li’s words can only be regarded as madness.
Your Highness–
I know that you have been restrained by Consort Hua for many years.
She appears not to know her limits. But the Emperor is fond of her.
And her brother is Nian Gengyao.
Now Concubine Li has lost her mind.
No one will believe the words of a madwoman.
Send her away from Jingren Palace to the Cold Palace,
lest she defile your residence.
Yes, Your Highness.
Tell the others that rumors were running throughout the palace.
The Empress herself had to intervene.
It was you who calmed the harem and dispelled the rumors.
As for Lady Wan, she is quite clever.
And Lady Shen shows self-possession.
You may let Lady Shen try managing things in the harem.
I will.
It was His Majesty and Your Highness who selected those two at the audition.
Then deliver my decree that Consort Hua must take a rest.
Her assistance in affairs of the harem is no longer required.
Yes, Your Highness.
I greet Consort Hua.
This is a scorching summer. It is no surprise that tempers are short.
I know not what I have done wrong. Please tell me directly, my lady.
I’ll accept your punishment accordingly.
I followed your advice.
I quickly informed the Empress Dowager of Concubine Li’s madness
in order to distance myself from those events.
I don’t care that Concubine Li was sent to the Cold Palace.
But I’ve lost the power to assist in the affairs of the harem.
All thanks to your brilliant idea, isn’t that so?
Congratulations, my lady.
To what do I owe the pleasure of your congratulation?
Anything Concubine Li says will be seen as the ravings of a madwoman.
Even if the Empress Dowager and His Majesty
grow suspicious, there is no evidence.
You have lost some power for now, but kept yourself from harm.
Besides, His Majesty is affectionate.
Your fortune may rise or fall on His Majesty’s whim.
You make it sound easy!
His Majesty is fascinated with Lady Wan.
And the Empress puts obstacles in my path.
It takes great trouble to even meet with him once.
My lady, you are most virtuous.
I will gladly do my utmost to make peace between His Majesty and my lady.
Are you capable of that?
Your Majesty, may blessings be with you.
Your Highness, may blessings be with you.
The sun shines fiercely at this hour.
Why are you walking about with the Princess?
Come, let me hold her.
I haven’t seen her for a few days. It seems she has lost some weight.
She has lost her appetite in the hot weather,
so she has lost some weight.
It has been quite hot.
Why don’t we go to Yuanming Palace to escape the heat?
Yuanming Palace is ready. Your Majesty may depart at any time.
Consort Duan is in poor health.
The hot weather is not good for her recovery.
- Let her come with us. - Of course.
As for Consort Hua–
Why don’t we let her stay here to care of the rest of the concubines?
That ornament–
It was a gift I granted to Consort Hua.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Every time Consort Hua wears it, the Princess smiles.
So Consort Hua gave it to me to entertain the Princess.
Let her come as well.
Yes, Your Majesty.
It is said that His Majesty prefers Yuanming Palace. This is my first visit.
Young mistress, I have heard that Consort Duan is here as well.
We have yet to meet her.
She has been ill for many years. Someday we will surely meet her.
What is it?
Remarkable archery.
It is a wild pigeon, known for its dexterity and nimbleness.
It was struck by a single arrow. The hunter displays remarkable skill.
I greet Lady Wan.
Is His Majesty practicing mounted archery?
Marquess Guo is here. His Majesty and the Marquess are hunting together.
The Marquess is quite skilled as an archer.
Even His Majesty praises him for it.
Marquess Guo is versed in music, chess, poetry and painting.
I did not know he excelled at archery as well.
You have not been here long enough to see, but the Marquess excels in many areas.
This imperial doctor is–
LIU BEN
Doctor Jiang has returned home for mourning.
I was sent by the Imperial Medical Bureau to check on Lady Shen.
- Doctor Liu, please wait. - Yes, madam.
From your accent, it seems that you’re from Jizhou.
I was transferred from Jizhou and just arrived a few days ago.
What a coincidence. I’m from Jizhou as well.
It’s a great honor to meet a fellow countryman.
Your Majesty and Lady Shen, my congratulations.
You are with child. More than one month already.
Good.
- You may rise. - Thank you, Your Majesty.
Where are Lady Shen’s closest maids?
Here.
You two are the personal servants of Lady Shen.
She is with child and should be looked after with extra care.
You must report to me on her condition daily.
Yes, Your Highness.
As usual, the Empress is meticulous in all matters.
Your Majesty, now that Lady Shen is expecting.
Shouldn’t we appoint a reliable doctor for her care?
Your Majesty, the one who was sent to check on me is Liu Ben.
I have high regard for him.
He and I are from the same province. May he take charge of my care?
That is good.
Your health comes before all else.
You must take care of yourself and ensure that there are no mishaps.
Yes, Your Highness.
JIUZHOU QINGYAN HALL (HALL OF THE NINE CONTINENTS IN PEACE)
Lady Hui, that hairpin is quite delicate.
It must be a new gift from the Empress Dowager.
Yes, it is.
Her Highness learned of Lady Hui’s pregnancy, so she had it sent here.
The Gods of Harmony on the hairpin
represent abundant fertility and good fortune.
This shows that the Empress Dowager very much looks forward to the newborn.
CONSORT DUAN
Consort Duan!
Your Majesty and Your Highness, may blessings and peace be with you.
- You may rise. - Thank you, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, you are once again surrounded by new beauties.
Consort Duan has not met any newcomers for quite some time.
I see that her eye is just as keen as in the old days.
The sun is shining fiercely, yet you still rushed here.
It’s just a feast for a child’s birthday, not any urgent matter.
Wenyi’s first birthday brings us great joy.
I must pay my respects.
Besides, much time has passed since I last saw the Princess.
- Take your seat. - Thank you, Your Majesty.
When last we met, Princess Wenyi was just one month old.
Your Majesty, I must say,
though the celebration is magnificent, it feels somewhat restrained.
Since this is a family feast, and everyone here is family,
may we not dispense with formality?
If you have an idea, just tell us.
Each of the concubines here possesses different and varied talents.
Let us write down the skills of each and draw lots.
Whatever is drawn will be performed to entertain the guests.
Does it please Your Majesty?
The idea is novel. We shall do as you say.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Highness, please show us your calligraphy, writing the word “longevity.”
Seeing as today is the birthday of Princess Wenyi,
I will write the word “longevity” as a gift to her.
I express gratitude to Your Highness on behalf of Wenyi.
LONGEVITY
The Empress’s calligraphy grows continually better.
So refined and exquisite.
Your Majesty and Your Highness, please forgive me.
I’m too weak to stay and enjoy the feast.
You’re indisposed. You may retire for some rest.
I will see you when time allows.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
My lady, I know that your health is poor,
but you’re leaving so soon.
I’m afraid His Majesty will be disappointed.
If I stay, I’m afraid those who want to put on a show will be disappointed.
I dislike such pretentious types.
Let us put them out of sight and out of mind.
This is for Lady Wan.
Please dance “Flying Wild Goose.”
The dance was created by Consort Mei of Emperor Xuanzong in the Tang Dynasty.
It was believed lost for many years, but Empress Chunyuan loved dance.
She attempted to find the original version and then spent great effort to amend it.
Everyone was profoundly moved by her dancing.
The whole palace was enchanted.
Lady Wan is still young. How could she perform “Flying Wild Goose”?
My dancing skills are truly unpresentable.
I’m afraid I will expose myself to ridicule.
If you are unable to dance, then no need to impose on yourself.
Empress Chunyuan moved so gracefully. I doubt that anyone could ever compare.
“Flying Wild Goose” is easy to learn but difficult to master. Let it be.
She will perform something else.
“Flying Wild Goose” has not been performed in the palace for a long time.
Its long absence makes us wish to see it again.
Lady Wan, you may dance in your own way.
Please allow me to prepare. I’ll return presently.
Your Majesty, the common musical accompaniment is vulgar.
Please allow me to play the music.
Attendant An will sing to accompany Lady Wan’s dancing.
With pleasure.
Bring out Consort Dowager Shu’s Zither of Endless Longing.
The day Consort Shu entered the palace,
the late Emperor granted her a zither named Endless Longing
and a flute named Eternal Faithfulness as a token of his love.
After the late Emperor died,
Consort Shu left the palace for the temple.
The zither and flute were left behind.
Today we have the good fortune of hearing one of them.
Dance lightly like a startled wild goose
Move gracefully like a soaring dragon
More glorious than the chrysanthemums of autumn
More majestic than the pines of spring
Just like the moon mantled in light clouds
Swinging like a snowflake swirling in the blowing breeze
Gazing from a distance
As bright as the sun rising above the rosy clouds of dawn
Her every movement corresponds to Empress Chunyuan’s.
DUKE DUN
It is beautiful, but lacking innovation.
Innovation is good. But respect is much more important.
How many more surprises can we expect from you?
It is a mere performance. Your Majesty, please don’t laugh.
You’ve danced for some time. Are you tired?
I am not.
I never saw Empress Chunyuan perform “Flying Wild Goose” with ingenious grace.
It is truly my loss.
What I performed today is an imitation of Consort Mei’s dance.
My insignificant skill cannot compare to the performance of Empress Chunyuan.
Yunli.
The sound of Eternal Faithfulness must indeed accompany Endless Longing.
Only together do they make truly unparalleled music.
This is Noble Lady Wan from the Zhen family.
This is Noble Lady Hui from the Shen family.
The one who just sang–
- I’m Second Attendant An. - Rewards.
You, come be seated here.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
We bow in respect before Your Majesty.
What a coincidence. You are all here.
You may rise.
Come here.
How are you? How do you feel today?
I am very well. Thank you, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, have you dined yet?
I’ve just retained a new chef, a master in Jiangnan cuisine.
I had dinner in Bitong Study Hall. Maybe another day.
Your Majesty, the General of Yili sent us melons in tribute.
Let’s try them together.
- Good. I’ll sample them with you. - Yes, Your Majesty.
Who is lurking there?
I saw you! Come out now!
Don’t catch me! I’m a servant of Lady Hui!
It’s Fuling, one of Lady Hui’s servants. Why is she sneaking about?
What is in your hands? What is it?
What?
You try to steal away with Lady Hui’s belongings?
Young mistress, save me!
How could you? I will not allow it.
- What is this? - Blood.
Why is there blood on the clothing?
Is it possible that someone attempted to kill for money?
Do these things belong to Lady Hui?
Why are they stained with blood?
Is it possible that Lady Hui had her menstruation?
I didn’t.
Your Majesty, this servant is acting so strangely.
We should send her to the Office of Punishment for a full interrogation.
I didn’t know you were a thief. Drag her out and beat her now.
Young mistress, I was destroying the evidence for you.
Yet you would ruthlessly allow me to die.
Why should I remain loyal to you?
Your Majesty, I dare not hide the truth from you now.
In fact, our young mistress was never pregnant at all.
Nor did I steal these clothes.
They were stained two days ago when the young mistress had her menstruation.
She asked me to get rid of them.
These clothes are solid evidence.
Mei.
Your Majesty, this is slander.
Lady Hui has had a shock. Summon the imperial doctor.
- Yes, Your Majesty. - Eunuch Su.
Please call Doctor Liu. He’s been caring for my pregnancy.
I don’t know if he is on duty tonight.
Young mistress, Doctor Liu is not on duty today.
- No matter. - Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, it’s Doctor Liu who’s been caring for my pregnancy.
No matter!
Your Majesty, the young mistress is not with child.
Which imperial doctor diagnosed her?
Your Majesty.
- Su Peisheng. - Yes, Your Majesty.
Summon Liu Ben at once.
If he dares to resist, tie him up immediately.
Your Majesty,
when I summoned Doctor Jiang just now,
I had Doctor Liu summoned as well.
But Doctor Liu’s residence has already been vacated.
A fine state of affairs this is.
Lady Shen, is he not from the same province as you?
It was you who requested that he care for you, wasn’t it?
Your Majesty.
Whoever dares intercede for Shen will receive the same punishment.
Your Majesty, Lady Wan and Lady Hui are quite close.
I’m wondering if that–
Silence!
Your Majesty, please quiet your anger.
You deceived the Empress Dowager as well as myself.
How dare you flaunt her hairpin!
Your Majesty, you must care for your health first.
The Noble Lady from the Shen family has behaved imprudently.
She is demoted to Second Attendant, deprived of the honorific name Hui
and to be confined to Cunju Hall.
No one is to visit her without our permission.
Your Majesty, please instruct us how to deal with Liu Ben and Fuling–
Track down Liu Ben, take him alive.
And Fuling will be sentenced to death.
Mei.
What? Liu Ben escaped?
My lady, please be calm. I’ve already sent someone to chase him.
Liu Ben knew too much of our plan. He must not remain alive.
He must be killed on sight.
Catch him alive, or bring his dead body to me.
I don’t believe a man can disappear completely.
Liuzhu, tell Xiao Yunzi to find Doctor Wen Shichu.
Ask him to convey a handwritten letter from myself to my family
and another letter to Mei’s grandparents in the capital.
Tell them that we must track down Liu Ben.
I will surely do so.
Young mistress, Fangruo has already done what you requested of her.
Mistress Meizhuang asked Fangruo to pass this to you.
It was only to be delivered into your hands.
Take care of yourself and support Lingrong.
Mei is trapped in such a difficult situation
yet still shows consideration for me.
Mistress Meizhuang is right.
At the moment, Attendant An is the only one you can rely on.
I hear that Princess Wenyi has been unwell and crying constantly.
I’ll ask the priest to hold a prayer ceremony to bless her.
Who is singing?
Perhaps a female entertainer from the palace.
Such a beautiful voice is rarely found.
One must pick a flower at the prime of its bloom
Do not wait until the blossoms fade and fall
Huan.
Who is singing there?
- I greet Consort Hua. - I greet Consort Hua.
- You may rise. - Thank you.
When did Lady Wan find her voice?
You are skilled in singing and dancing. This comes as quite a surprise.
I’m not the one who should receive your praise. I could never sing like that.
It was Second Attendant An.
“One must pick a flower at the prime of its bloom.”
Flowers are always used as a symbol for women.
With her song, she aims to draw the attention of men.
She’s willing to be “picked” at a moment’s notice.
The title is “Golden Embroidered Garments.”
It advises us to cherish what we have.
Surely you have mistaken its meaning.
Lady Wan indeed has a glib tongue.
But only a dutiful woman will be regarded as virtuous,
not one who defies with sophistry.
Lady Wan disregards the rules of decorum and offends her superiors with her words.
I dare not.
Lady Wan intends no offense. My lady, please forgive her.
Isn’t it too late to beg for forgiveness once you’ve already made an error?
I, as the head of the harem,
must spare no effort in instructing you what rules are to be followed.
- Servants! - Yes, my lady.
Your Majesty and Your Highness, may blessings and peace be with you.
What a wonderful voice.
You’ve seldom dressed in such bright colors.
You may rise.
What is wrong? You seem out of sorts today.
Here we are in full daylight. How dare she sing such unseemly songs.
Tell me. What do you think of the song?
Attendant An’s singing has a heavenly ring to it.
Your Highness praises me too highly. I am unworthy of such praise.
One must pick a flower at the prime of its bloom indeed.
- What is your name? - An Lingrong.
Lovely.
Your voice is refreshing, as are you.
Your Majesty, I’m a little tired. I’d like to retire.
Very well. Liuzhu, come. Escort Lady Wan so she may rest.
Yes, Your Majesty.
I will return with Huan as well.
I advise you not to covet golden embroidered garments
I very much enjoyed Attendant An’s song.
Have her sing it again for His Majesty and myself.
Summon Attendant An.
Yes, Your Highness.
One must pick a flower at the prime of its bloom
Do not wait until the blossoms fade and fall
LADY FUCHA
Lady Fucha, are you unwell? Did you eat something unclean?
I inform Your Highness that she is not ill.
She is with child.
Nonsense.
Is it true? Wonderful. It is a joyous occurrence.
Congratulations are due to His Majesty.
Is it true? Has an imperial doctor confirmed it?
Two imperial doctors have confirmed it.
I’m not the type to say anything to win His Majesty’s favor.
If pregnant, I say yes. If not, I say no. How could I lie about an imperial heir?
Isn’t it enough to have Attendant Shen as an example?
Lady Wan, don’t you agree?
Young mistress, it’s quite late. Try to sleep now.
Lady Fucha is with child after serving His Majesty only a few times.
Yet it has never happened to me.
I can’t help but think that I lack blessings and good fortune.
How can it be?
Mistress, you are fated to enjoy blessings and good fortune.
Conceiving a child is only a matter of time.
Do not worry at all, mistress.
However, I learned from the city guards
that an epidemic has broken out in the capital city.
It’s possible that it may spread to the palace.
Young mistress, you must take extra caution.
Sleep now.
My lady, the epidemic has reached the palace.
What?
Xiao Dezi, a eunuch in our palace was infected.
The Imperial Household Department plans to remove him.
A report, my lady.
The Empress sends word that the epidemic has reached the palace.
Your assistance is required.
The eastern six palaces have been doused
with boiling liquor and mugwort is burning.
The western six palaces will be under your management.
Very well.
Her Highness also states
that mugwort must be burned at Cunju Hall where Attendant Shen resides as well.
No palace among the six is to be left out.
Report to Her Highness that I will get the job done.
Yes, my lady.
I was unable to eliminate Shen Meizhuang. She has tremendous luck.
But if Attendant Shen should die,
even though Liu Ben were to be caught, there would be no one to confront him.
Is there anything of use to us in Xiao Dezi’s quarters?
There is a tea set that he used after contracting the disease.
Send it to Cunju Hall.
Understood.
Two patients died this morning.
This epidemic threatens us all.
Not even the Imperial Medical Bureau has a remedy.
Young mistress, bad news!
Slowly.
Xianfu Palace informs us that Mistress Meizhuang is ill.
Young mistress.
Mistress Meizhuang is already ill. You must think of your own health.
- Just one look. - Who else will defend Mistress Meizhuang?
Young mistress.
Please take good care of Mei.
If I had one request for you, could you help me?
I must remind you, if you succeed, you may receive no recognition.
And if others find out, you may be blamed.
But if I don’t do this, I’m afraid my heart will never rest easy.
To give you peace, I’m prepared to do all that I can.
I am at your disposal.
Doctor Wen, you’re working so hard. Haven’t you taken a rest yet?
Doctor Jiang.
Recently you have been caring for all the concubines by day
JIANG SHEN
while also working on a remedy for the epidemic by night.
You must be exhausted.
Is there any progress?
Not yet. But I’ll do my best to develop it.
Then please return to your work.
I’ve secretly arranged for Doctor Wen to treat her.
However, we’re short of medicine, and her diet is not good.
Mistress Meizhuang isn’t getting any better.
Congratulations, young mistress. We’ve found the one you requested.
So it is you.
I never believed that Attendant Shen would feign pregnancy to win favor.
So I secretly began to search for Liu Ben.
Our efforts have finally paid off. He was caught at the border of Yongzhou.
We will not torture you to force a confession.
But if you dare tell any lies,
you will suffer pain much worse than death.
Your Majesty, Mistress Meizhuang was never pregnant.
I’m aware of that.
But Mistress Meizhuang did not know that she was not with child.
When I started taking care of her, her menstruation had already stopped.
The symptoms of dizziness and nausea were caused by medicine, not pregnancy.
I received orders before examining Mistress Meizhuang.
No matter what, I was to report that she was pregnant.
Received orders? From whom?
From–
She planned to have you killed. Will you still hide her guilt?
Consort Hua. It was Consort Hua.
That day, Consort Hua gave me a sum of money
and told me to leave Yuanming Palace at once to avoid trouble.
As soon as I entered the city, I was chased by killers.
I was forced to become an outcast and wander like a homeless dog.
Xiao Yunzi, keep a close watch over him. Don’t let anything happen.
Yes, young mistress.
Get up.
Your Majesty, please quiet your anger.
Is it possible Liu Ben did not reveal the whole truth?
Actually there are many doubts about what happened that day.
But we have no evidence.
If Attendant Shen truly did have her menstruation a few days before,
the stained clothes could have been discarded at any time.
Why was it done in your presence?
Consort Hua.
Very well.
We have wronged Mei.
Release her and restore her rank at once.
- I’m afraid she can’t go out now. - Did she–
No, Mei did not take her life.
Unfortunately, she’s contracted the disease in her extreme sorrow.
We shall order the imperial doctors to treat Noble Lady Hui at once.
We must let her live a good life from now on.
Your Majesty, please forgive my impertinence.
Seeing that Attendant Shen was seriously ill,
I privately requested an imperial doctor to save her life.
- Is that so? - Your Majesty, please forgive me.
If it hadn’t been for you risking your life to take such measures,
I’m afraid I would be faced with deep regret over Lady Hui.
Your Majesty is blameless.
It was those guileful schemers. They clouded Your Majesty’s clear vision.
Su Peisheng.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Deliver my order to the Imperial Medical Bureau.
Jiang Cheng and Jiang Shen are decreed to take their own lives.
Consort Hua’s honorific name is revoked. She is demoted to Noble Lady.
The demotion of Consort Hua–
It’s already midnight.
If we ask the Imperial Household Department to deliver your decree,
I’m afraid it will disturb the entire harem.
Then wait until tomorrow.
Go to Cunju Hall first.
Announce that we have reinstated Lady Shen to her former rank.
Her honorific name is restored.
- The most urgent matter is to cure her. - Yes, Your Majesty.
What? Liu Ben has been found?
I knew nothing of it until I overheard a conversation
between First Attendant An’s maid and our servants.
It must be Zhen Huan.
The Jiang brothers could not keep themselves out of trouble either.
Zhou Ninghai, tell those two to keep their mouths shut.
Understood. I’ll do so right away.
My lady, it would be wise to silence those two men.
But if you want to change His Majesty’s mind,
you can’t simply expect that His Majesty will soften out of affection for you.
You must offer him what he most desires at this moment.
My lady, if you are guilty of a fault, His Majesty is obliged to punish you.
Faults must be punished, but achievements must be rewarded.
Why have you come in such haste?
Your Majesty, congratulations. I have just learned
that Jiang Cheng and Jiang Shen have developed a remedy for the epidemic.
I have brought the two imperial doctors here to report to you.
Your Majesty, most disease is caused by unsanitary food
and leads to damage of the spleen, stomach and intestine.
We’ve pored over ancient books
and developed a remedy, an emergency disease preparation.
Several young eunuchs have already taken the medicine.
After taking two doses, they showed a reduction of fever.
Good.
My lady.
Your Majesty, please forgive my discourtesy.
Are you unwell? Take your seat quickly.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Consort Hua recalled that disease remedies may be found in ancient books.
She stayed up last night reading through books.
Over the last few days she has done the same.
Perhaps that is why she feels weak.
My beloved, you are tired.
- Su Peisheng. - Your Majesty.
Take your men and accompany Doctor Jiang to the Medical Bureau.
Deliver the medicine to Lady Hui’s residence at Cunju Hall first.
Then give it to every servant in the palace who has been infected.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Lady Hui?
We have already restored Shen’s rank.
We’ve wronged her over what happened in the past.
Your Majesty, I dare not ask you to forgive my past recklessness.
I only ask that you do not risk your own health in anger over me.
I’m merely one insignificant individual.
But your health matters to everyone in this land.
All right. Today you’ve made a great achievement.
If this remedy can cure the epidemic,
it will prove a blessing to us all.
I’m not the kind to fail in dispensing rewards and punishment.
Your Majesty, you’re divinely wise.
Doctor Wen, Doctor Jiang told us to deliver this remedy to Lady Hui.
What? Doctor Jiang has developed a remedy for the disease as well?
Place it here.
Lady Hui, there has been one doubt in my mind all along.
Tell me.
Does it seem you contracted the disease too suddenly?
I remember that the epidemic reached us first at Consort Hua’s palace.
Then your palace followed.
At the time, you were confined to your palace.
You had no contact with Consort Hua’s servants.
How did you catch the disease so suddenly?
The Imperial Household Department ordered me to send you a new tea set.
The tea is ready now. Please enjoy.
It was her!
Mei, please be calm.
We have no evidence at the moment.
I have another doubt.
Jiang Cheng and Jiang Shen are studied in women’s health and infant care.
How could they suddenly make a leap to the treatment of diseases?
If I say that the remedy was mostly developed by myself,
- will you believe me? - Yes, you are capable.
But His Majesty has already said that they are of great merit.
If you say anything now, nobody will believe your words.
Your Majesty, does Lady Wan serve you well?
That’s hard to answer.
If I say she serves me well,
and then I do not dress warmly in order to enjoy the bracing cold,
Queen Mother will blame her for it.
If I say she doesn’t serve me well–
In fact, she is very attentive.
But I’ve been busy with my duties. I haven’t seen her for several days.
Your Majesty has been occupied with affairs of state.
It’s a mere few days that you haven’t met with her.
How often do you meet with Consort Hua?
How often do you meet with the Empress?
How often do you meet with Concubine Jing and the rest of them?
Since Your Majesty is busy,
you may meet all of the concubines much less frequently.
But if you show partiality to one,
then you aggrieve the others.
Queen Mother, I have learned from you.
I will bear this in mind.
Such fine black fox fur may only be found in Qinghai.
Your Majesty has a keen eye and a clear heart.
It is quite dim here, yet you still recognize this black fox fur.
When you behold the harem and the court, of course it’s as clear as day to you.
This black fox cloak
has a satin lining selected by Consort Hua,
embroidered with passionflowers.
When inside and outside are balanced, there is harmony in the whole.
Queen Mother, I understand what you have just taught me.
You should temper justice with mercy, not only in the court,
but also in the harem.
The pacification of the Northwest is nearly complete.
But the chieftain of the Southwest is still a thorn in our side.
If we have to calm the situation, it will take great effort.
Nian Gengyao displays great talent and acceptable loyalty.
Such a meritorious official, providing he grows not overly arrogant,
should be put to proper use by Your Majesty.
Calming the situation on the western frontier shows true merit.
He will surely be highly rewarded.
- My lady. - Has my brother returned?
The General has calmed the situation on the frontier and has just returned.
He has gone to greet His Majesty.
My lady.
On His Majesty’s order, please come to Yangxin Hall to dine.
Wait outside. I’ll come immediately.
This is grilled mutton. It’s fresh, tender and savory.
My favorite dish. Try it yourself.
Delicious indeed.
Brother.
When His Majesty grants you a feast, you must be served by imperial servants.
NIAN GENGYAO
Your Majesty, I’ve been discourteous. Please don’t hold it against me.
You have been far away at battle for a long time.
Of course you are used to attending to every detail yourself.
It’s of no importance.
The edible bird’s nest with duck placed before me looks quite good.
I’d like to trouble Eunuch Su.
General, please enjoy.
What a rare chance to eat at the same table as the Emperor.
Very well. Let us enjoy this meal.
Your Majesty, you’ve been keeping me company recently,
without visiting the others.
Since you strive to be a generous concubine,
then I will pay a visit to Consort Qi and the others.
Your Majesty.
I know you are reluctant to part with me.
Your Majesty, you always enjoy listening to Attendant An sing.
I haven’t heard her for quite some time.
Why don’t we ask her to come sing for us?
Let me take this chance to enjoy it together with you once.
It is late at night. Why should we trouble her?
Your Majesty.
If you want to call her, you may do as you wish.
I greet Lady Wan and First Attendant An.
May good fortune be with you.
Eunuch Zhou, why have you come?
His Majesty wishes to hear Attendant An sing.
He awaits you at Yikun Palace.
His Majesty is visiting Consort Hua. What am I if I go there?
His Majesty awaits.
If you intend to defy the order, you should reply to it yourself.
Don’t make it difficult for us. We are merely servants.
Jinxi, fetch my zither.
Young mistress.
Singing without accompaniment is monotonous.
I’d like to join Attendant An and play the zither to entertain His Majesty.
By order of Your Highness, I went to Yikun Palace
to report that the Empress is ill and will be
absent for the chrysanthemum viewing.
To my surprise, Xiao Xiazi told me
that Lady Wan and Attendant An were summoned to entertain Consort Hua.
I watched for a while out of curiosity.
When Lady Wan and Attendant An came out,
they were perfectly calm as if nothing had happened.
I know the temperament of Lady Wan. She is not easily perturbed.
But I never imagined that Attendant An could bear it as well.
It seems that I haven’t paid much attention to An lately.
Consort Hua has been overly arrogant and capricious.
But First Attendant An–
She is quite good.
Huan, we are not performers who sing for a living.
How can she humiliate us that way?
Don’t cry.
Have some water to soothe your throat.
Huan, you were humiliated as well just because of me.
If it were not for your presence,
as His Majesty was considerate of you,
I can’t imagine how much humiliation I would have had to take from her.
His Majesty holds Nian Gengyao in high regard.
Consort Hua is gloating.
His Majesty must consider the overall situation.
It would not be wise of him to offend her openly for our sake.
As long as Nian Gengyao exists,
His Majesty will not neglect Consort Hua.
The spread of the epidemic in the palace has been checked.
Consort Hua is congratulated.
Starting today, Consort Hua regains power to assist in affairs of the harem.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
Congratulations, Hua.
Concubine Jing has been serving me for eight or nine years.
She is hereby promoted to Consort Jing.
Thank you for your kindness, Your Majesty.
The conferring ceremony will be held on the 19th of next month.
I will discharge my duties and share the burden with Her Highness the Empress.
Mei and Huan.
Mei and Huan, help me!
- Lingrong, what’s the matter? - Get up, speak slowly.
Mei and Huan, my father has been imprisoned.
How could such a thing happen?
I received a letter from home.
It said that the Magistrate of Songyang County, Jiang Wenqing,
was convoying provisions to the Northwest.
My father was a member of the escort group.
However, they encountered deserters of the enemy
and the military provisions were snatched.
His Majesty was furious.
Jiang Wenqing was captured immediately and was imprisoned along with my father.
I’m afraid that in a fit of rage,
His Majesty will kill my father.
This matter concerns your family.
Of course we will intercede with His Majesty.
I’m overwhelmed with gratitude.
Lingrong.
Lady Hui, are you here to plead for the father of Attendant An?
Yes, I can’t sit by and do nothing.
You’d better do nothing.
Think about it. If you write a letter to your parents,
of course, your father will give a mild punishment.
But if someone raises objections to this,
His Majesty will be furious.
Then what of your father’s future?
Besides, once you intervene
and Consort Hua learns of it,
Attendant An’s father will surely be put to death.
As soon as the Empress left Consort Hua arrived.
They came for the same person.
Did they come for Attendant An’s father, An Bihuai?
Exactly.
Let me guess.
Her Highness the Empress is kind and virtuous.
She interceded on behalf of Attendant An’s father.
Consort Hua is righteous and tenacious.
She must have asked my dear to enforce the law strictly,
and to remain unswayed by personal considerations.
And what say you?
Concubines should not meddle in affairs of state. I always bear this in mind.
As a child, I studied history books.
I learned that when the wise Emperors punished their officials,
they would punish the leader yet forgive
the follower, balancing justice with mercy.
The people not only revered them, but also admired their clemency.
I am ignorant in these matters.
Battles are fought outside the palace. Discipline is maintained within.
If both are clearly settled, then the nation will thrive in peace.
I already knew you were well-read in the classics,
but did not expect you to be versed in history and national policy.
Your words did not concern affairs of state,
yet you advised through history.
We will send someone to reinvestigate An Bihuai’s case,
and shall let no one suffer a wrong.
Congratulations, young mistress.
You’re too kind. What is it?
This morning His Majesty ordered Shen Zishan, Colonel of Jizhou Garrison,
to reexamine your father’s case.
Hopefully, your father will live.
- Is it true? - Of course.
Yesterday the Empress interceded with His Majesty.
Of course His Majesty won’t disappoint her.
- Thanks to the Empress. - Don’t–
If such things may befall me,
I know that I can rely on nothing.
I finally understand now.
One word from the Empress is much more powerful than any others.
Of course. Besides the Empress Dowager,
Her Highness the Empress is the most powerful woman in the palace.
Your Highness, I made a sachet and would like to present it to you.
I hope that Your Highness will not dislike it due to my unskillful handwork.
What an exquisite sachet.
Its fragrance is delicate and elegant.
It contains peony and orchid,
mixed with eaglewood and pine needle.
Though the sachet is wonderful,
it is a pity that I usually don’t use perfume.
I had not noticed.
Every time I come to greet Your Highness,
I only notice that your palace is filled with
the fragrance of fresh flowers and fruits.
But I was not aware that Your Highness doesn’t like perfume at all.
I’m quite careless.
It’s not that I don’t like perfume.
But I must remind you
that certain perfumes may do harm to your health if used improperly.
Thank you for your counsel, Your Highness.
As you understand perfumes, you must know how terrible they can be.
It’s springtime. Even the cats are starting to wail.
Other cats will yowl. But my cat, Songzi, loves to pounce.
Cats are not easy to train when in heat.
But they are quite susceptible to scents.
They can be trained once accustomed to certain scents.
Very good. The flowers at Jingren Palace are in full bloom.
I will invite all the concubines to the palace to view them.
Yes, Your Highness.
Consort Jing and Consort Hua became concubines of His Majesty on the same day.
Now Jing has been promoted to Consort,
and will help Consort Hua to assist in affairs of the harem.
It is a blessing that you now have a helper.
But even more so for me since I can enjoy my leisure time now.
Lady Fucha, you’ve viewed the flowers for a while, your makeup has run.
It truly must be a gift from His Majesty. Your powder smells so good.
- Young mistress. - Call the imperial doctor.
Young mistress, are you all right?
- Are you all right? - It hurts.
Are you all right? Young mistress, don’t worry.
It’s hopeless.
Who is the owner of that beast?
I am to blame.
The cat is named Songzi. It was given to me by Consort Qi.
I only kept it as a pet for pleasure.
Songzi is usually very gentle. But she suddenly went wild today.
It is truly my fault.
You may rise.
What happened to Lady Wan?
Lady Wan stumbled when she attempted to save Lady Fucha.
Maybe she was injured.
Imperial doctor, check on Lady Wan.
Yes, Your Highness.
Congratulations, young mistress. You are with child, about two months.
Wonderful.
Don’t move.
You sit down. Sit down.
Doctor Zhang, are you certain that Lady Wan is with child?
I’ve been a doctor for several decades.
I’m quite confident of my diagnosis.
What happened today was entirely unexpected.
But Lady Wan, you’re quite careless.
You didn’t even realize that you were with child
and threw yourself down to save another.
It’s fortunate that you weren’t hurt.
What if an accident were to happen?
This is important news vital to the imperial family.
If I were to say that I was pushed, would you believe me?
I guess the true intention of that person
was to make me strike Lady Fucha’s belly.
If Lady Fucha were to miscarry, then I would be to blame.
Kill two birds with one stone.
Among the concubines in the harem,
those who carry a child will become the targets of all the others.
I’m afraid there are many who will not sleep well tonight.
Precisely.
Those who could not sleep due to Lady Fucha’s pregnancy
can finally sleep well tonight.
But when they think of you, young mistress,
they will pass another sleepless night.
Hasn’t that wretched creature been caught yet?
I’ve tried my best.
It seems that even such trifles still require my personal attention.
- Zhuxi. - Your Highness.
- Is it ready? - Yes, Your Highness.
I have been suffering from eye problems, so you think I’m blind.
It’s fortunate that my mind is still clear.
That vile creature has killed my own grandson.
Please forgive me, Your Highness.
Lady Fucha has lost her baby. It is beyond repair.
But as for Lady Wan’s baby, no further mishaps are to happen.
Consort Hua!
My lady, Consort Duan has already retired for the night.
If you’d like to visit, please return tomorrow.
- Hold her. - Yes, my lady.
My lady.
It’s been so many years.
Whenever you lost your temper, you would burst into my palace
in exactly the same pose as now.
It’s been so many years.
Whenever I think of my unborn child,
I wish I could eat your flesh and drink your blood.
It was you who served me that medicinal tonic.
You were the most inoffensive concubine. That’s why I trusted you somehow.
I never imagined you could be so vicious.
How could you kill my baby like that?
If you had any solid evidence,
you should have ended my life in the most terrible fashion.
Why are you still standing there?
As long as you dwell in the palace,
I will never let you off.
I will watch you linger on to your last breath
and make your life a living hell.
How’s your wound?
It’s healing.
This healing balm is made from my family’s traditional recipe.
It contains peach blossom and pearl powder which can give you a rosy complexion.
The most valuable ingredient is the marrow of white otter.
It can erase the scar, leaving your skin as good as new.
It’s best to use it while it’s still fresh.
Otherwise, as it grows stale, it will lose its effect.
It smells good.
At first I wanted to use perfume to regulate the odor.
But I realized that you should avoid perfumes since you’re pregnant.
So I used fresh flowers to regulate the odor instead.
In this case, it doesn’t smell like an ointment.
You are so thoughtful. I don’t know how to show my gratitude.
I’ve already told the Empress.
On the day Consort Jing is conferred, you will be promoted to Concubine Wan.
Huan Huan, what do you think?
It looks softer, not as stiff as a normal floral ornament.
Imitating its beauty is enough. It need not be exactly the same.
We’ll call it “Lovely Pear Blossom Makeup.”
My dear, as you created it, you may name it.
It’s very elegant and refined.
I’m afraid the others will think you are partial to me.
I am clearly partial only to you. Does that displease you?
Mei has only just recovered. Your Majesty, you should visit her.
I just did.
I somehow sensed that she received me coldly.
Mei has been ill for so long. It’s no surprise that she is dispirited.
Your Majesty, if she has displeased you, please forgive her.
Speaking of the illness,
a vexing question remains in my mind.
Is it proper for you to share it with me?
The other day Consort Jing told me
that Jiang Cheng and Jiang Shen have an effective treatment for the disease.
But they accept bribes in secret from many imperial maids and eunuchs.
They treat the powerful first
without even glancing at those of lower status.
They withhold the medicine and let them perish untreated.
But the epidemic has not abated. We must keep them alive.
I can recommend a doctor. He is able to treat the disease.
- Who? - Imperial Doctor Wen Shichu.
Why him?
When Doctor Wen treated Mei’s illness, she recovered effectively.
Besides, I have also heard
that Jiang Cheng and Jiang Shen’s remedy was derived from Doctor Wen’s work.
Your Majesty, if you don’t believe me, you may look into it.
Those who were treated by Doctor Wen recovered in a shorter time
and had no residual problems, like nausea or weakness.
What Doctor Jiang used was an old prescription drawn up by Doctor Wen.
The side effects were stronger.
I see.
After all, those two men work for Consort Hua.
But if I wish to remove them, there are many ways to do so.
Very well. Let’s change the subject.
April 17th is your birthday.
Moreover, you’re expecting.
I will order the Imperial Household Department to hold a celebration.
It is your decision, Your Majesty.
Good, leave it to me.
So long as it pleases you and the baby.
Your Majesty, you are very fond of children.
And you meet with Consort Hua quite often.
How is it that Consort Hua has not yet conceived a child?
She never will.
I understand that Consort Hua had a miscarriage before.
Did it cause a complication?
My lady.
The two Doctor Jiangs came to check on you.
But they left when they learned that His Majesty was coming to dine.
They said they would return in the evening.
By the way,
that pregnant woman at Suiyu Pavilion is unable to serve in bed.
Yet His Majesty visits her frequently.
Tell Doctor Jiang to remind His Majesty that he should avoid going there.
Xia Yi.
I wish to remove two men.
I await your orders.
Do it secretly and do not arouse suspicion.
XIA YI
As you wish, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty.
Jiang Cheng and Jiang Shen were killed by robbers on their way home last night.
Their heads are not to be found.
In the capital city, at the Emperor’s feet,
how can such a murder happen?
It’s outrageous!
My beloved concubine,
I was shocked to hear of this grievous event.
I’ve ordered an investigation. You may rest easy.
But with those two imperial doctors dead, the treatment of the epidemic–
You need not worry.
Here.
Throw more fish food here.
Don’t let some overeat while others starve to death.
- Over there. - Eunuch Yun. The fish here are well-fed.
Well-fed? Of course.
In those years, Consort Hua wished she could feed her enemies to the fish.
However, I do not believe Consort Hua was born like that.
Her behavior grew outrageous over time, for two reasons alone.
Having lost her own, she could not bear to see any other raise a child.
Loving the Emperor, she could not bear to see any other win his favor.
She was arrogant and capricious because she enjoyed the Emperor’s favor.
If not for her, I would not have lost my first imperial son.
Everyone in the harem feared her and hated her
but secretly hoped one day to become just like her.
Empress Dowager, aren’t you tired?
Let me help you walk to the pavilion for some rest.
Let us go.