It was here that I first met Marquess Guo.
He saw my bare feet
and expressed his admiration with quotations from the classics.
I flushed with shame, flustered and exasperated by what he said.
I never imagined that in the future
he would become the true love of my life.
And I would become his entire world as well.
The love between Yunli and myself has been a curing remedy in my life,
yet it also became the poison wine which he willingly drank.
My lady,
Consort Li would like to meet with you.
Very well.
Eunuch Su, keep it secret. Do not raise alarm.
Please rest easy. I shall see to it.
One more thing,
Consort Li would like to eat bitter almonds.
His Majesty has stated that all of her needs shall be provided.
She remains Consort Li.
Huan, you have come.
Look at me. Does my face show signs of aging?
Do I look the same as before?
Your face is unchanged.
Yet your heart is no longer as simple as it once was.
If I had remained as artless as before,
I likely would have died many times over in this harem.
Consort Hua was shrewd and overbearing.
The Empress is adept at intrigue.
I live in deep fear.
By night, I am set upon by nightmares.
Cruelty and humiliation have made my life unbearable.
Everyone finds life in the harem most difficult.
Yet no matter how difficult it becomes,
how much you must steel yourself at each step,
you should not do harm to those around you.
Especially those who have always treated you as a sister.
Once I believed your kindness was sincere.
Later I learned
that you treated me well,
always looked after me and lent me a hand
only to have me vie with Shen Meizhuang for the Emperor's favor.
All in order to consolidate your own status within the palace.
Since we entered the palace,
we have depended on one other for survival.
I would never force you to do anything you were unwilling to do.
During the time of Mei's confinement,
if I had not been allied with you,
we would have faced cruel oppression everywhere.
These bitter almonds are delicious.
After living in the palace for so long,
even bitter almonds taste sweet to me.
Do not bear grudges against me. And do not say that I am vicious.
For after all,
it is you I hate the most
because you possess everything
while I have nothing.
I knew full well that the aid the Empress offered me was insincere.
However, within the harem,
there is no such thing as sincerity.
Nights in the palace were so cold and so long
that I shudder to think how I survived every single second of those nights.
No matter how cold,
you should not warm yourself with the blood of others.
I will not hate you.
Nor will I forgive you.
For you are not worthy of either.
Exactly.
My entire life
has been unworthy from the start.
Huan.
I am sorry.
My life,
my very breath,
has never been mine to command.
Today,
it is finally up to me
to choose my own fate.
My lady, why did you remain inside for so long?
What did Consort Li say to you?
Nothing of importance.
She is truly pitiful.
Consort Li has passed away!
Hongli, it has been hot recently.
AISIN GIORO HONGLI
Your old maidservant says that you study until midnight every night.
Profound study is good, yet you must also care for your health.
Mother, you send me soup every night. I haven't felt tired at all.
The bowl of soup is to remind you that it is time for rest,
not to encourage further studies afterwards.
Then I have misunderstood.
I greet Noble Consort Xi and the Fourth Prince.
-The hour is late. -Concubine Ning.
Why do you stand here alone?
I've come by the order of His Majesty.
However, the Third Prince is inside now.
Eunuch Su says His Majesty is in a rage. He asked me to wait outside for a while.
By the way, Your Highness, I am told you are quite assiduous in your studies.
Can you recite the classics His Majesty mentioned just now?
How could I compare to the Third Brother? I started schooling at a later age.
If I am assiduous, it means I have much to learn.
That is why I spend much time on it. Otherwise, my teachers will reprimand me.
Study this passage thoroughly for three more days.
If you cannot interpret its meaning, do not come to see me anymore.
AISIN GIORO HONGSHI
I greet Noble Consort Xi and Concubine Ning.
You should go in now.
His Majesty was simply vexed.
It was inevitable that he spoke so harshly.
Do not pay it heed.
After all, you two are father and son. He will relent in a few days.
I understand.
The hour is late. I must excuse myself.
Mother, Third Brother studies quite hard.
I must study harder than he does. Only then will Imperial Father like me.
You told Concubine Ning you could not recite
the classics His Majesty mentioned.
Yet I overheard you reciting them a few days ago.
You were able to interpret those passages correctly and recite them fluently.
Mother, you never call attention to yourself.
I take instruction from your example. Of course I will do likewise.
You are quite astute.
We are family. Of course I resemble you.
Has everything been properly arranged for the Third Prince?
As you instructed, the Third Prince has composed a poem as a gift for His Majesty.
Many days were spent preparing it. His Majesty will surely be pleased.
On the late Emperor's birthday, His Majesty
shows special reverence for his father.
He will definitely be moved easily.
The Third Prince just needs to make an effort.
As the eldest son, it's natural His Majesty
places high expectations in him.
I will persuade the high-ranking officials to vouch for the Third Prince.
Hopefully, he will gain recognition and support
so that His Majesty may select him as Crown Prince with confidence.
With the aid of Your Highness, everything will turn out well.
Doctor Wei, what's wrong with my lady?
She cannot hold down her food, and her sleep is fitful at night.
What could be wrong?
I must send for Doctor Wen at once. Perhaps he can save the unborn child.
How has Noble Consort Xi fared these last two days?
The imperial doctor says she suffers from a digestive disorder.
She is continually ill and weak.
During the morning audience at court,
Ortai debated Maci.
I listened to their discussion.
It concerned the selection of Crown Prince.
Inside and outside the palace,
heaven knows how many people have their eyes fixed on this throne.
Selecting the Crown Prince openly will surely bring disorder.
I must devise a way to be prepared for any contingency.
Your Majesty, you are right.
I am well aware
that though the harem
seems calm and tranquil outwardly,
it is in fact filled with depravity.
My real concern
is that the harem and the state are linked
and entangled.
I must take precautions and be well prepared.
My lady,
I believe Wei Lin has done all that is possible.
-Unfortunately... -What is it?
You have carried this child only a short while,
yet you are in constant agitation and depression.
You are still weakened from the birth of the twins.
Now is not the time for another child.
My lady, four months have passed already.
This child...
Even though Wei Lin and I may do everything known to our medical art,
you will carry the child no more than five months.
-Five months? -Exactly.
Then the bond between us
will last no longer than one more month?
My lady, your health is of great importance.
You will conceive another child someday.
Tell no one
of what you know.
Help me to carry this child as long as possible.
Besides that,
you must prepare medication in advance
that will bring this to an end.
Perhaps at some point,
this child may yet do me a great favor.
I understand.
The officials of Qiongzhou have sent us a large red coral in tribute.
It is truly rare.
Hinayana Buddhism regards red coral as the reincarnation of Tathagata.
It would make the finest protective charm for the child.
With such a precious coral,
it would be a pity to hide it away.
We must invite all the concubines to Yongshou Palace to view it.
You may do as you wish.
It just so happens that the priest of Baohua Temple
has made some amulets to bless my unborn child.
The priest says it must be those of highest rank in the harem
to place each amulet in a blessed pouch and fasten it at my bedside.
Then the ritual will be completed.
The most suitable persons
are the Empress, Imperial Noble Consort Duan and Noble Consort Jing.
I myself will fasten one of them. That will complete the four corners.
It is an act that vouchsafes great blessings, they will not refuse.
The Empress rarely comes out nowadays.
She has refused all invitations from others.
However, if the Empress is absent, the ritual will not be perfect.
If it is your wish, I will issue the invitation personally.
Why has the Empress failed to arrive?
Could it be that the Empress is displeased with me?
No, it can't be.
She is the Empress. She is obliged to be magnanimous.
Her Highness the Empress!
Your Highness, may blessings and peace be with you.
I greet Your Majesty. May blessings and peace be with you.
-Please rise. -Yes, Your Majesty.
Even in your illness, I asked you to come. I have troubled you. Do you resent me?
How could I?
Your Majesty and myself are joined as a couple.
How could I not be concerned for Noble Consort Xi?
The Empress is most virtuous.
Your Highness,
the priest says these amulets and blessed pouches are auspicious tokens.
They can secure peace and good health for my unborn child.
But I must trouble Your Highness and two high-ranking concubines
to place each amulet in a blessed pouch
and then fasten them at my bedside.
It is no trouble. It is our pleasure.
Your Majesty, Noble Consort Xi is carrying a child.
Naturally, the tutelary god is guarding over her bedchamber.
I bring my illness.
Moreover, a stranger may offend the god by entering the bedchamber. It is unwise.
Imperial Noble Consort Duan and Noble Consort Jing
do not mind performing this modest task.
Why do you try to avoid it with so many excuses?
As head of the harem, you should be responsible for maintaining harmony
and set an example for all the concubines.
Yes, Your Majesty.
We servants are too lowly to touch these auspicious items.
Therefore, we shall not enter my lady's bedchamber with you
lest we offend the gods.
It would not be wise.
You are right. We must be especially cautious with regard to such matters.
I will carry them.
My lady, you have not taken your medicinal tonic yet.
You said it was too hot when it was sent to you earlier.
Now it is merely warm.
If you don't take it now, it will cool down.
The Empress is truly exemplary when she reveals her virtuous nature.
She has always disliked Noble Consort Xi.
Nonetheless, she now yields to her for the greater good.
Do not speak ill of the Empress.
I am grateful to Your Highness for fulfilling my wish,
for agreeing to fasten this blessed pouch for me.
I am the Empress. I am obliged to do so.
You are bound by custom to do so.
But inwardly, Your Highness must hate me to the core.
I hope you can maintain your composure and not lose yourself in distractions.
Your first priority now should be the birth of His Majesty's child.
Whether the child will be born or not depends entirely on the Empress, not me.
Impudence! How dare you slander me!
Slander?
Let go.
Will you swear upon the gods that you have never harmed any imperial heirs,
that you have never harmed any of the concubines, including myself?
I am head of the harem. How could I swear vows by your command?
Why did Consort Qi die?
Why did Concubine Ning become barren?
Lady Fucha miscarried
and I lost my own child.
So many shameful things, all originating with you.
-How did it happen? -What's wrong with my lady?
My lady.
What happened to my lady?
My lady, what's the matter?
Help! My lady!
-Huan Huan. -Your Majesty, she has fainted.
Summon the doctor.
-Go quickly. -Imperial doctor!
Noble Consort Xi, you are awake.
Noble Consort Xi, please contain your grief.
You will conceive another child someday.
"I will conceive another child someday"?
You say that so plainly.
Was the life of my child so insignificant?
Your Highness,
no matter how great your hatred for me,
why did you have to harm my child?
Preposterous! When did I harm your child?
Your Majesty.
I have lost my child.
It was not caused by my carelessness.
It was Her Highness the Empress.
She and I came into conflict.
Then she pushed me.
Your Majesty, her abdomen indeed shows signs of a heavy blow.
Any imperial doctor can verify this.
She had to be pushed forcefully by someone.
Besides, her unborn child had been of sound health.
It is probable that Your Majesty has even felt the child move.
If not for an accident, she would not have miscarried.
Empress,
only you and Noble Consort Xi were in the bedchamber at that time.
Your Majesty.
There are many witnesses here, including myself.
As Noble Consort Xi lay injured and prone, the Empress was the only person near her.
Your Majesty.
The Empress has long begrudged me the favor shown to me.
She has always felt I disrespected her. So she scolded me.
In a fit of rage, she pushed me.
At that moment, Noble Consort Xi grew desperate and dared grasp my hand.
I struggled vigorously to shake her grip. But I never pushed Noble Consort Xi.
Empress, from what you have said,
you mean that it was Noble Consort Xi who tossed herself to the ground?
You have said that Noble Consort Xi became desperate,
then how on earth did she offend you?
Only Noble Consort Xi and I were inside the bedchamber.
There's nothing I can say on that account.
But if it appears I had some role in this,
it is because someone has arranged things to appear that way.
You claim there's nothing you can say.
But there's nothing I can say to explain how this happened either.
You have always disliked Noble Consort Xi. I know that full well.
Yet Noble Consort Xi has always shown deference to you to maintain harmony.
Your Majesty, there is no reason for me to harm Noble Consort Xi.
I swear upon my ancestors of the Ula Nara clan.
I have done nothing to harm the unborn child of Noble Consort Xi!
You would do better to swear it again
before the memorial of the Empress Dowager.
The Empress is vicious and has harmed an imperial heir.
Henceforward,
she will be confined to Jingren Palace.
-Su Peisheng. -Your Majesty.
-Take her away. -Yes, sir.
Your Highness, please come with me.
Mother, I know you are grieved at the death of my unborn brother.
I transcribed some prayer flags and burned them for my little brother.
I hope he may find peace.
You are truly dutiful to family.
How fares the Third Prince?
The Third Prince and the Empress are as closely united as hand in glove.
Naturally, with the Empress present,
the Third Prince is likely to win the throne.
And with the Third Prince present, the Empress has one more ally.
Yes, I understand.
Fourth Brother, you are always studying. How are you at leisure today?
It is our Eighth Uncle's birthday.
I visited him at the prison of the Imperial Clan Court.
You dared to visit our Eighth Uncle? Were you not afraid of being seen?
Of course I concealed it from others.
But I dare not hide it from my own brother.
How fares our Eighth Uncle?
How else? His title was revoked and he is imprisoned in unbearable conditions.
Third Brother, I wish to tell you something,
but I don't know if it is appropriate.
We are brothers. We can dispense with formalities.
Our father imprisoned several clan relatives
due to struggles over the throne.
The Eighth Uncle and the 14th Uncle are both brothers to our Imperial Father.
If we intercede for them and thus allow our Imperial Father to forgive them,
not only will his reputation be cemented,
sparing him condemnation as a fratricide for hundreds of years,
but it will also allow the Empress Dowager to rest in peace.
The late Emperor's birthday is next month.
If the opportunity arises,
I plan to beg our father to forgive the Eighth Uncle and the 14th Uncle.
It will also show deep filial piety towards
the late Emperor and the Empress Dowager.
Brother, you have given much thought to this.
It had not even occurred to me.
Very well. If the opportunity arises on that day,
I will ask our father to show mercy and try to convince him.
Good.
Your Highness, bad news!
The Third Prince has been removed from the imperial lineage
and renamed son of the Eighth Lord.
What are you talking about?
The Imperial Clan Court has already received the decree.
Nonsense!
The Third Prince is His Majesty's own son. How can it be?
I dare not lie.
The Third Prince interceded for the 14th Lord,
the Eighth Lord and yourself.
His Majesty berated him for his disloyalty.
Everything was going well. Why did he intercede for those offenders?
All the painstaking effort I have spent over so many years was in vain.
It was all in vain!
You must devise a way to save the Prince.
Useless fool!
His Majesty has always been ruthless.
And now, the ties between father and son have broken.
Your Highness, if the Third Prince cannot be selected as Crown Prince...
Without the Third Prince, he still has the Fourth Prince and the Fifth Prince.
In the worst case, the Sixth Prince may be chosen as well.
The Sixth Prince?
Just as took place after Consort Qi died.
Without Zhen Huan,
I could raise the Sixth Prince.
As long as I remain the Empress,
as long as a chance remains for me to reestablish myself,
it doesn't matter whose child he is.
As long as I am appointed his mother,
I will be the one true Empress Dowager.
-Have you prepared what I asked for? -It is ready now.
The Empress knows nothing of it. Should we report it to her?
A master disgraced while her servants do nothing!
I have served the Empress for years. Never has she suffered such humiliation.
The Empress herself, framed by a lowly concubine and confined to her palace.
The Empress's hopes for the Third Prince are dashed as well.
It is utterly intolerable.
Give it to me.
Yunli.
The birthday celebration for our late Imperial Father is now finished.
Whenever I recall the times when our Imperial Father lived
and the guidance he gave the both of us,
I have always felt sorrowful.
But were our father here today,
were he to see you married and expecting a child so soon,
MENG JINGXIAN
he would truly be gratified.
Everything I have was given by Your Majesty's grace.
Your little cousin is within my belly.
-Sixth Prince, do you like him? -I want a girl cousin.
My lord, what do you think?
Very well.
Hongyan, come to your mother for soup.
Don't bother Secondary Princess Consort Xian.
I want Auntie to feed me.
Fine. I will feed you, good boy.
Hongyan is still young, yet he likes Xian's baby very much.
It appears they have been brought together by fate.
They are cousins, of course they are together by fate.
Jingxian.
Jingxian, what's the matter? Jingxian!
Imperial doctor!
What happened? She was well just a moment ago.
It appears she has been poisoned.
The food is poisoned! Imperial guards, protect His Majesty!
Your Majesty, if Xian has been poisoned, you'd best return to Yangxin Hall at once.
-Your Majesty. -I shall not leave.
I must stay to discover who could be so audacious
as to carry out an assassination in my presence.
It is crane's red crown.
Crane's red crown?
That's not good. The child is already mature.
Quickly, prepare the medicine to hasten delivery.
-My lord. -Go! Hurry up!
Your Majesty, Secondary Princess Consort Xian has been poisoned.
What was the last thing she ate?
Your Majesty,
Secondary Princess Consort Xian tasted the Sixth Prince's soup.
The silver needle has turned black. This bowl of soup is poisonous.
Check this one as well.
This one is poisonous as well.
Your Majesty, someone intended to kill Hongyan and myself.
Xian was simply caught in between.
Investigate at once!
Yes, Your Majesty.
My lord.
It was I who plied you with drink.
That is how our child was conceived.
Do not speak of it now.
I am by your side.
I will always remain by your side.
The maid who served the soup to Noble Consort Xi and the Sixth Prince
states that on her way she crossed paths with Jianqiu of Jingren Palace.
Jianqiu opened the lid of the food box and asked what was inside.
Aside from her, no other is suspicious.
I have brought Jianqiu here.
-Bring her here. -Yes, Your Majesty.
Was it the Empress?
The Empress remains confined. She knew nothing of this.
I planned it on my own.
She is going to commit suicide.
Your Majesty, why didn't you trust Her Highness the Empress?
She is your wife. She has truly loved you.
Take her to the Office of Punishment for interrogation by torture.
She must be forced to tell the truth.
Take her away!
Noble Consort Xi, aren't you afraid of being punished in the end?
Fate will bring you to a miserable end!
Noble Consort Xi, you are a vile wretch!
Your Majesty, it is a baby boy.
Yet Secondary Princess Consort Xian was so weakened by her labor
that she was unable to endure the poison and has expired.
All has been confessed.
In addition to the plot on Noble Consort Xi,
much more was revealed.
I dare not hide it from Your Majesty.
What is it?
Your Majesty, it concerns the cause of Empress Chunyuan's death.
It is linked to the Empress.
Impudence!
I dare not lie.
Speak. Spare me no detail.
Your Majesty, I have consulted the imperial doctors.
They say the plantain is of cold nature. Normally, eating a little causes no harm.
But a woman who carries a child should not consume any.
Because the plantain has the same effect as peach stone and safflower,
it can unblock the blood and relieve swelling.
The effect is not as strong as safflower.
Yet if steamed together with other foods, its properties may infiltrate that food.
After many exposures, it may be harmful to health.
Besides, an ingredient of the almond milk tea
was also replaced by peach stone, which is harmful to the fetus.
Since it was blended into the tea, it was difficult to recognize by taste.
All of these ingredients
had always been slipped into the food of Empress Chunyuan.
Did the servants admit this with their own mouths?
Jianqiu was mercilessly tortured, yet she didn't say a word.
However, Jiang Fuhai has confessed to everything.
At such a juncture, do you admit your own guilt?
Your Majesty, since you already believe it is so,
why bother to ask?
Were I not obliged to hear your confession myself
do you think I would willingly look upon your face?
This pair of jade bracelets was given to me when I married you.
You personally placed them on my wrists.
At the time,
you took this bracelet in hand and told me
if I should someday give birth to a son,
I would become your primary spouse.
Yet when I did give birth to a son,
you had already married my sister as your primary spouse.
Even my son was forced to accept the rank of a concubine's son.
Just as I did,
he endured scorn as the child of a concubine.
How could you truly understand
how hard it is to be the child of a concubine?
It is precisely because I understood
that I have treated you well since we married.
Even though Chunyuan was my only primary spouse,
I made you my secondary spouse, second only to her.
Chunyuan was your own sister.
Were you not afraid of the consequences?
During the nighttime,
had you no fear that Chunyuan and her child
would haunt you and claim your life?
If she wanted to claim my life, she could have just come for me.
But during the long nights,
the incessant crying of my own child haunted my dreams.
At the moment I lost my own child, my sister learned that she was expecting.
Your Majesty, you were overjoyed by my sister's pregnancy
and had already forgotten our own child.
He was less than three years old.
His body was scalding hot with fever.
He died from an incurable illness.
Unexpectedly, my sister conceived at the very same time.
Was it not her son that claimed my son's life?
How could I allow her son to become the Crown Prince?
What madness.
It was I who insisted on marrying Chunyuan.
It was I who took her as my primary spouse.
It was I who conceived a child with her.
Why did you not hate me instead?
You think I didn't want to hate you?
But I could not.
I truly could not.
You only cared for my sister.
Your Majesty, did you ever know
that my love for you was no less than your love for my sister?
Every woman who truly loves her husband
could never bear to watch her beloved husband
fall in love and have a child with another woman.
I cannot bear it.
I truly cannot bear it.
Though you think I am spiteful and jealous,
I am the one who has loved you most truly.
That is why I have acted in this way.
Honeyed words but evil intent.
You truly disgust me.
The Empress, descended from the Ula Nara clan,
has not been blessed by heaven, and is utterly deceitful.
She harmed imperial heirs and conspired with imperial officials.
She is unsuitable to be a member of the
royal family, a model mother to the nation.
Thus, she will be demoted to the status of a commoner
and sent to the Cold Palace.
-Su Peisheng. -Your Majesty.
Announce my decree to the harem.
She and I
shall never meet again in this lifetime nor in death.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty,
Moge Khan of the Dzungar Mongols is overweening and ambitious.
He is moving towards Yanming Pass with a cavalry of 400,000.
Once Yanming Pass is occupied by the enemy,
the capital will be placed in a critical situation.
The Dzungar Mongols are nothing more than a tribe of the steppes.
Even they dare to challenge me now.
If we must appoint another capable general at this moment,
it will probably prove quite difficult.
It is easier to raise an army of thousands than it is to find one good general.
For a leader to send to the battlefront, the Imperial Dukes are the best choice.
After careful consideration,
I believe Marquess Guo is the best choice.
Marquess Guo has always known his place.
Your Majesty, you have considered every detail. Most admirable.
He is fond of poetry and literature.
It matters not if I promote him to duke and grant him undeserved recognition.
It is the skilled generals that must be chosen with care.
I understand.
Once the situation at the battlefront becomes somewhat stable,
we shall send him to guard Yanming Pass.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Flowers in blossom and the full moon, symbols of a conjugal bliss which endures.
Flowers in blossom and the full moon are easy to attain.
Yet lovers' moments together do not endure.
Huan, at this very moment,
I hope you are enjoying peace and happiness beneath this moonlight.
Are these letters authentic?
Have you confirmed that the handwriting is his?
Yes, I have.
When I greeted Secondary Princess Consort Yu,
I took them from the lowest drawer of her dressing table.
Are they all here?
I was afraid they would be noticed missing.
Thus, I only took a few.
How fares Duke Guo?
Your Majesty, Duke Guo has guarded Yanming Pass for three years.
During this time, the Dzungars have not launched a single attack.
He guards the borderlands and
commands the troops with strict discipline.
He drinks with and bunks beside his generals and soldiers.
Despite his high status, he is not haughty or imperious.
The generals and soldiers respect and support him to the last man.
So he hopes to purchase popular support.
I have already read his memorandum.
He writes, "The breezes of spring have not yet arrived at Yumen Pass."
He describes life in the borderlands as very harsh.
He suggests that we show consideration for the soldiers and the populace there
and recommence frontier trade
so the people of the borderlands may live in prosperity and contentment.
Duke Guo's opinion is most reasonable.
No matter how reasonable, his opinion is unnecessary.
I ordered him to guard the borderlands,
not to interfere with the affairs of state.
Your Majesty, please do not stoke your anger.
You are taking the remedy prescribed by the imperial doctors.
You must not indulge your anger while taking it.
Three years have passed.
Summon him back to the capital to report on his mission.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, Noble Consort Xi is here.
Your Majesty, may blessings and peace be with you.
You are here.
-You may retire now. -Yes, my lady.
Your forehead is covered with sweat.
That is the first time I've struck you since you came to the palace.
If Your Majesty intends to strike me, then I must bear it.
However, please instruct me on what I have done wrong.
Instruct you?
Yunli has returned. You must be quite content.
I only feel content for Huanbi.
Was it you or Huanbi who longed for Yunli's return?
You know full well in your heart.
Since we were children, Imperial Father always loved Yunli most.
If not for the objections of the officials,
another man would be sitting on this throne.
Now he leads the troops by my decree.
If he harbors disloyal intentions, just as Duke Dun once did...
-I cannot help but be wary of him. -Your Majesty, Duke Guo would never...
How can you know what thoughts run through his mind?
I always knew he harbored improper thoughts for you.
I dare not think it.
Proper relations between the Emperor and his
officials come before bonds of fraternity.
If the Emperor orders an official to die, he has no choice but to do so.
Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, please reconsider.
Duke Guo is of great military merit and has never made an error.
If Your Majesty intends to dispose of him,
I'm afraid it will tarnish your reputation.
You have never failed to carry out my instructions.
Therefore, at this time,
I intend to entrust you with another task.
I must dispose of Yunli.
I simply offer you the chance
to prove to me by your actions
that you do not harbor improper thoughts for him.
-I greet Your Majesty. -Your Grace, it is Noble Consort Xi.
His Majesty asked me to meet him here.
His Majesty drank overmuch, so he asked Noble Consort Xi to come first.
His Majesty will come after he bathes and changes.
So I must trouble you again, Noble Consort Xi.
No need for such courtesy, Your Grace.
This fine wine was sent by His Majesty.
My lady, please accompany the Duke.
I will escort His Majesty here.
I seldom have the chance to drink with the Duke.
Just as in the past. It is summer once again.
You still like to dress in light pink.
Your Grace,
over these years,
you have suffered greatly in the borderlands.
Noble Consort Xi, have you ever heard this saying?
"Yearning for a life long in years,
"we share the same moonlight even a thousand miles apart."
As long as my heart knows that this shared moonlight
also shines for another who lives in peace and health,
then it doesn't matter in what straits I find myself.
The best days of my life were the ones we shared at Mount Lingyun.
Then tonight,
allow me to indulge myself just this once.
There is a draft. Please close the window first.
Look at the decoration on the window. Does it not suit the occasion well?
It is a drawing of silk tree flowers.
Do such brilliant colors not recall the decorations of a wedding ceremony?
Mother was fond of silk tree flowers.
When they built Tung Blossom Terrace, Imperial Father ordered
that all the windows be decorated with this flower.
Silk tree flowers represent tenderness and everlasting love.
Didn't silk trees use to grow all around Ninghui Hall?
Two hearts united as one bring true joy.
It's a pity that no matter how deeply Imperial Father loved Mother,
he could never remain by her side alone.
Nor can I.
I pity Jingxian.
I pity Huanbi.
But I have even greater pity for you.
Don't say such sad words.
I fear if I do not say so now, I will not have another chance.
-Nonsense! -Isn't it true?
Let us not speak of such things.
Then I will say,
"Let us commit ourselves to one another for life, two souls eternally united."
If only we may live in harmonious matrimony,
"our days filled with peace and joy.
Look, I have emptied my cup.
Let this wine seal our wedlock.
I did not leave a single drop.
I want to tell you something.
Now that I have lived out this moment in my life,
I have no regrets at all.
Let me hold you in my arms again.
Hongyan was very naughty as a small child,
yet very clever.
Unlike Lingxi,
who was self-possessed from the start.
One is active, the other quiet.
They do not seem twins at all.
Yunli.
Yunli, what is it?
A jug that contains two wines, one poisoned, the other unpoisoned.
I know His Majesty well.
He allowed you to come alone after nightfall.
I knew it was unusual.
When you left the table to close the window,
I exchanged our cups.
Huan.
I had to spare you this difficult task.
My fate was sealed long ago.
His Majesty intends that I die.
How could I remain alive?
Don't leave me.
I am your wife. Take me away from the palace.
I don't want to stay here.
In my heart,
you have always been my one, true...
wife.
I never told you
that Hongyan and Lingxi
are both yours.
My lady, you have emerged.
By secret imperial edict,
if my lady should emerge, then I am to deliver another edict.
If, besides my lady, another should emerge as well,
then I am to kill the both of you on sight.
I am safe and well and have already emerged.
-Then... -Duke Guo
is dead.
Eunuch, please read the imperial edict.
Noble Consort Xi, kneel to receive the decree.
By the grace of heaven, the Emperor hereby decrees
that the Empress has misbehaved, leaving the harem leaderless.
Therefore, we appoint Noble Consort Xi
to take charge of the harem for the present.
Her status will be that of a Secondary Empress.
Issued by His Imperial Majesty.
My lady, this is an unprecedented elevation.
His Majesty knew you would be tired.
He especially instructed me to escort you to your residence for rest.
I want my father, I want...
Do not cry. It is forbidden.
Madam, it is owing to His Majesty's mercy
that your private mourning has been allowed.
Nevertheless, he has decreed that no lamentations must be heard.
His Majesty has unrighteously harmed his own brother.
Of course he allows no one to speak of it. Even crying out is forbidden.
Never say such words, madam. It is greatly disrespectful.
What should a person like me be frightened of?
It is time now. Move the coffin.
Madam.
Yunli, don't leave me behind!
Madam!
Mantra of Rebirth in The Pure Land
-My lady, Su Peisheng is here. -My lady.
What is it?
My lady, you must contain your grief.
Huanbi has followed Duke Guo and passed away.
-My lady. -My lady, do not despair.
His Majesty has been moved by her devotion.
She will be honored as Primary Spouse
and buried together with Duke Guo in the borderlands by imperial edict.
What of Yuanche?
As he is young, His Majesty says he is
to be raised by Marquess Shen and his wife.
Duke Guo died so suddenly. His Majesty is sorely grieved
and was forced to keep his death hidden to prevent others from talking about it.
He has grown gaunt over the last several days.
-Advise him to contain his grief. -Yes, my lady.
There is something I need you to investigate for me.
My lady, I am at your service.
Why was His Majesty
obliged to kill Duke Guo so suddenly?
It appears it was on account of some letters.
Letters?
"Wish Noble Consort Xi well."
This phrase was written at the end of every letter he sent home.
Jinxi.
It was on every letter.
It showed that Duke Guo had deep concern for you, my lady.
That's what led to his death.
How did His Majesty come to possess these letters?
Xia Yi.
Xia Yi is the leader of an organization called the Cicada Removal Service.
They are assassins, known as the Guillotines.
They secretly pore over affairs of state
and purge all opposing voices to His Majesty.
So that is what it was.
-I greet Noble Consort Xi. -You may rise.
I just passed by Ninghui Hall
and saw the eunuchs cutting down all the silk trees by imperial decree.
His Majesty found it discordant that their flowers fall in late autumn.
His Majesty could not even bear the sight of those silk trees.
Yet I think His Majesty is right.
As their owner is no longer here, they may as well be cut down.
Those silk tree flowers
were planted by Yunli as a gift to celebrate
your conferment as Noble Consort.
I was afraid you would be distressed over this.
So I told His Majesty that I do not sleep well at night
and need to keep those silk tree flowers for medicinal use.
Fortunately, His Majesty agreed.
He ordered someone to replant the silk trees at my palace.
I appreciate that.
Then don't let him off easily.
No hurry.
Your Majesty,
even though you are still young and healthy,
a Crown Prince must be selected without delay.
Among the imperial heirs, the Fourth Prince is the eldest.
I suggest that the Fourth Prince be selected as Crown Prince
and let him share responsibility for affairs of state with Your Majesty.
The Crown Princes of this dynasty have never been selected according to age.
Virtue and talent is all that matters.
Your Majesty,
the Fourth Prince has been raised outside the palace and not much educated.
Among the imperial heirs, I find the Sixth Prince most intelligent.
Your Majesty,
though the Sixth Prince is intelligent,
he is still young and his mother is in her prime.
Should Noble Consort Xi become Empress Dowager,
she will control the court and the state will fall into a woman's hands.
I hope the Crown Prince will be selected rightly.
Your Majesty, please hear my opinion.
Speak.
Those who say that Hongyan is overly young and unqualified to become Crown Prince
have evil thoughts in their hearts.
Your Majesty, you are in good health.
Why not wait until Hongyan reaches his 30s?
I don't care for this point of view either.
So, you still believe that our son is the best choice,
do you not?
Hongyan's skills are modest,
not suitable for selection as Crown Prince.
So in the long run,
the Fourth Prince is the best choice.
The Fourth Prince is not your biological son.
Your Majesty, at issue is the choice of a Crown Prince,
not whether he is my biological son.
My return to the palace has already provoked
much discussion amongst the populace.
I do not wish to become the target of intrigue,
forcing Your Majesty to choose between your officials and our marital affection.
Mother, I bow in respect before you.
You may rise.
During the morning audience at court, Imperial Father conferred me as Duke Bao.
It is natural.
You are the eldest son, and should be first
to be named Duke among the princes.
Yet Hongyan has not been conferred as a Duke yet.
The Sixth Prince is still young.
Besides, I hope
that he will be conferred as a Duke by you someday.
Mother.
If you understand what I mean, then you should know what to do.
Don't show your emotions on your face and don't let others know your thoughts.
Moreover, don't let others guess your preferences easily.
We hermits wish Your Majesty a joyous birthday and a long life.
To celebrate Your Majesty's birthday,
my fellow disciple and I have developed another two pellets of elixir.
We humbly present them to you, Your Majesty.
I begin to wonder,
after taking these pellets, will I truly live a long life?
Your Majesty, your complexion looks much better than before.
I have been by your side every day.
I also notice that you are full of vigor and more energetic than before.
Very well then.
Your Majesty, you must not exert yourself after taking the elixir.
Please remember my advice.
Why have you rushed here at this late hour?
My lady, Concubine Ning asked me for a certain substance this afternoon.
-What kind of substance? -An aphrodisiac that stimulates desire.
She enjoys His Majesty's favor now. Why did she ask for such things?
Concubine Ning especially requested the incense left behind by Consort Li.
Yet that matters not.
More importantly, she asked for cinnabar as well.
Cinnabar? What is it for?
My lady, you may not know, but since His Majesty ascended the throne,
he has continuously taken elixirs intended to increase his longevity.
The elixir contains sulfur and mercury.
Though it is just slightly poisonous, when catalyzed by cinnabar,
it will appear that he grows stronger, when in fact he grows weaker within.
When combined with the effect of the aphrodisiac fragrances,
then his health will decline both within and without.
I dare not provide Concubine Ning with cinnabar.
Concubine Ning simply asked for cinnabar.
Perhaps she will use it for another purpose.
If you are concerned about her motives, then do not give it to her.
If she truly wishes to obtain some,
she will find a way to do so.
Yes, I understand.
BITONG STUDY HALL
It is summer once again.
His Majesty has been recuperating intermittently for six months now.
He should be enjoying a peaceful life here in Yuanming Palace.
But he has never recovered.
His Majesty is concerned about affairs of state.
Tell Su Peisheng to send the memoranda to His Majesty.
He will surely read them.
He has read every last one.
However, his health has worsened considerably.
How could he read dispatches for 12 or 14 hours a day as in the past?
Where are Hongyan and Lingxi?
Princess Lingxi went to Noble Consort Jing's residence
to play with Princess Longyue.
The Sixth Prince is having fun with Marquess Shen's wife in the garden.
It is already summer.
Why do I still feel cold inside, as if the heat was drained from my body?
Your Majesty, you are quite healthy now.
You have outdone yourself in the bedchamber recently.
Some caution is advised.
Slow down, Prince.
Who is that?
Slow down.
Your Majesty, Marquess Shen's wife
has come to the palace with the Duke's son.
They are playing with the Sixth Prince.
-The Duke's son? -Yes, Your Majesty.
Yuanche, Yunli's son?
Exactly.
His Majesty the Emperor!
-I greet Your Majesty. -I greet the Imperial Father.
You may rise.
Come here. You come too.
They resemble each other. Yet Hongyan looks stronger.
The Sixth Prince is older and much stronger.
Yet he resembles the Duke's son very much.
It's as if they were true brothers.
Let me take a look.
They do look alike.
Especially in the eyes and the chin.
Your Majesty!
This concerns the imperial bloodline.
This task must be performed with considerable prudence.
No one must know.
You may rely on me.
Why did you bring them here?
If I had not,
your son would already have been strangled in his sleep without your knowledge.
-Jinxi. -Yes, my lady.
-Xiao Yunzi. -Yes, madam.
Send the children to the bedchamber.
Xia Yi incapacitated everyone with sleep-inducing incense
and pricked Hongyan's toe to obtain his blood.
Xia Yi works for His Majesty.
His Majesty must have instructed him to prove kinship by another blood test.
Yet something escapes me.
Why would His Majesty need to do another blood test?
Who exactly is Hongyan's father?
I am truly indebted to you.
You have done me a great service.
You have saved Yunli's children.
They are Duke Guo's children?
Are they, indeed?
The situation is dire.
He had it done to Hongyan and Lingxi. He must have grown suspicious.
You should be well prepared.
His Majesty is seriously ill.
We can no longer allow Xia Yi to live.
It is not enough simply to dispose of Xia Yi.
From here forward,
what I do is of no concern to you, it is not your business.
Care well for Duke Guo's children.
I am thirsty.
I need water.
Of course.
Your Majesty, it's time for you to take the elixir.
Allow me to help you with it.
Here, let me help you.
I remember
when you first joined the harem,
you were haughty and aloof.
But now
you have grown gentle and tender.
Your Majesty, have you ever heard the saying,
"Tenderness can kill a man just like a cut of a knife"?
I greet Your Majesty.
Where is Xia Yi?
The medicine is ready.
Your Majesty, why did you have the ginseng soup first?
Xia Yi.
Xia Yi has failed to serve Your Majesty well.
Instead, he has caused you great concern.
Your Majesty, I have already disposed of him for you.
You killed him?
You have always instructed me that
there is no need to keep useless people alive.
So you found out.
I have been living a peaceful life under your protection.
I depend entirely upon Your Majesty.
I need not trouble myself with anything more.
I have always appreciated your honesty.
I would like to ask you a question.
I will surely answer without reservation.
Hongyan...
Is he not my own son?
Of course.
Your Majesty, all the people of this nation are your children.
Well said.
You are right.
The entire nation is mine.
Yet very soon it will be yours.
What do I need the entire nation for?
I never obtained the one thing I have desired all this time.
Throughout my life,
perhaps at one time I did obtain what I desired.
However, like sand that slips through your fingers
in the end, nothing remains.
Huan Huan.
It has been a long time since you called me "my dear".
Speak to me that way once again.
Would you?
Your Majesty, you are tired.
Rest a while.
I'd like to retire now.
Call me "my dear" once more.
Just as you did when you first entered the palace.
The Zhen Huan of those days has already died.
Have you forgotten, Your Majesty?
It was you who killed her.
I am Niohuru Zhen Huan.
We may never return to those days.
We may never return.
Huan Huan and I.
Chunyuan and I.
To those grand times
we may never return.
Because of Yunli,
you now hate me to the core, don't you?
Your Majesty, you are truly wise.
Yet please rest easy, Your Majesty.
No matter how much I hate you,
I will raise Princess Jinghe with nurturing care.
If Mei could know that the child she bore to Wen Shichu
has been doted on by Your Majesty for all these years,
I think she would be happy in the underworld.
Vile wench!
I must kill you!
Compared to Your Majesty's ruthlessness at killing your own brothers,
I am certainly no match for you.
I may as well tell you another truth, Your Majesty.
Every moment I was by your side after returning to the palace,
every moment I shared with you,
was infinitely repulsive to me.
Concubine Ning has felt the same.
Someone.
Help me.
Help you?
The sentries at the doorways have been sent away.
Your Majesty, you have just consumed the ginseng soup.
Angering yourself is not good for your health.
It will only cause depression and intensify your inner heat.
Your Majesty, please calm your anger.
My dear.
Long ago, we met in the rain surrounded by apricot blossoms.
You claimed to be Marquess Guo.
Perhaps from the very beginning,
it was all a mistake.
His Majesty
has just passed away.
IN MEMORY OF THE YONGZHENG EMPEROR
All bow.
Rise.
All bow a third time.
All stand.
The ritual is completed.
A nation cannot afford one day without a sovereign.
Noble Consort Xi, please take charge of the selection.
Noble Consort Xi is the mother of two princes.
How can she take charge of the succession to the throne?
When the late Emperor was alive,
Noble Consort Xi was in charge of the Harem as Secondary Empress.
Of course she is capable.
How can a woman of the harem manage affairs of state?
When the late Emperor lived, he mentioned the succession many times.
He also did instruct me before his death.
I dare not lie.
Today, as all the dukes are assembled here,
I must tell you the truth.
The late Emperor has personally written a secret imperial edict.
The Fourth Prince, Hongli,
of noble character, having grown experienced and mature,
should ascend the throne.
How can the succession to the throne be decided by your unilateral statement?
When the Emperor was gravely ill, the Fourth Prince supervised the nation.
Duke Heng, do you intend to disrespect the late Emperor?
So this is why you doubted everything.
You...
The late Emperor showed great foresight.
He sealed the secret imperial edict with yellow paper,
kept it in a brocade box,
and hid it behind the "Justice and Honesty"
tablet that hangs in Qianqing Palace.
All lords and officials may proceed to Qianqing Palace and examine it.
THE FOUNDATION OF A POWERFUL AND PEACEFUL NATION
QIANLONG
All kneel!
You are here.
The Empress has sharp eyes and ears just as in the old days.
Today is the enthronement ceremony.
Apart from you, who else could pay me a visit at her leisure?
You haven't changed at all.
Exactly the same face I have hated all this time.
Impudence! How dare you disrespect the Empress Dowager?
Kneel now.
The new Emperor has ascended the throne!
She is the mother of the new Emperor
and has become the Holy Mother Empress Dowager.
The late Emperor never revoked my title. I am still his Empress.
Your Highness, your thoughts are muddled.
When the late Emperor lived, she was Noble Consort, in charge of the harem.
Now the Fourth Prince has ascended the throne
and acknowledged her as the one true Empress Dowager.
You did not let your own son become Emperor.
What kind of mother are you?
Being the Emperor is not the highest enjoyment on this earth.
How much did the late Emperor suffer for the intrigues of his concubines?
Not even he himself could say.
I fear greatly
lest my own son would marry an Empress such as you in the future.
How vicious you are!
How can you go against the late Emperor? How can you disregard his decree?
The late Emperor indeed promised never
to reject the Empress of the Ula Nara clan.
Therefore, you will remain Empress as long as you live.
I've decided the Emperor will be buried beside
Empress Chunyuan at Tailing Mausoleum.
After your death, you will be buried in the Tomb of the Concubines.
Please enjoy the rest of your days,
Empress.
Empress?
Empress!
I have been considering something recently.
Your Majesty, I would like to discuss it with you today.
Queen Mother, please speak.
Hongyan is my youngest son.
He was candidate for Crown Prince in the late Emperor's heart.
Now Hongyan has grown up.
If any rumors spread again and shake the foundations of the nation,
then I will be blamed.
Therefore, I ask your permission
to allow Hongyan to inherit Duke Guo's bloodline.
Queen Mother, how thoughtful of you. Of course I will allow it.
When Hongyan is grown, I will confer him as an honorable Duke,
and he will live a glorious life.
He is your own brother.
I am already aged. Of course, I must rely on you to take care of him.
You always have my interest at heart. I am overwhelmed with gratitude.
Only when I have done my utmost to care for you,
may I return the favor of your nurture and support.
Between mother and son no such words are needed.
The affairs of state are pressing. You should return to Yangxin Hall early.
In that case, I must leave. I will pay my respects to you another day.
Your Highness,
are you trying to protect the Sixth Prince?
Parents love their children immeasurably.
Of course they plan far into the future for them.
The Emperor is not my biological son.
Only if Hongyan is made heir to a branch that may never succeed to the throne,
will he be able to live a peaceful life.
For the Sixth Prince, that is a good arrangement as well.
While Duke Guo lived,
Hongyan could not call him Father.
Now that he is dead, his son will remain bound to him.
Jinxi,
I am weary.
Help me to sleep for a while.
Members of the palace come and go, live and die.
They likely number more than thousands. They have never lived in tranquility.
I have never regretted my past actions.
Even I made use of my own child's death to frame Empress Wenyu.
Because it was my only way forward.
Yet at my first misstep,
I would become a lonely ghost trampled underfoot by the others.
And I have never worried about my life coming to an end.
Since Marquess Guo and I were separated by life and death,
there is nothing in this world I am reluctant to leave behind.
There is so much I want to tell him.
I await that day with eager anticipation.