Empresses in the Palace
Episode 4
I bow before the Empress Dowager.
His Majesty sends you a prayer bracelet of agilawood, offered in tribute.
Its fragrance soothes the nerves and eases the mind, a fine treasure indeed.
This Buddhist prayer bracelet calls Ganlu Temple to mind.
Who would expect a spiritual temple to be involved in worldly affairs?
It is merely another venue for the contest of powers.
I suffered greatly there.
Yet, "In misfortune lies the seed of happiness."
Those days at Ganlu Temple,
were the happiest of my life.
How is Mei's wound?
Much improved, my lady.
Lady Hui's wound was slow in healing,
but she had fully recovered before summer arrived.
Only a pale scar remains.
A scar? Did she not use the balm?
Something was put in the balm.
Musk.
There was musk in the balm, wasn't there?
Yes, my lady.
The balm contained a fair amount of musk.
If musk is absorbed into the skin through a wound,
the abortive effect is the same as if it were directly ingested.
Moreover, the balm has a rich floral fragrance
designed to conceal the smell of the musk.
Only an expert in fragrances could have mixed it.
- Young mistress! - My lady!
My lady, are you ill?
Human nature sickens me more.
Does Mei know this?
I dare not speak of it lightly.
She must know nothing of this.
If An Lingrong is truly behind this, she is masterful in her guile.
I find myself in desperate straits while Mei is alone and powerless.
Be sure to tell Mei
not to fall afoul of the Empress and An Lingrong.
GOOD FORTUNE
Your Highness, Concubine Huan is bleeding profusely.
The child may come too soon.
Caiyue, hurry! Send for a sedan chair. I must go to Suiyu Pavilion.
- Yes, my lady. - Do not go.
I must. Huan is in labor. I must be at her side.
Now is not the time.
His Majesty must see that Concubine Huan risks her life for his child.
Then she will always be present in His Majesty's thoughts.
Only in this way can Concubine Huan regain His Majesty's favor.
Then I will request his presence.
Mei, His Majesty must go of his own accord.
With all your strength, my lady!
The head can be seen.
Push, my lady!
- My lady, push! - Push harder!
The head can be seen. My lady, push!
- Harder, my lady! - With all your strength!
Your Majesty, please do not worry.
At last!
Your Majesty, the baby is born.
Congratulations, Your Majesty! It is a princess.
Congratulations, Your Majesty!
A princess is good, too.
We will visit Concubine Huan.
Your Majesty, you are beaming. She is not even your first princess.
Only a princess. Nothing to be delighted about.
Your Majesty, you cannot hide the smile on your face.
- You may rise. - Thank you, Your Majesty.
Concubine Huan.
You have given me a princess.
Are you still angry with me?
If you wish, I can issue an imperial decree tomorrow
to grant you the rank of Consort.
Your Majesty, do you still believe we can return to the way it was?
I have spoiled you indeed.
With such a disposition, you are not fit to stay in the palace.
Calm your mind at the temple. You cannot live here any longer.
As a person of ill omen,
I dare not disturb the peace of the palace.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
You shall leave soon. Do not stay in the palace any longer.
My lady.
Young mistress.
I have but one request to make.
Speak.
After my departure,
I hope Consort Jing will raise my princess.
If you could grant that, I would have nothing more to worry about.
Consort Duan has adopted Princess Wenyi,
and Consort Jing can be trusted.
Born in this dim moonlight,
she shall be granted the honorific name of Longyue.
All princesses are granted an honorific name after the first month of life.
Longyue is honored to be granted one shortly after birth.
Thank you for your gracious concern, Your Majesty.
Have you nothing else to tell me?
Very well. So be it.
Since you are resolved to leave,
I have nothing more to say.
Consort Jing and I will raise Longyue well.
Huan,
is this the only way out?
If I stay here even one more day,
the princess will be in greater danger.
From now on,
you will be a mother to the princess.
I entrust her to your care.
I am well aware
that you could have entrusted any other with this child,
but you have shown me compassion, for I have no child of my own.
Please leave, or I won't be able to bear losing her.
Huan, it is not all bad,
for now you are freed from this place.
As long as you remain in the palace,
you must beware of the Empress and An Lingrong.
Don't be swayed by resentment on my account.
- Be at peace and take care of yourself. - I will.
Doctor Wen, Mei has no one else.
I entrust her to you.
Do not fall into any traps.
Please take care as well, Concubine Huan.
The imperial decree says you shall not shave your hair.
You are now one of us, not a noble lady of the palace.
You must abstain from worldly life and abandon your original name.
JING'AN
You shall be of the Mo class, just as my disciples.
There is a hint of melancholy on your face,
and so you shall be called Mochou.
That is very thoughtful of you, Abbess. I accept with all my heart.
Here we are. You may tidy it up yourselves.
Please sit down, madam.
Please take a seat, mistress. I will unpack the clothes.
No need to unpack.
Merely a few changes of clothes.
Mistress, you've been given a special Buddhist name.
"Mochou" seems quite peculiar,
like the name of a young lady from a wealthy family.
The Abbess tries to warn me
that I am now a nun
and should no longer pay heed to worldly concerns.
Be quick, now!
Quickly!
Mopping the floor is torture.
You can't straighten up or raise your head.
Worse still, the main hall is enormous.
After several hours of work, you will be completely worn out.
- Jingbai always plays tricks. - Absolutely.
Jinxi, I'm fine.
It is I.
Marquess Guo!
This is no place for conversation. I would like a word with you.
Two days ago, I saw someone in the palace,
and I painted a portrait of her.
Please give me your remarks and advise me.
I am no expert in painting, how could I advise you?
This is Consort Jing.
This is Mei.
This is--
I painted it when I first saw Princess Longyue
to show goodwill as her royal uncle.
In such a short time,
Longyue has grown much.
Children always grow fast.
It is said that Princess Longyue will soon be one year old.
You are her birth mother,
so I thought you might want to know how she was.
Your painting tells me all I could ever wish to know.
Thank you for your kindness, my lord.
In front of you is Mount Piaomiao where my pavilion is located.
Each month I stay there for some 10 days.
Do inform me if you are in need of anything.
I will do all I can.
I am filled with gratitude for Longyue's portrait.
I have nothing more to ask for.
Your Majesty, the princess turns one today.
You have drunk much for this happy occasion.
Please return and rest.
I shall escort you to Yangxin Hall.
- We have reached Suiyu Pavilion. - Lady Hui will soon live here.
Lady Hui?
It was bestowed upon Lady Hui by the Empress Dowager.
In two days she will move in.
- Then I will enter. - Yes, Your Majesty.
This is her favorite rose hairpin.
Are they beautiful on me?
She did not even take the jade shoes I gifted her.
She took few belongings with her.
How did you get so ill?
With tuberculosis, Mochou must not stay in Ganlu Temple.
JINGBAI
- Absolutely. - Enough.
I know how you have been torturing her little by little.
Is she truly unbearable?
Mochou has been coughing for over half a month.
She is so emaciated that her face reddens when she coughs.
MOYAN
It is probably incurable. We must not live with her.
- Absolutely. - We must not live with her.
Mochou,
you are gravely ill now,
and they are reluctant to be near you.
It is best that you move out.
Abbess, you do know I have nowhere to turn.
Where could I go?
Abbess, you fail to uphold justice, and merely listen to the nuns' nonsense.
How gullible you are!
Silence!
How dare you fault the Abbess!
You need not hit her. You are so domineering!
Abbess, we do not know yet whether our lady has tuberculosis,
but now she is very ill and weak, and it is bitterly cold outside,
where can we go in the meantime?
Please bear with us for a few more days.
She is sickly. How can we live with her?
If Mochou stays in Ganlu Temple, we will all leave.
- You are right. - Yes.
If Ganlu Temple cannot shelter us, we shall leave.
There are some monastic dwellings at Mount Lingyun.
You shall stay there and be exempted from your devotions.
Remain there until you have recovered.
Thank you, Abbess.
No one desires to stay in such a place.
I will help you pack up and escort you there.
Mistress!
- Madam! - What should we do now?
It's impossible to reach Mount Lingyun in such heavy snow.
We can't return to Ganlu Temple, either.
There is still one place to go.
Huanbi, his pavilion is not far.
We must fetch him.
Go quickly!
Mistress! What should we do?
Huanbi has been gone for quite some time.
Will this individual you've sent for come or not?
We must try our luck.
If we truly have nowhere to go, and madam cannot be saved,
we will stay with her until the end.
My lord!
- Have you sent for Doctor Wen? - Yes, sir.
I insisted that Doctor Wen come to treat you, sir.
But he has difficulty coming here because of the heavy snow.
He must!
We do not have much medicine here, and she has quite a fever.
If it lasts much longer, it can be deadly.
Quickly!
Huanbi, you have been bustling around.
You must rest, or you will exhaust yourself.
- But mistress-- - We will take care of her.
If you wear yourself out, how can you look after her?
- Ah Jin, show Huanbi to her room. - Yes, sir.
Huanbi, please come with me.
Thank you for your help, my lord.
Continue.
I will attend to her. You may all leave.
Yes, my lord.
Dreams are vague the past, shrouded in mist
In the beauty of autumn and spring
I long for you endlessly to be eternally faithful
But only the zither and the flute remain
We are meant for each other
Our souls remain together
Forget me not, betray me not
My lord, this is madness!
I would gladly go mad if I could bring down her fever.
Keep watch outside the room and say nothing of this.
Fate has grieved us
Our true love has after all
Drifted away like fallen leaves
I hope for the rising moon and the morning sun
For the caress of the warm spring breeze
Like a pair of phoenixes we shall wing our ways
Far away without a trace
Soft rain rustles the leaves of the wutong tree
Memories blown away on the wind
Mistress, you have come to.
Doctor Wen, come! She is awake.
She is much better indeed.
Then we should make haste to return.
You have not fully recovered. Please rest to regain your strength.
This is the ideal place to recuperate for we have few visitors here.
His Lordship seems unwell.
You must examine him.
Please rest well while I examine His Lordship.
His Lordship has always been in good health.
A cold shall not matter.
- He merely needs some rest. - Thank you, Doctor.
Ah Jin, how is His Lordship?
He has a violent cold. He has had nothing but medicine,
and thus has lost much weight.
How did he fall ill without reason?
You may all leave. I shall have a word with Ah Jin.
Yes, mistress.
His Lordship is foolish,
falling for someone he cannot have and acting rashly.
Madam, you were feverish and cold towels were of no use.
Then His Lordship decided to lie in the snow in solely his undershirt.
After his body became stone-cold, he embraced you, madam.
He did this several times until your fever finally dropped.
Even a body strong as iron cannot bear this hardship.
Still, please do not worry, madam.
His Lordship never did anything inappropriate.
You were neatly dressed.
It is not the first time His Lordship has acted foolishly.
Ever since he saved you at Yikun Palace,
I have known that he is hopelessly in love.
The snow has melted.
We have troubled His Lordship for days.
Tomorrow we will set out
for the monastic dwelling at Mount Lingyun.
I am thankful for His Lordship's hospitality.
A cat!
Jinxi, chase it out!
The mistress is frightened of cats as she was injured by one before.
Mistress!
Don't be scared. I have chased out the cat.
My lord.
How could you keep birds?
While there are no wild predators here, there are many feral cats.
They live on birds.
Fortunately, no one was hurt.
It is Doctor Wen's fault.
He brought the birds to amuse my lady, but only feral cats were attracted.
Thank you, my lord, for saving us.
Yet it is quite late at night.
For what reason are you here?
These days you could not sleep until the dead of night.
No wonder you look pale.
You have been here all the while.
I merely intend to wait until you are asleep.
I was asleep just now, yet still you remained nearby.
I was simply enjoying the moonlight.
I dozed off and was caught off-guard. I am sorry you were startled.
Please return and sleep, my lord. It is quite late at night.
Sleep at ease, my lady. I--
I shall leave.
His Lordship is playing the flute again.
Is he?
Only His Lordship's music can be of such emotion and richness.
I wonder how long he will play tonight.
Mistress, can you still hear the sound of the flute outside?
Yes, I can.
Poor soul, it's starting to rain.
He may fall ill.
Please leave the shadows behind you, madam.
If you trouble your head over nothing,
you only torture yourself and His Lordship.
I have observed everything these past days.
His love is profound and pure. You can glide through life at his side.
Allow me to say,
no one can foretell the future.
It is best to follow your heart and pursue happiness in life.
It is not worth securing the future
at the expense of present wellness.
Huan, is it you?
Yes.
Here I am.
Su Peisheng, where are we?
Your Majesty, this is Baijun Garden,
designated training ground for fine horses offered in tribute.
His Majesty the Emperor!
May good fortune be with you, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty--
YE LANYI
Eunuch Duan.
Eunuch Su.
Who is that lady on horseback?
She is a horse trainer of Baijun Garden, named Ye Lanyi.
A horse trainer.
Young mistress, you have come to receive the imperial decree at last.
Say what you must.
It has been issued.
Young mistress, you must kneel to receive the decree.
"By the Grace of Heaven, the Emperor hereby decrees
that Miss Ye of Yuanming Palace is bright and elegant.
Ranked as Second Attendant, she shall move into the palace."
Issued by His Imperial Majesty.
Young mistress, you should show your gratitude.
I thank His Majesty.
Congratulations, young mistress. You are truly fortunate.
Maidens of the Imperial Palace are usually ranked Female Attendant first.
But you have bypassed that and become Second Attendant.
Then accept this good fortune in my place.
Young mistress, you cannot be serious.
I can wait for him no longer, and I promised to show him my skills.
Mistress, who is it that you mention?
It is not your concern.
Upheavals led by an official named Napodpa have taken place in Tibet.
Now he's turning to the Dzungar Mongols.
I've sent an Imperial Resident to Tibet,
and I've been preparing to make war on the Dzungar Mongols,
but many things remain unclear.
You shall travel to Yunnan and Tibet to investigate.
I appreciate your trust, Your Majesty, but I'm afraid I am incapable.
You're barely involved in imperial affairs.
If you travel incognito,
it'll be easier to investigate, as no one recognizes you.
You're the best person for this mission.
I shall spare no effort.
Are you leaving tomorrow?
I must go for the sake of the country, Huan.
Tarry not for the spring blossoms and return with haste,
for I will be waiting here for you.
For this reason,
I will hurry back to you just as a flying arrow.
I have everything arranged.
Upon my return, I will take you away from this place.
Is that true?
I bow before Your Highness, and all the young mistresses.
You may rise.
You have been here for some time, but I have yet to meet you.
I had to invite you over to gather with the other concubines.
His Majesty knows well my cold character and my distaste for social activities,
so I am exempt from the formal salutation.
His Majesty is surely generous,
but how could you fail to pay respect to Her Highness,
who leads the Imperial Harem?
If I respect her with all my heart, daily greeting may not be necessary.
Besides, any one of the ladies here could be playing a double game.
You--
Your Highness, what insolence!
Your Highness, if you have no other commands,
I shall consider my duty fulfilled.
I will excuse myself now.
Your Highness, you see, she--
She has done nothing wrong. Why do you take offense?
Concubine Huan was arrogant, having won His Majesty's favor.
That I can comprehend.
But Second Attendant Ye was a low-ranking servant before.
How dare she speak in such a manner to Your Highness!
Having won His Majesty's favor, she will bear a prince soon enough.
Concubine Qi was right.
If only she were barren.
Consider what I have told you.
It is not for my benefit,
but for the sake of an untroubled future for the Third Prince.
Madam, what is the matter?
Was it something you ate?
Could it be--
Congratulations, madam!
It has not yet been a month. Lower your voice.
Huanbi.
My child will be yours, too.
We will raise the child together, won't we?
Is it true?
The child of the mistress and His Lordship
will be mine as well.
I bow before Second Attendant Ye.
Consort Qi sends you some red-date soup.
Must I drink it?
It is an act of kindness from Consort Qi.
Why does Second Attendant Ye suffer from ceaseless stomach pain?
Your Majesty,
Second Attendant Ye had some food of an extremely cold nature
and her body has been damaged.
She may never be able to conceive a child.
Who did this? Speak!
What did she have before the stomach pain started?
Consort Qi asked Cuiguo to bring her a red-date soup.
The young mistress fell ill after drinking it.
Consort Qi?
Is it true that you did this?
Your Highness, I merely acted on your words.
My words?
Have I ever instructed you to harm others?
You are the one who planned all of this.
Merely out of benevolence, I might try to help you.
But if you cannot be saved, you have solely yourself to blame.
You are too malicious to help the Third Prince succeed to the throne.
With such a ruthless mother, he will never become the Crown Prince.
You must put an end to this.
In your stead, I shall help the Third Prince succeed to the throne.
You may choose your own course.
Consort Qi, why on earth did you end your life?
Your Majesty, Consort Qi's memorial--
She did it to escape punishment, thus she is not fit for a posthumous name.
To keep this behind closed doors, and for the sake of the Third Prince,
she shall not be held to account.
Consort Qi is dead.
Although the Third Prince has grown up, he must be looked after.
I lead the Imperial Harem,
and I have treated all children here as my own.
Moreover, I have been raising the Third Prince.
I shall devote myself to my maternal duties with all my heart.
It relieves me to hear these words.
It is most proper to entrust him to your care.
Yes, Your Majesty.
I know you are grieved,
but the imperial doctors are knowledgeable.
You may yet bear a child of your own.
Why should I grieve?
You've come to see me since I was tricked,
the same as your best friend, Concubine Huan.
Similar, yet different.
It does not matter,
it is merely one life after all.
Very well. Then rest. You shall not be disturbed.
With or without Consort Qi's red-date soup,
I have no desire to have children.
I merely felt suspicious
as the red-date soup seemed so strange.
Even my cat could smell that something was wrong.
She had every intention of killing me, so I let her fulfill her wish.
Do you truly desire to die?
I was alone, free as a bird,
but now I am locked up here until my dying day,
at the service of a man that I have no interest in.
- He has deprived me of my one chance. - What chance?
It is now of little import.
Consort Qi has helped me settle the matter.
I do not wish to bear his child at all.
Never speak such nonsense again.
May good fortune be with you, Concubine Hui and Second Attendant Ye.
An imperial decree has been issued.
"Second Attendant Ye has been wronged
and we lament her loss.
Second Attendant Ye shall be granted the rank of Noble Lady, called Ning."
Issued by His Imperial Majesty.
I thank His Majesty.
Doctor Wen, please follow me.
- Madam. - Here you are.
Please take this new medicine for pregnancy, my lady.
Have you not rested well? You look very pale.
His Lordship said he would return in 40 days,
but he has been gone 50 days and we have not received word of him.
Madam is certainly worried.
Last night she had a nightmare and could not sleep well.
Therefore, she is ashen-faced.
We must not take heed of nightmares.
He shall return soon.
He will not.
What did you say?
Marquess Guo will never return. He is dead.
Doctor Wen, you--
What nonsense is this?
How could you jinx him, the father of my child?
Have I ever in my life deceived you, Huan?
Marquess Guo did not return from his journey to Yunnan and Tibet,
and we received no news of him.
His Majesty sent men to look for him,
but it is said that the vessel he took sank,
and his body has not yet been found.
Madam!
Huan, the current of the Yellow River was so swift
that even an iron vessel was shattered.
Even if his body were found, he would not be recognizable.
He is dead.
I was not fated to see him one last time.
Huan.
Huan, come to your senses. The dead will never return to life.
The dead will never return to life.
His soul has never entered my dreams.
- Huan! - Madam!
Huan!
Huan.
Impossible.
It is impossible.
It cannot be.
Madam, if you refuse to eat, please at least take this medicine.
I requested Doctor Wen to prescribe this medicine for you.
It is very effective.
The unborn child will certainly die.
Please take it, madam.
You must not take it, mistress!
You must keep this baby, the sole kin of His Lordship.
The child must not be aborted.
Jinxi,
I will not take the medicine that causes miscarriage.
I want this baby.
Yunli is dead.
No one else will protect me as he has.
I must learn to protect myself
and those I care for.
Madam, the old Zhen Huan that I knew has returned.
I must not die.
For the sake of my unborn child
and of Yunli who has died for nothing,
I must live,
and live well.
What do you intend to do, madam?
Royal status
must be acquired for this child.
Yunli once told me
that His Majesty uttered my name in his sleep.
I am not absolutely certain of success,
but I must do all I can.
We shall return to the palace.
Jinxi?
You have come.
- You there! - Yes, sir.
Replace the tea leaves with those given by His Majesty.
Please drink mine.
Thank you, Eunuch Su.
No need to be so courteous. Call me by my name.
Peisheng.
Please sit.
The residence has been refurbished. Is it comfortable?
Well enough, but it seems empty, as I live here alone.
After all these years, I am already well used to it.
Then,
it is too late for me
to accompany you.
What happened?
At last you consent to live with me.
Your legs must ache after a long day's work.
Life is full of twists and turns indeed.
Some people are meant to be together.
But I pity Concubine Huan.
There will be no one left to take care of her.
I pity her in earnest.
Are you suggesting that Concubine Wan and His Majesty--
Can you be sure of helping them?
If the love between Concubine Wan and His Majesty is revived,
we may be together as a matter of course.
- I greet Your Majesty. - You may rise.
- I thank Your Majesty. - I've just visited the Queen Mother.
She still looks quite pale.
I was told that you have been looking after her.
It is my filial duty.
You may rise.
Your Majesty, what a fine day.
Even Concubine Hui and the princess came out to enjoy the spring weather.
Indeed.
In a few days, it will be the Spring Dragon Festival.
Traditionally, you make an excursion and pray for good fortune.
Will you be praying for good fortune at Baohua Temple, Your Majesty?
I shall spare myself the trouble and read memoranda in Yangxin Hall.
The Spring Dragon Festival is of great significance, Your Majesty.
It is said, "when the dragon raises its head,
abundant harvests of crops are promised ahead."
It is the moment to pray for a year of prosperity and peace.
If you make an excursion
and pray for good fortune on the same day,
I can think of the perfect place.
As I child, I remember taking a spring walk at Mount Lingyun,
where stunning views may be seen.
Then we may pray for good fortune at Ganlu Temple,
perfect for spending the day.
Concubine Hui is quite knowledgeable. That is the place I wished to mention.
Now is the time to enjoy the beautiful scenery at Ganlu Temple,
pleasant for a tranquil stroll.
Besides, no idlers will be near as it belongs to the Imperial Palace.
Ganlu Temple.
Your Majesty, please have some tea.
Where is Concubine Wan?
Your Majesty,
she fell ill and moved to a monastic dwelling at Mount Lingyun.
She was ill?
For how long? Was it serious?
Concubine Wan should have recovered by now.
Nonsense!
What are you suggesting?
How could the Abbess not know?
Forgive me, Your Majesty!
It has been a great honor to have Concubine Wan study Buddhism with us.
Yes, sir.
She has great compassion,
offering to wash clothes, chop firewood
and shoulder buckets of water for the old and weak at the temple.
Did she truly perform all of those tasks?
Yes, Your Majesty.
Madam, you didn't sleep well yet again. You had better--
Your Majesty!
"Your Majesty"?
How could His Majesty come here?
Madam, it truly is His Majesty. I deceive you not.
Huan Huan.
The nuns of Ganlu Temple say you moved here because of your illness
and have recovered already.
But you seem to me quite sickly.
Your Majesty,
during the month of convalescence after giving birth,
her body was not well cared for, causing her ill health.
At first we were told she would recover by spring.
Yet since her departure, she has longed for Your Majesty and the princess.
She often falls into a trance, unable to sleep for nights on end.
For this reason she has never recovered fully.
Madam, Eunuch Su has come.
I bow before the Consort.
- No need to be so formal. Please sit. - Thank you, my lady.
Huanbi, serve tea.
It is no fine tea, but it has quite a delicate fragrance.
Thank you, my lady.
My lady, what is the matter?
She has felt sick for some days.
Congratulations, my lady!
You are the first to know after Jinxi and Huanbi.
I see.
Please forgive my curiosity.
How long has it been, my lady?
Barely over a month.
Wasn't that exactly when His Majesty first came to Mount Lingyun?
I must congratulate you again, my lady.
This conception comes at the best moment.
It will now be appropriate for you to return to the palace.
A rejected concubine cannot return to the palace.
I merely wish for this child to grow up safe and well.
Why do you say this, my lady?
Your child is of royal blood.
His name must be put in the genealogy of the royal family.
Besides, His Majesty thinks much of his descendants.
He will cherish the child.
Should His Majesty grant my unborn child royal status,
I would be most grateful, even were I to return as Second Attendant.
My lady and the royal child are of utmost importance.
I will tell His Majesty.
You must make haste, and tell no one of this.
Madam remains outside the palace.
If it is known that she carries a child, who knows what chaos would ensue.
I understand the importance. Take good care of your mistress.
As soon as I return, I shall tell His Majesty
that Doctor Wen must attend to the pregnancy of Her Highness.
- Is it true that Zhen Huan is pregnant? - Absolutely.
Doctor Wen prepared pregnancy medicine at the Imperial Medical Bureau.
But no young mistress here is pregnant.
The only one Doctor Wen would care for resides at Mount Lingyun.
No matter how hard we tried, we have failed to prevent this from happening.
It would be easier if she did not carry a child.
Now it is another matter.
Everything is well arranged at the palace. Soon my lady can return.
His Majesty will grant you the title of Consort Xi.
You shall live at Yongshou Palace.
He also requested that you raise the Fourth Prince.
- The Fourth Prince? - Yes, my lady.
You were rejected, my lady. There is a great stir about your return.
To avoid suspicion, His Majesty grants you the noble surname Niohuru,
and states that you are the birth mother of the Fourth Prince.
Ten years have been added to your age. You are now 32, my lady.
Truly? How could madam seem 32?
Of course not.
It is to prevent further rumors.
It is unimportant.
It is good that His Majesty has arranged it so.
Queen Mother, I wish to bring Zhen Huan back to the palace soon.
I merely need to appoint a Conferring Emissary.
She should now be three months along.
It is time for her to be looked after in the palace.
Your Majesty, he has returned!
Calm yourself and speak clearly.
Who has returned?
Huan!
My lord!
Huan, have you waited for me?
This is a joyous day for my lady.
Clothing moist with tears is an ill omen.
Go change into something more festive.
His Lordship has returned safe and sound. I must burn incense to thank the Buddha.
The imperial edict has been issued. It is irreversible.
If you are swayed by emotion,
endless troubles await us in the future.
"My lady"?
I did not expect...
to see you return alive and well in this lifetime, my lord.
"My lord"?
We were parted for merely four months, but all has changed swiftly.
You are called "my lady" again.
I have not heard these titles for so long. They sound strange to me.
I am glad you have returned.
I wish I had died out there and never returned!
Huan,
if it were not for you, I would not have survived!
But I have returned
only to find that you are to return to the palace, into His Majesty's embrace.
If you had not returned,
you would have thought I was waiting for you.
you would not have known I am such a heartless soul!
Heartless?
Heartless!
I have done you wrong, my lord. It will do no good to say more.
Please leave, my lord.
I am glad you have returned.
God has indeed blessed our empire.
I could not have survived without your blessing, Your Majesty.
You have returned at the right moment.
I was not sure who to appoint for a happy occasion.
I am at your command.
I desire to bring Consort Xi back to the palace,
who was known as Concubine Wan.
She was once rejected but will now return to the palace.
It has given rise to a flurry of discussion.
I intend to appoint a respectable person of high position as Conferring Emissary
to escort Consort Xi back to the palace.
Yet other, older imperial brothers have declined,
so you are the sole one I can rely on.
If I am to be the emissary, will it bring more honor to Consort Xi?
Were it not so, I would not appoint you.
I understand.
Seeing you here safe, I may now return to the palace without worries.
You came merely to say this?
What did you expect, my lord?
We were parted for so many days yet you do not even ask what befell me.
Does it matter?
That day my vessel sank in the Yellow River,
everything was washed away!
Were I not an accomplished swimmer, my body would remain submerged even now.
I reached the shore with great difficulty,
but was ambushed by Dzungar spies.
I was being taken from Longnan to Dzungaria,
but I took my chances and seized one of the horses.
I knew you would be worried, so I traveled day and night to see you.
You came too late!
Yunli,
love is not the only treasure
in the entire world.
The imperial edict has been issued.
If we fail to execute it, every person near to us will be punished.
We cannot be so selfish as to sacrifice them for our happiness.
You cannot do it, nor can I.
In this vast world,
there is no place for you and me.
We have no choice.
Consort Xi returns!
"By the Grace of Heaven, the Emperor decrees
that the liveliness of the Imperial Palace endures
by virtue of the good and the beautiful.
Niohuru Zhen Huan,
a well-born lady of benevolence and many virtues,
is now conferred as Consort Xi
in accord with the Empress Dowager's order."
Issued by His Imperial Majesty.
It is now four months?
Yes, Your Highness.
The Emperor is growing old,
but he has fewer men of true loyalty near to him.
Since you have returned,
you shall counsel him.
He will certainly listen to you.
I shall abide by your words, Your Highness.
Very well.
You are like a sister to Consort Xi. She will have her second child.
You should hasten to have your own.
I thought highly of you,
but you do not devote yourself to the Emperor.
I used to think you calm and graceful,
but after all that has transpired,
at last I realize you are proud.
I understand
that all these years you have resented me.
I dare not, Your Majesty.
You are not speaking your mind.
Be honest with me.
Since the departure of Consort Xi,
you have resided in Suiyu Pavilion to avoid me.
Am I right?
You have treated me with coldness,
and I have done the same to you.
Come to think of it,
if it were not for Consort Hua,
I would have treated you the same way
as I treat Consort Xi.
Your Highness, at last His Majesty is passing the night with Concubine Hui.
Concubine Hui is thoughtful and kind,
but His Majesty has ignored her all this time.
Send a pot of passion wine to their room
as a gift on my behalf.
Yes, Your Highness.
The Empress Dowager knows that His Majesty is with Concubine Hui.
SUN ZHUXI
Pleased at heart, she sends you a pot of wine.
The Queen Mother still thinks of sending wine so late at night.
What wine is this?
His Majesty and Concubine Hui are deeply in love.
It must be passion wine for conjugal bliss.
I am grateful for the Queen Mother's concern.
I will excuse myself now.
If we were truly in love,
we would not need this wine.
We still have a long way ahead.
I will visit you again when there is no longer any doubt in your mind.
I will return to Yangxin Hall.
His Majesty departs!
Your Majesty!
Hold on to His Majesty!
My heart has withered.
What good can such heartfelt words do me?
See,
even the Empress Dowager knows
that without this passion wine,
nothing will ever take place between us.
What of my feelings?
My own feelings.
Does he know them?
Even if he did,
he would never care about me.
Wen Shichu!
Shichu!
Young mistress, you are drunk. Please cease drinking.
What is the use of restraint?
Can I not indulge myself for once?
Wen Shichu!
I will send for Doctor Wen at once to help you sober up, my lady.
Master Wen, you are still packing medicine for Consort Xi at this late hour.
This is not for Consort Xi.
Concubine Hui always loses her appetite in summer.
WEI LIN
This medicine is to whet her appetite.
- Have you written everything down? - Yes, sir.
Doctor Wen, Caiyue requests that you visit Suiyu Pavilion immediately.
Concubine Hui has drunk too much and needs medicine to sober up.
I shall go at once.
My lady, why have you drunk so much?
You are here.
It is harmful to your health.
Concubine Hui, why do you make yourself suffer?
Concubine Hui!
Do I not have my own name?
I--
Please do not say such things.
Sit down.
Yes, my lady.
I have a pot of good wine here.
Have some.
My lady, I dare not.
I did not know I had no one to drink and talk with.
My lady,
I will do as you command.
It is said that drinking is pleasurable,
but I still feel lonely after drinking.
Aside from Huan,
I have no one else.
Please do not speak like this, my lady. I know you are distressed.
Please tell me everything.
I will listen to you.
Are we not the same?
We ignore our own feelings in order to protect those we love.
You and I,
are we not the same?
You and I are true companions, my lady.
We are true companions.
My lady!
What is the matter?
My lady.
The flowers of the silk tree are beautiful.
However beautiful they are,
in this heavy rain,
they are doomed to fall.
My lady, please step back. It is frigid here.
Who is that?
Invite her to take shelter from the rain.
I will have a look, my lady.
Lady Ning.
My lady invites you to take shelter from the rain.
Come.
My lady, it is Lady Ning.
- May blessings be with you, Consort Xi. - You are soaked. Jinxi, get her a coat.
My lady, take care.
You are fond of silk tree flowers.
I will ask the servants to put a cloth under that tree.
When the rain stops and the water drains, the petals will be sent to your residence.
- You need not be exposed to the rain. - Thank you, my lady.
You are a Noble Lady. Why are there no servants with you?
When the rain ceases, shall I escort you?
No other concubine ever wishes to enter Chunxi Hall.
Why do you wish to visit my humble residence?
Am I not welcome, Lady Ning?
I bow before Consort Xi.
Please sit, my lady.
Your cat is well trained, Lady Ning.
There is nothing special about this clumsy cat.
Where is Tuanrong?
The cat is calm and gentle.
And most intelligent.
She rarely makes a noise,
but when she does,
she can draw all the cats in the neighborhood here.
Are you afraid of cats, my lady?
No.
I am merely curious how one tames such an intelligent animal.
Before I became a horse trainer, I used to be an animal trainer.
It took no effort to tame this one.
For what reason did you send for me, young mistress?
A question troubles my mind.
Please feel my pulse and tell me the answer.
Yes, my lady.
Young mistress!
My dream seems to have come true.
Could it be from what happened that night?
You need not warn me of guilt by association.
This is my child.
I will keep him safe whether it means my life or death.
Shichu, please help me.
Do not turn this dream into a nightmare.
Are you certain that His Majesty exits the imperial counsel at this hour?
Yes, I am certain of it, my lady.
Then search intently for my lost bracelet.
What are you searching for at such an early hour?
I bow before Your Majesty.
I discovered that my bracelet was missing.
It would not matter
were it not the one Your Majesty gave to me in my first year here.
I am loath to give it up.
- Su Peisheng. - Yes, sir.
- Help search for it. - Yes, Your Majesty.
You seldom wear dresses of such delicate color.
Delicate but not coquettish. You do look lovely.
This dress is blessed to have found favor with you.
Your Majesty, the bracelet has been found.
Do not go searching if it is lost again. We have many in the storehouse.
The bracelet can be lost, but not the affection.
I have prepared your favorite tea in Suiyu Pavilion.
Would you care for some?
How can I refuse your invitation?
And pigs may well fly!
Your Majesty, the plum soup looks appetizing.
- Please ask Consort Xi to give me some. - I know you enjoy wine.
Su Peisheng, fill the cup of Concubine Hui.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, I should not drink for I am with child.
When did this happen? How many months has it been?
I felt ill yesterday,
so I sent for Doctor Wen and was told of my two-month pregnancy.
That is correct. It has been two months.
The chrysanthemums have blossomed very early this summer.
I was worried it was an ill omen,
but it turns out to be a good one.
Huan and Mei are now pregnant.
Such a joyous coincidence has never happened before.
How is the Empress?
She should soon recover from her severe headaches.
If she recovers, I will face endless troubles.
All suppose I am eight months pregnant.
We must prepare for the last resort.
Do not worry, my lady. Everything is well prepared.
I will soon be in labor,
but Concubine Hui is far from stable with her three-month pregnancy.
Please take particular care of Concubine Hui and her child.
I shall spare no effort and pass through fire and water for them.
I am late.
- Please forgive me, Your Majesty. - Be at ease for this family feast. Sit.
I greet Concubine Hui. I have not yet congratulated you.
Thank you, my lord.
I greet Consort Xi.
My respects, my lord.
You will be in labor soon. Are you in good health, my lady?
I am well. Thank you for your concern, my lord.
Your Majesty, Consort Xi must take her medication.
Make haste then.
I shall return shortly.
Are you all right, young mistress?
I thought I could restrain my affection and forget him,
but I almost lost control.
I do understand the pain you and His Lordship bear, young mistress.
Are you well?
As I told you at the feast, all is well.
But now it is different. Only the two of us are here.
I wish to hear you say it again with all your heart.
- Huanbi, we must leave. - Do not go!
Let me go.
Let me go!
I feel that you are not at all living a happy life
though Yongshou Palace glitters like gold.
Whether a golden palace or a thatched cottage,
I chose it of my own accord.
My lord,
please do not be grieved over a person who is undeserving of your affection.
If we delay any longer, His Majesty will be alarmed.
Take good care of yourself.
And you.
To avoid suspicion, I shall return first.
Then wait a while and come in after me.
Who's there?
Huanbi, what is it?
I saw a shadow there, my lady.
Where have these cats come from? Protect Consort Xi!
Cats! Hurry!
Hurry!
Mistress, are you hurt?
It hurts!
What should we do?
Push, my lady, with all your strength!
Push hard, my lady!
Hurry to see if the labor medicine is ready.
Remember it must be thick for Consort Xi to take.
Yes, Doctor.
My lady, I must ask you a question.
Should an accident occur, do you wish to save yourself or the baby?
Wen Shichu, we are lifelong friends.
You must promise me
not to hurt my child,
cost what it may.
Do you hear me?
Don't even think about it!
I told you that Consort Xi and her child must both be safe,
or the entire Medical Bureau shall be buried with them!
I have had enough punishment. Another child of mine must not be lost.
The young mistress is awake.
My child.
Where is my child?
The wet nurse is feeding them. They shall return soon, my lady.
They are boy-girl twins.
Huan Huan, you have given me a dragon and a phoenix of good fortune.
Did Mei come?
And where is Doctor Wen?
Concubine Hui cannot visit you for her pregnancy. I asked her to rest.
Doctor Wen is directing the others to prepare medicine in the back.
Huan Huan, you have given me two children at once,
a praiseworthy accomplishment.
I grant you the title of Noble Consort,
and you shall be my favorite of all.
In my heart, no one deserves this title except for you.
Why do you shiver so suddenly? Are you cold?
Feiwen, she just gave birth. How could you open the windows?
She might catch cold. Close them now!
Your Majesty, the midwife said the hall smelled of blood,
so I left the windows open at her request.
How dare you retort after a misdeed! Slap her in the face 20 times.
Yes, Your Majesty.
- Su Peisheng! - Yes, sir.
Issue a decree to the Imperial Harem.
Consort Xi of Yongshou Palace is promoted to Noble Consort Xi.
The conferring ceremony will be held on the day the Prince turns one month old.
Yes, Your Majesty.
His Majesty is listening inside.
Do it yourself. I might hit you too hard.
Eunuch Yun, you heard as well. It is truly not my fault.
I merely did as I was told.
His Majesty vents his anger out of concern for Noble Consort Xi.
Do not take it to heart.
His Majesty should not do that simply out of his love for her.
Mind your words! If His Majesty hears, you shall be punished more severely.
I bid farewell to Your Highness.
What happened to your face?
I was at fault.
Feiwen, where are you going?
Huanbi ordered me to fetch provisions from the Imperial Household Department.
I am heading there too. Shall we go together?
I was already a Noble Consort at that time,
in a lofty position,
having won His Majesty's highest favor.
I had nothing to worry about.
Little did I know that the worst was yet to come.
Empress Wenyu is truly hateful, fearful and pitiful.
She would never let slip away the chance to drag another down.